<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 18:08:20 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 17 - He will strengthen us</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-17-strength.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>Consider how the Lord provided for Nephi and his people</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And so great were the blessings of the Lord upon us, that while we did live upon raw meat in the wilderness, our women did give plenty of suck for their children, and were strong, yea, even like unto the men; and they began to bear their journeyings without murmurings.<br>
And thus we see that the commandments of God must be fulfilled. And if it so be that the children of men keep the commandments of God he <strong>doth nourish them, and strengthen them</strong>, and provide means whereby they can accomplish the thing which he has commanded them; wherefore, he did provide means for us while we did sojourn in the wilderness. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-17.2-3">1 Nephi 17.2–3</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-1-nephi-17-journey-in-wilderness.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Journeying"> # Meaning</p>
<p>The Lord intends to strengthen me to overcome the trials ahead, not to take them away. The purpose of the life is to be strengthen. Whenever we feel overwhelmed, we can take those things to the Lord.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>strength</category>
  <category>trust in the Lord</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-17-strength.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 18:08:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 18.3</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-18.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And I, Nephi, did go into the mount oft, and I did pray oft unto the Lord; wherefore the Lord showed unto me great things.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>See <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/1-ne/18?id=p3&amp;lang=eng#p3">1 Nephi 18.3</a></p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>favorite scriptures</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-18.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 16 - Christ Guides us in Unique Ways</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-16-christ-guides-us.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Lehi had a humbling experience as he was complaining at how hard the journey was:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass that the voice of the Lord came unto my father; and he was truly chastened because of his murmuring against the Lord, insomuch that he was brought down into the depths of sorrow. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-16.25">1 Nephi 16.25</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>When the Lord chastened Lehi, he pointed Lehi to the Liahona for next steps:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass that the voice of the Lord said unto him: Look upon the ball, and behold the things which are written. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-16.26">1 Nephi 16.26</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Lord was <em>already</em> speaking to Lehi, so why did he tell Lehi to look at the Liahona? Why not just tell him what next to do?</p>
<p>An interesting thing happened with the Brother of Jared as well:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass at the end of four years that the Lord came again unto the brother of Jared, and stood in a cloud and talked with him. <strong>And for the space of three hours did the Lord talk with the brother of Jared, and chastened him because he remembered not to call upon the name of the Lord.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/ether-2.14">Ether 2.14</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-christ-standing-brother-of-jared.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Christ standing with the Brother of Jared in a cloud</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In this case, the Lord just told him the next steps: “Go to work and build, after the manner of barges which ye have hitherto built.” (<a href="../scriptures/ether-2.16">Ether 2.16</a>)</p>
<p>Why did Lehi get a compass, and the Jaredites not? Why did the Lord point Lehi to get his answers from the compass, but just told brother of Jared what next to do?</p>
<p>Well, I’m sure it’s not so black and white. But the fact that there <em>is</em> a <em>black</em> and a <em>white</em> way in which the Lord teaches us is my point.</p>
<p>Sometimes the Lord tells us what to do (black). Sometimes he reminds us of the things he’s already given us (white). He reminds us of words from the scriptures. He reminds us of past prayers. He reminds us to pray.</p>
<p>And if we look more closely, we actually <em>do</em> see a similarity between Brother of Jared and Lehi because they “built barges after the manner which they <strong>had</strong> built, according to the instructions of the Lord.” (<a href="../scriptures/ether-2.16">Ether 2.16</a>)</p>
<p>Meaning: they already had the answer and the Lord just had to remind them.</p>
<p>Meaning: their liahona was the fact that they already had directions from the Lord.</p>
<p>Let’s go back a little. Earlier in Jaredite journey, they were being very deliberately lead by the Lord:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass that the Lord commanded them that they should go forth into the wilderness, yea, into that quarter where there never had man been. And it came to pass that the Lord did go before them, and did talk with them as he stood in a cloud, and <strong>gave directions whither they should travel.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/ether-2.5">Ether 2.5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Not only that, but the Lord gave them instructions on how to build a barge:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass that they did travel in the wilderness, and <strong>did build barges</strong>, in which <strong>they did cross many waters, being directed continually by the hand of the Lord.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/ether-2.6">Ether 2.6</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>So Lehi and Brother of Jared were both pointed in the direction they should go. But the Lord teaches them each in their own way. For Lehi he gives him a Liahona and tells him to read the words therein. This is a physical tool, kind of like the Book of Mormon and other scripture. We should not be surprised if sometimes the Lord tells us “go to the scriptures, I will answer your question there” or “listen to general conference”. The Lord often points us to places where He’ll speak to us, giving us opportunities to show our faith and do our part.</p>
<p>On the other hand, sometimes he may guide us by the hand and show us the way to go. He may directly just tell us to go one way. This is another way of His for interacting with us.</p>
<p>And interestingly, he later told brother of Jared “remember those barges I gave you four years ago? Rebuild more.” He didn’t necessarily give them more designs but reminded the Jaredites of how he had already guided them.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-brother-of-jared-in-cloud-with-lord.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Brother of Jared and the Lord</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There is power in remembering the things the Lord has already done for us. We shouldn’t always seek new signs. We should seek to remember. And in remembering, we’re lead anew.</p>
<section id="what-i-learned" class="level1">
<h1>What I Learned</h1>
<ol type="1">
<li>The Lord guides the same person in different ways</li>
<li>He guides two people in the same circumstance in different ways</li>
<li>He asks us to remember</li>
<li>If we’ve embarked on the journey, even if we stumble, he’ll lovingly chastise us to remember the Way</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>I take solice in that He wants to guide me personally. He may ask me to read my scriptures. He may remind me of a past time. He may give me specific instructions. He may just expect me to walk or build and do the thing I’m supposed to do. Keep going until you receive further instruction.</p>
<p>He’s also actually heavily involved in the details it seems. We may wander lost (Israelites) or be caught relaxing for four years on the beach (Jaredites), but He’s still very heavily involved. I can trust He loves me and wants to guide me.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>prayer</category>
  <category>revelation</category>
  <category>guidance</category>
  <category>hand of the Lord</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-16-christ-guides-us.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 19:53:41 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bread in the Oven</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/bread-in-the-oven.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="symbol" class="level1">
<h1>Symbol</h1>
<p>Bread is placed in an oven. Likewise His body was placed in a sepulcher. And he was in that sepulcher three days. When he came out, He was finished as a resurrected Lord.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-bread-in-oven.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Bread in the oven, like He was in the sepulchre"> # Scriptures</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For as Jonas was three days and three nights in the whale’s belly; <strong>so shall the Son of man be three days and three nights in the heart of the earth.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/matthew-12.40">Matthew 12.40</a></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And he bought fine linen, and took him down, and wrapped him in the linen, and laid him in a sepulchre which was hewn out of a rock, and rolled a stone unto the door of the sepulchre. <a href="../scriptures/mark-15.46">Mark 15.46</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>Christ prophesied he’d be in the tomb three days, and He was. He keeps His promises. The covenant of the sacrament is a promise, one I can trust. For “I, the Lord, am bound when ye do what I say; but when ye do not what I say, ye have no promise.” (<a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-82.10">Doctrine and Covenants 82.10</a>)</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>sacrament-symbols</category>
  <category>symbol-bread</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/bread-in-the-oven.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 10:37:25 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2024-01-28 Come Follow Me CTR 7 Jan 22-28 1 Nephi 11-15</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-28-jan-28-1-nephi-11-15.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="studies" class="level1">
<h1>Studies</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-11-seeing-signs-of-christ.html">1 Nephi 11 - Angel shows signs to Nephi</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-12-broad-roads.html">1 Nephi 12 - Broad Roads</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-13-publish-peace.html">1 Nephi 13 - Publish Peace</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-14-convincing-unto-peace.html">1 Nephi 14 - Convincing unto Peace</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-15-hearken-and-hold-fast.html">1 Nephi 15 - Hearken and Hold Fast</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="focus-scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Focus Scriptures</h1>
<section id="covenant-armor" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="covenant-armor">Covenant Armor</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>” And it came to pass that I, Nephi, beheld the power of the Lamb of God, that it descended upon the saints of the church of the Lamb, and upon the covenant people of the Lord, who were scattered upon all the face of the earth; <strong>and they were armed with righteousness and with the power of God in great glory.”</strong> (<a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-14.14">1 Nephi 14.14</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="protection-through-the-word-of-god" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="protection-through-the-word-of-god">Protection through the Word of God</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And they said unto me: What meaneth the rod of iron which our father saw, that led to the tree? 24 And I said unto them that it was the word of God; and whoso would hearken unto the word of God, and <strong>would hold fast unto it, they would never perish; neither could the temptations and the fiery darts of the adversary overpower them unto blindness</strong>, to lead them away to destruction. 25 Wherefore, I, Nephi, did exhort them to give heed unto the word of the Lord; yea, I did exhort them with all the energies of my soul, and with all the faculty which I possessed, that they would give heed to the word of God and remember to keep his commandments always in all things. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-15.23-25">1 Nephi 15.23–25</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="armor-of-god" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="armor-of-god">Armor of God</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>10 Finally, my brethren, be strong in the Lord, and in the power of his might. 11 Put on the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to stand against the wiles of the devil. 12 For we wrestle not against flesh and blood, but against principalities, against powers, against the rulers of the darkness of this world, against spiritual wickedness in high places. 13 Wherefore take unto you the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to withstand in the evil day, and having done all, to stand. 14 Stand therefore, having your loins girt about with truth, and having on the breastplate of righteousness; 15 And your feet shod with the preparation of the gospel of peace; 16 Above all, taking the shield of faith, wherewith ye shall be able to quench all the fiery darts of the wicked. 17 And take the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God: 18 Praying always with all prayer and supplication in the Spirit, and watching thereunto with all perseverance and supplication for all saints; <a href="../scriptures/ephesians-6.10-18">Ephesians 6.10–18</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
</section>
<section id="activity" class="level1">
<h1>Activity</h1>
<ul>
<li>Armor: Helmet. Gloves. Glasses.
<ul>
<li>Need a covenant</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Fiery Darts:
<ul>
<li>Nerf darts</li>
<li>Wrist guards</li>
<li>Get to the other side</li>
<li>Armed: nerf darts flying towards. Things at school. Mean words. Temptations to yell at my brother.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Armed with righteousness.</li>
</ul>
<p>What I want them to learn: - Armed with righteousness because of my baptismal covenant</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>come follow me lesson plan</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-28-jan-28-1-nephi-11-15.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 23:59:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bread given freely, like His life</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/bread-given-freely-like-his-life.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="symbol" class="level1">
<h1>Symbol</h1>
<p>All are welcome. Everyone. He doesn’t want a skimpy congregation. He wants it packed. The bread is offered to everyone, the way His life was.</p>
<p>Likewise, his life was freely given. Free. He had control. And He gives the sacrament freely to all who see it.</p>
</section>
<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p><em>All</em> are invited to participate in the sacrament, which is symbolic of the life He freely gave. All souls in the chapel are invited to partake of His goodness.</p>
<p>Only He could give up His life:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>A natural effect of His immortal origin, as the earth-born Son of an immortal Sire, was that He was immune to death except as He surrendered thereto. <strong>The life of Jesus the Christ could not be taken save as He willed and allowed. The power to lay down His life was inherent in Himself, as was the power to take up His slain body in an immortalized state.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/chapter-25.-jesus-again-in-jerusalem">Chapter 25. Jesus Again in Jerusalem</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Christ alone was given power by God to control the fate of his otherwise immortal body:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Therefore doth my Father love me, because I lay down my life, that I might take it again. <strong>No man taketh it from me</strong>, but I lay it down of myself. <strong>I have power to lay it down, and I have power to take it again.</strong> This commandment have I received of my Father. <a href="../scriptures/john-10.17-18">John 10.17–18</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>By similar rite, all are welcome. He is in control.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And behold, ye shall meet together oft; and ye shall not forbid any man from coming unto you when ye shall meet together, but suffer them that they may come unto you and forbid them not; <a href="../scriptures/3-nephi-18.22">3 Nephi 18.22</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>Because Christ had a choice, and not the Romans, over the timing of His death, and He chose to be taken in captivity, and He chose to walk up the hill, the Lord showed he did all that He could to offer Himself to us.</p>
<p>When I pray, I’m not praying to an unknown God. I’m praying to one who fully understands me (<a href="../sacrament-symbols/porous-bread.html">Porous Bread</a>).</p>
<p>When I pray, I can remember He’s already done His part. The only thing holding me back from feeling His love is me.</p>
<p>How can I pray in such a way to lower those barriers that I put up between Him and me ?</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>sacrament-symbols</category>
  <category>symbol-bread</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/bread-given-freely-like-his-life.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 22:22:08 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Sunday Dress Reminds me of Bringing Sacrifices to Him</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/sunday-dress.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="symbol" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Symbol</h1>
<p>We show up to take the sacrament in our Sunday best. There were many “sinners” who came and adored the Lord. A lady gave him oil and washed His feet. The widow gave two mites. The publicans prayed for forgiveness while the Pharisees judged them.</p>
<p>We give Him our best when we show up, as sinners, to offer Him a broken heart and contrite spirit.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-sunday-best.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Sunday best dress</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And one of the Pharisees desired him that he would eat with him. And he went into the Pharisee’s house, and sat down to meat. 37 And, behold, a woman in the city, which was a sinner, when she knew that Jesus sat at meat in the Pharisee’s house, brought an alabaster box of ointment, 38 And stood at his feet behind him weeping, and began to wash his feet with tears, and did wipe them with the hairs of her head, and kissed his feet, and anointed them with the ointment. <a href="../scriptures/luke-7.36-38">Luke 7.36–38</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Pharisees didn’t like that she was a sinner.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Now when the Pharisee which had bidden him saw it, he spake within himself, saying, This man, if he were a prophet, would have known who and what manner of woman this is that toucheth him: for she is a sinner. <a href="../scriptures/luke-7.39">Luke 7.39</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>We are redeemed by Him when we come with such a spirit as this woman.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Behold, he offereth himself a sacrifice for sin, to answer the ends of the law, unto all those who have a broken heart and a contrite spirit; and unto none else can the ends of the law be answered. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-2.7">2 Nephi 2.7</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>The sacrament isn’t for those who are perfect. It’s for me, a sinner. One who sins. And is sinning and doesn’t even know it. One who is separated from the happiness God would have me fully feel because of my ignorance, my natural state. I am good. I am loved. When I pray, He already knows I’m a sinner and loves me regardless. He doesn’t want me to see myself as a sinner, but as a worshipper who has much to grow from. And I am growing.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>sacrament-symbols</category>
  <category>symbol-dress</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/sunday-dress.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 10:37:26 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Broken Bread, but No Broken Bones</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/broken-bread-but-no-broken-bones.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="symbol" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Symbol</h1>
<p>We break bread, but His bones were not broken. Only His flesh.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-bread-about-to-be-torn.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Bread to be broken</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>Whenever we break the bread, I’m reminded of many things. But one that sticks out is that Christ’s legs were commanded to be broken by the Roman leaders:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The Jewish officials, who had not hesitated to slay their Lord, were horrified at the thought of men left hanging on crosses on such a day, for thereby the land would be defiled; so these scrupulous <strong>rulers went to Pilate and begged that Jesus and the two malefactors be summarily dispatched by the brutal Roman method of breaking their legs</strong>, the shock of which violent treatment had been found to be promptly fatal to the crucified. <a href="../scriptures/Jesus-the-Christ-chapter-35.-death-and-burial.html">Jesus the Christ. Chapter 35. Death and Burial</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It was a technique practiced by the Romans to hasten the death of the crucified:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Victims in the head up position could spend several days on the cross before they died. <strong>One technique used by the Romans to hasten death was to break the legs below the knee with a blunt instrument1 (p.&nbsp;25)</strong> <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1420788/#">Medical theories on the cause of death in crucifixion - PMC</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>A bit graphic, but how did this technique possibly accelerate the death?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>According to those who have studied the grim mechanics of crucifixion, in order to breathe adequately, the crucified victim periodically had to push himself up using his legs. <strong>Breaking the legs prevented him from doing that, thus hastening his death. He would suffocate.</strong> <a href="https://www.stcatherinercc.org/single-post/2018/03/14/why-are-the-crucified-persons-legs-broken">Why are the crucified persons’ legs broken?</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But Christ’s legs were <em>not</em> broken as instructed. Continuing the quote above from Jesus the Christ:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>…The governor gave his consent, and the soldiers broke the limbs of the two thieves with cudgels. <strong>Jesus, however, was found to be already dead, so they broke not His bones.</strong> Christ, the great Passover sacrifice, of whom all altar victims had been but suggestive prototypes, died through violence yet without a bone of His body being broken, as was a prescribed condition of the slain paschal lambs. <a href="../scriptures/Jesus-the-Christ-chapter-35.-death-and-burial.html">Jesus the Christ. Chapter 35. Death and Burial</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Why? Why weren’t the bones broken? Why is this significant?</p>
<p>The bones of a paschal lamb were meant <em>not</em> to be broken.</p>
<p>It dates back to the Mosiac Passover in Egypt (when the firstborns of the Egyptians and the Pharaoh were killed)</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In one house shall it be eaten; thou shalt not carry forth ought of the flesh abroad out of the house; <strong>neither shall ye break a bone thereof.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/exodus-12.46">Exodus 12.46</a></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>They shall leave none of it unto the morning, nor break any bone of it: according to all the ordinances of the passover they shall keep it. <a href="../scriptures/numbers-9.12">Numbers 9.12</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It was prophesied that “Many are the afflictions of the righteous: but the Lord delivereth him out of them all. <strong>He keepeth all his bones: not one of them is broken</strong>.” (<a href="../scriptures/psalm-34.19-20">Psalm 34.19–20</a>)</p>
<p>John testified of the fulfillment of this prophecy:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The Jews therefore, because it was the preparation, that the bodies should not remain upon the cross on the sabbath day, (for that sabbath day was an high day,) besought Pilate that their legs might be broken, and that they might be taken away. 32 Then came the soldiers, and brake the legs of the first, and of the other which was crucified with him. 33 But when they came to Jesus, and saw that he was dead already, <strong>they brake not his legs:</strong> <a href="../scriptures/john-19.31-33">John 19.31–33</a></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>36 For these things were done, that the scripture should be fulfilled, A bone of him shall not be broken. <a href="../scriptures/john-19.36">John 19.36</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>So while we break the bread, His bones were not broken. Just His flesh.</p>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>The details that were fulfilled at His death remind me of His prophetic life. The fact that he was killed according to the law, and the law predated him and is scripture in the Torah, is further evidence that Christ truly lived and that his life was a fulfillment of prophecy.</p>
<p>Likewise, those same details apply to my life. He is involved in those details. <a href="../scriptures/alma-37.7.html">Alma 37.7</a></p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>sacrament-symbols</category>
  <category>symbol-bread</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/broken-bread-but-no-broken-bones.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 10:35:16 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Porous Bread</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/porous-bread.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="symbol" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Symbol</h1>
<p>Bread is porous.</p>
<ul>
<li>In the sacrament, the bread (flesh) is first broken, then the water (blood) is administered.</li>
<li>Blood follows broken flesh. Blood flowed through the broken flesh. The pores of the flesh.</li>
</ul>
<p>Bread, being porous, is also absorbent. → He absorbed our problems. He internalized them inside His flesh to the point that his own blood didn’t have space internally anymore and exited through the pores.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-sourdough-bread-is-porous.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The pores in bread remind me of the pores that let blood for me</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="supporting-scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Supporting Scriptures</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And lo, he shall suffer temptations, and pain of body, hunger, thirst, and fatigue, even more than man can suffer, except it be unto death; for behold, blood cometh from every pore, so great shall be his anguish for the wickedness and the abominations of his people. <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-3.7">Mosiah 3.7</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>The Savior suffered an enormous amount. Even the thought of imagining blood coming out of my pores evokes thoughts of feeling so much physically overwhelming internal pressure or emotional agony that it would make a human body explode.</p>
<p>I can remember this when I pray. I can feel heard because He not only felt what I feel today, but he knows the future me, the past me, and the past/present/future everyone else. When I pray, I’m not approaching a distant God. I’m approaching the one that understands humanity better than any human possibly could. Someone that understands me more than I’ll ever understand myself. Someone who’s been there.</p>
<p>When I pray, I don’t have to give pretenses, because “your Father knoweth what things ye have need of, before ye ask him.” (<a href="../scriptures/matthew-6.8">Matthew 6.8</a>)</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>sacrament-symbols</category>
  <category>prayer</category>
  <category>symbol-bread</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/porous-bread.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 10:33:31 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 15 - Hearken and Hold Fast</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-15-hearken-and-hold-fast.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Who do we listen to?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And I said unto them that it was the word of God; and whoso would hearken unto the word of God, and would hold fast unto it, they would never perish; neither could the temptations and the fiery darts of the adversary overpower them unto blindness, to lead them away to destruction. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-15.24">1 Nephi 15.24</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>To learn biology, do you go to the math teacher? To learn happiness, perhaps the Source of truth and light can be our Teacher.</p>
<p>Once we learn truth, everything else becomes a lot more clear. And once we know what clear looks like, we don’t heed the distracting darts.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Hearken (listen, read, pay attention to, follow)</li>
<li>Hold fast (appreciate, come back to daily) <img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-hold-fast-fiery-darts.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Look to Christ. He is the Word"></li>
</ol>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>obedience</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-15-hearken-and-hold-fast.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 23:59:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 14 - Convincing unto Peace</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-14-convincing-unto-peace.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The Lord gives unto us according to our desires:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For the time cometh, saith the Lamb of God, that I will work a great and a marvelous work among the children of men; a work which shall be everlasting, either on the one hand or on the other—either to <strong>the convincing of them unto peace and life eternal</strong>, or unto the deliverance of them to the hardness of their hearts and the blindness of their minds unto their being brought down into captivity, and also into destruction, both temporally and spiritually, according to the captivity of the devil, of which I have spoken. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-14.7">1 Nephi 14.7</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Remember that He cannot take away our agency. So he doesn’t come to judge us or cast us to lots of good or evil.</p>
<p>People self select. They choose for themselves in their own life.</p>
<p>And this is the marvelous work: to be convinced of peace.</p>
<p>Am I “convince” of peace as stated above? Do I recognize that the peaceful way is always the best way through?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-convincing-of-peace-dove-two-guys.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Convince me unto peace, please!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>No, it says “convincing of them <em>unto</em> peace”, meaning that convincing them of Jesus, which leads to peace. But the sentiment is the same: that living a life of peace is the one I want.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>peace</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-14-convincing-unto-peace.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 23:44:37 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 13 - Publish Peace</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-13-publish-peace.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A lot of us have very little control over the world we’re born into. We can do a lot for our own lives, but very few of us will have the ability to change nations.</p>
<p>Which is why I love this scripture:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And blessed are they who shall seek to bring forth my Zion at that day, for they shall have the gift and the power of the Holy Ghost; and if they endure unto the end they shall be lifted up at the last day, and shall be saved in the everlasting kingdom of the Lamb; and <strong>whoso shall publish peace, yea, tidings of great joy, how beautiful upon the mountains shall they be.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-13.37">1 Nephi 13.37</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Regardless of your status, if you publish peace, good awaits you.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-dove-on-a-branch.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Dove on a branch</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>peace</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-13-publish-peace.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 23:59:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 12 - Broad Roads</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-12-broad-roads.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The modern refrain is to do and be whatever you want. While I largely agree with this refrain, there are some caveats: certain things bring us happiness. Being kind to people. Helping people. Saying sorry, etc.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And the mists of darkness are the temptations of the devil, which blindeth the eyes, and hardeneth the hearts of the children of men, and <strong>leadeth them away into broad roads</strong>, that they perish and are lost. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-12.17">1 Nephi 12.17</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-image-a-hill-with-a-tree-at-the-top-a-lot-of-broad-roads-at-the-base-of-the-hill-heading-down-strange-paths.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">All the roads we can take can confuse us. Instead, we can focus on where we’re heading</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The temptation we all face is to be lured down broad roads. By contrast, the way of the Lord is the straight and narrow.</p>
<p>Once I was working with someone and I was writing my code a few ways, with a bunch of tries that had failed. I finally kept the right one along side the failures. The reviewer said “why do you keep this junk?” I thought; because it helps me remember the way to not do it. “Why not just keep the answer though?”</p>
<p>Sometimes we like to focus on the “broad” roads in a few ways.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Remember all our failings, rather than focus on the things that bring us happiness. We do this as a badge of “I don’t want to repeat those bad mistakes.” Sure, the intent is good, but that’s like carrying a broken phone around with you to remind you not to drop your phone again. The effect is far more positive if we focus on the good things that come from following Christ.</li>
<li>There are a lot of paths we can go down in life. The Lord wants us to do many good things! (<a href="../christianity/turn-to-god-not-your-idols.html">Turn to God in All Things, and Not Your Idols</a>). But there are a few roads he doesn’t want us to go down: selfishness, greed, love of money, etc. These roads are broad. There are a lot of ways to lose yourself.</li>
</ol>
<p>So remember, “focus on the right answer”. Focus on the Savior, and walk towards him. Drop your load at his feet (<a href="../scriptures/matthew-11.28-30.html">Matthew 11.28–30</a>).</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-12-broad-roads.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 23:44:37 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Turn to God in All Things, and Not Your Idols</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/turn-to-god-not-your-idols.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I wrote <a href="../christianity/the-power-of-habitual-prayer.html">The Power of Habitual Prayer</a> in the mindset of having intentional prayers. Today, I experienced another one.</p>
<section id="a-typical-day" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>A Typical Day</h1>
<p>I felt overwhelmed by a few things (just day to day life, parenting, working, making sure I get that insurance policy and that bill figured out, etc, etc, etc.)</p>
<p>I decided to see if prayer could help me get out of my funk.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-angels-in-the-crop-fields.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Pray for help in all things, and watch the Hand of the Lord reveal itself</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>During my prayer, I felt something happen. I decided I would pray until I felt a change. And I did. I felt a change. More hope entered in. (“It’s all gonna be fine!”) I felt more grateful for the help I failed to fully appreciate just moments ago.</p>
<p>We get into moods. And bad moods are hard to get out of. But this is life. Life is full of bad moods.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-do-you-do-to-fix-your-bad-mood" class="level1">
<h1>What do you do to fix your bad mood?</h1>
<p>This quote came to mind while I was praying:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>As you think celestial, you will find yourself avoiding anything that robs you of your agency. Any addiction—be it gaming, gambling, debt, drugs, alcohol, anger, pornography, sex, or even food﻿—offends God. Why? <strong>Because your obsession becomes your god. You look to it rather than to Him for solace.</strong><br>
<a href="../scriptures/russell-m-nelson-think-celestial">“Think Celestial!”, Russell M. Nelson</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>You don’t need an addiction to appreciate the sentiment here: where do you turn when you’re struggling?</p>
<p>Do you turn to social media? Phone calls? News? The internet? TV? Anger? Food?</p>
<p>I’ve tried all those things. They’re all wonderful (except anger lol), especially calling a friend. But am I doing that before taking the issue to the Lord?</p>
<p>He has invited us to take all things to Him. Every thought even:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Look unto me in <strong><em>every</em></strong> thought; doubt not, fear not.<br>
<a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-6.36">Doctrine and Covenants 6.36</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>And we take all things to Him so He can consecrate them to us:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>ye must <strong>not perform any thing</strong> unto the Lord <strong>save in the first place ye shall pray</strong> unto the Father in the name of Christ, that he will consecrate thy performance unto thee, that thy performance may be for the welfare of thy soul.<br>
<a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-32.9">2 Nephi 32.9</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes, the Lord blesses us even when we don’t pray. But the promise is in the prayer: pray in all things. Pray in every thought. Do all things for Good reasons.</p>
<p>And he didn’t qualify what “labor” means here:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Come unto me, <strong>all ye that labour and are heavy laden, and I will give you rest</strong> Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me; for I am meek and lowly in heart: and ye shall find rest unto your souls. For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light.<br>
<a href="../scriptures/matthew-11.28-30">Matthew 11.28–30</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Perhaps He wants us to decide what our labor is, bring it to Him, and consecrate it and ask His help. This seems aligned with Him wanting us to be agents:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For the power is in them, wherein they are agents unto themselves. And inasmuch as men do good they shall in nowise lose their reward.<br>
<a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-58.28">Doctrine and Covenants 58.28</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>(This comes after “Verily I say, men should be anxiously engaged in a good cause, and do many things of their own free will, and bring to pass much righteousness;” <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-58.27">Doctrine and Covenants 58.27</a>)</p>
</section>
<section id="let-god-prevail" class="level1">
<h1>Let God Prevail</h1>
<p>So: get an idea of some good cause to be engaged in (parenting, providing for family, etc), pray for support in it, ask Him to consecrate it, watch for miracles.</p>
<p>I think we find reasons for why we <em>shouldn’t</em> pray.<sup>1</sup> Because we think we need to do it on our own. There’s a constant balance between “how much do I rely on God and how much should I just get up and do it myself”. I think the balance is rather not a balance at all. Just pick a plan, ask for help, then go and do what’s in your power. The scriptures are full of examples of people who did this.<sup>2</sup></p>
<p>He loves us. He wants us to succeed. He cares about our daily labor, whether that’s in a field or in the barn that a home turns into. If you’re still wondering, <a href="https://knowhy.bookofmormoncentral.org/knowhy/the-simple-miracle-that-helped-the-whitmers-further-the-book-of-mormon">Read this cool story on David Whitmer and how the Lord helped him with his crops</a> and how the Lord is aware of all our needs, temporal and spiritual.</p>
<p>I got up from my prayer feeling “I can do this!” And the impression came “<em>we</em> can do this”.</p>


</section>
<aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>“And now, my beloved brethren, I perceive that ye ponder still in your hearts; and it grieveth me that I must speak concerning this thing. For if ye would hearken unto the Spirit which teacheth a man to pray, ye would know that ye must pray; for the evil spirit teacheth not a man to pray, but teacheth him that he must not pray.” (<a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-32.8">2 Nephi 32.8</a>)↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Nephi and the broken bow, Nephi and the material for the ship, brother of Jared and the stones, etc.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</aside>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>scripture of the day</category>
  <category>prayer</category>
  <category>faith</category>
  <category>consecration</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/turn-to-god-not-your-idols.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 21:43:10 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 11 - Angel shows signs to Nephi</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-11-seeing-signs-of-christ.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Nephi saw a vision because he desired knowledge. Consider the Angel’s instruction:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>7 And behold this thing <strong>shall be given unto thee for a sign</strong>, that after thou hast beheld the tree which bore the fruit which thy father tasted, thou shalt also behold a man descending out of heaven, and him shall ye witness; and after ye have witnessed him ye shall bear record that it is the Son of God. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-11.7">1 Nephi 11.7</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Now, we know that the Lord rebuked the Pharisees for seeking signs:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The Pharisees also with the Sadducees came, and tempting desired him that he would shew them a sign from heaven. He answered and said unto them, When it is evening, ye say, It will be fair weather: for the sky is red. And in the morning, It will be foul weather to day: for the sky is red and lowring. O ye hypocrites, ye can discern the face of the sky; but <strong>can ye not discern the signs of the times?</strong> A <strong>wicked and adulterous generation seeketh after a sign</strong>; and there shall no sign be given unto it, but the sign of the prophet Jonas. And he left them, and departed. <a href="../scriptures/matthew-16.1-4">Matthew 16.1–4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But signs themselves are good. Moses lead by signs: the seven miracles. Baal was trumped by a sign: fire from heaven. Manna in the wilderness. Water from the rock. The fall of the city from trumpets. Oil in the vial.</p>
<p>Any miracle is a sign. A sign that God exists. That He has all power. That Christ is His son.</p>
<p>But today we don’t need to seek for <em>new</em> signs but instead do as the Lord said and “discern the signs of the times”.</p>
<p>By seeking to see His hand, we find the signs.</p>
<p>It’s wicked to seek for a sign, because wicked means “unrepentant”. An unrepentant soul, one who is not going to Heavenly Father and seeking His love, doesn’t see the Hand of God in their life. As a result, they are without his signs (<a href="../concepts/gratus-sum-ergo-habeo.html">Gratus sum, ergo habeo</a>).</p>
<p>So to see signs:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Repent (desire a connection with Heavenly Father and His son)</li>
<li>Look for them (discern)</li>
</ol>
<p>Presto poof.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-moses-raising-a-brass-serpent-watercolor-expressionist.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Why would I believe a new sign if I don’t believe the old signs?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>faith</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-11-seeing-signs-of-christ.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 09:14:07 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2024-01-21 Come Follow Me CTR 7 Jan 15-21 1 Nephi 6-10</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-21-jan-21.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="summary" class="level1">
<h1>Summary</h1>
<p>These chapters teach me:</p>
<ul>
<li>how to overcome adversity (prayer)</li>
<li>Some people never change (Laman and Lemuel)</li>
<li>People who don’t like the message usually reject it and denounce it (Laman and Lemuel)</li>
<li>The love of God is accessible to all</li>
<li>The Lord invites all, even if He knows they won’t listen</li>
<li>Those who come can fully appreciate the beauty of the Lord’s love</li>
<li>If you take your eyes off the Savior, and care what people think instead, you can feel shame which can drive you to leave Him</li>
<li>The scriptures are written with a specific purpose: they don’t know. They’re doing what the Lord wants them to do.</li>
<li>The Lord will teach those about the Tree of Life who want to know about it. Nephi wasn’t any more special than anyone else. He just wanted to know.</li>
<li>The Lord works through prophets. Through the priesthood.</li>
<li>Perhaps Lehi could have been more gentle with Laman and Lemuel. But Nephi <em>did</em> mention the “tender feelings” that Lehi had for them, so maybe Laman and Lemuel just didn’t get it</li>
<li>There’s a little bit of Laman and Lemuel and Nephi and Sam and Lehi and Sariah in all of us.</li>
<li>Over time, the prophecies are revealed and fulfilled.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-1-nephi-610-summary.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="The image generated by GPT from the above bullets"> # Studies</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-6-god-of-the-covenant.html">1 Nephi 6 - God of the Covenant</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-7-commitment.html">1 Nephi 7 - Make a Choice, Don’t go Halvsies</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-8-what-others-think.html">1 Nephi 8 - Think for yourself</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-9-write-with-a-purpose.html">1 Nephi 9 - Write with a Purpose</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-10-rely-on-the-redeemer.html">1 Nephi 10 - Rely on the Redeemer</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="activity-ideas" class="level1">
<h1>Activity Ideas</h1>
<ul>
<li>“let me see” (<a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-11.1.html">1 Nephi 11.1</a>) - show a video to one kid, have him share or try to draw it. Have others try to understand. They just have to see for themselves.</li>
<li>Iron rod activity: blindfold.</li>
</ul>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me lesson plan</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-21-jan-21.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 23:34:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Receive the Holy Ghost</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/receive-the-holy-ghost.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today at church someone was confirmed a member of the Church after having been baptized yesterday. This taught me something new about the sacrament and the covenant we make with Him every week.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-receive-the-holy-ghostXimage-the-resurrected-christ-in-white-laying-both-of-his-hands-on-the-heads-of-one-person-water-colors-peaceful--inside-focus-on-the-savior-phase-out-other-things-impressionist.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Receive the Holy Ghost</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="entry-into-his-church-by-baptism" class="level1">
<h1>Entry into His Church by Baptism</h1>
<p>After baptism, we receive the gift of the Holy Ghost:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>But now I give unto thee a commandment, that thou shalt baptize by water, and they shall receive the Holy Ghost by the laying on of the hands, even as the apostles of old. <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-35.6">Doctrine and Covenants 35.6</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>There is precedence for this, as the Savior gave the gift of the Holy Ghost to his apostles after he was no longer tarrying with them:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And when he had said this, he breathed on them, and saith unto them, Receive ye the Holy Ghost: <a href="../scriptures/john-20.22">John 20.22</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Pausing on that thought for a moment, let’s consider the last sentence in the sacrament prayer on the bread:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>that they may <strong>always</strong> have his Spirit to be with them. <a href="../scriptures/moroni-4.3">Moroni 4.3</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Also consider that the last of the water prayer omits that word “always”:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>that they may have his Spirit to be with them. <a href="../scriptures/moroni-5.2">Moroni 5.2</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Are they contradictory? No.&nbsp;Because the full last sentence of the water prayer says:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>that they do <strong>always</strong> remember him, that they may have his Spirit to be with them. <a href="../scriptures/moroni-5.2">Moroni 5.2</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This tells us that if we always remember him (the Savior), we’ll have His spirit to be with us.</p>
<p>Back to the New Teatament. The Lord taught His disciples that the comforter would come to them <em>once He left</em>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Nevertheless I tell you the truth; It is expedient for you that I go away: for if I go not away, the Comforter will not come unto you; but if I depart, I will send him unto you. <a href="../scriptures/john-16.7">John 16.7</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>And in a prior chapter, Jesus had instructed that this was the plan - that he would give them the gift of the Comforter when He was gone. Notice the word “another”:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And I will pray the Father, and he shall give you <em>another</em> Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever; Even the Spirit of truth; whom the world cannot receive, because it seeth him not, neither knoweth him: but ye know him; for he dwelleth with you, and shall be in you. I will not leave you comfortless: I will come to you. <a href="../scriptures/john-14.16-18">John 14.16–18</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Perhaps He said “another” Comforter because He is the first?</p>
<p>He further promised the role of the Holy Ghost is to teach of truth and testify of the Savior:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>But when the Comforter is come, whom I will send unto you from the Father, even the Spirit of truth, which proceedeth from the Father, he shall testify of me: <a href="../scriptures/john-15.26">John 15.26</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Lord also explained how He works with the Holy Ghost. It appears that, because the Savior was with them, He was their source of truth. But as He was planning to leave them He needed to leave them with a source of truth. As such, they were being prepared to receive the gift of the Holy Ghost:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>These things have I spoken unto you, <strong>being yet present with you.</strong> But the Comforter, which is the Holy Ghost, whom the Father will send in my name, he shall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, whatsoever I have said unto you. <a href="../scriptures/john-14.25-26">John 14.25–26</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This doesn’t mean they didn’t have the spirit - how else could Peter have received His spiritual witness of the Savior? <a href="../scriptures/matthew-16.15-17.html">matthew-16.15-17</a></p>
<p>What do these scriptures all teach me?</p>
<ul>
<li>If we always remember the Savior, we’ll have His spirit to be with us</li>
<li>His spirit teaches us what is truth: it testifies of Christ</li>
<li>He gave this gift because we can’t always be in His presence.</li>
<li>Even if we were in His presence, we’d need the spirit to let us know that He is the Christ</li>
<li>When we receive the Holy Ghost after baptism, we are commanded to “receive the Holy Ghost” by confirmation into the church.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="what-is-the-gift-of-the-holy-ghost" class="level1">
<h1>What is the “gift” of the Holy Ghost?</h1>
<p>This last one is powerful, because of a clarifying point in the handbook of the church:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>States “receive the Holy Ghost” (not “receive the gift of the Holy Ghost”).<br>
<a href="../scriptures/18.-performing-priesthood-ordinances-and-blessings">18. Performing Priesthood Ordinances and Blessings</a></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Or, the “gift” of the Holy Ghost perhaps isn’t a thing like the priesthood - something bestowed upon us. (This is something I’ve thought it was my whole life - a gift I receive.) why aren’t we told to receive the gift of the Holy Ghost?</p>
<p>What, then, is legally binding about the Lord’s covenant? And what is the “gift of the Holy Ghost” as mentioned in the scriptures? (<a href="../scriptures/articles-of-faith-1.4">Articles of Faith 1.4</a>, <a href="../scriptures/moses-5.58">Moses 5.58</a>, <a href="../scriptures/jacob-6.8">Jacob 6.8</a>, <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-39.23">Doctrine and Covenants 39.23</a>, <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-49.14">Doctrine and Covenants 49.14</a>, <a href="../scriptures/acts-10.45">Acts 10.45</a>, and like 4 other references…it’s referenced in every standard work!)</p>
<p>Even the Lord says he’ll bestow the gift of the Holy Ghost:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And whoso having faith you shall confirm in my church, by the laying on of the hands, and <strong>I will bestow the gift of the Holy Ghost upon them</strong>. <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-33.15">Doctrine and Covenants 33.15</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Because we don’t “receive the gift of the Holy Ghost”, perhaps the <em>gift</em> of the Holy Ghost is instead the <em>promised blessing of the constant companionship</em> as a <em>result</em> of keeping our covenant. Things consistent with the definitions in the Guide to the Scriptures:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>It is the right of every worthy baptized member of the Church to have the constant influence of the Holy Ghost</strong>. Following a person’s baptism into the true Church of Jesus Christ, he receives the gift of the Holy Ghost by the laying on of hands from one who has the proper authority <a href="../scriptures/gift-of-the-holy-ghost">Gift of the Holy Ghost</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Anyone on earth can enjoy the Holy Ghost. It teaches those of truth. But only those of the covenant of baptism, who keep that covenant and the <a href="../concepts/sacrament-covenant.html">Sacrament Covenant</a> (To always remember Him, keep His commandments, and take His name upon us), are blessed <em>always</em> with His spirit. Things the gift of the Holy Ghost: its constant companionship.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>While someone is being confirmed a member of the Church, he or she is told to “receive the Holy Ghost.” The gift of the Holy Ghost is not forced on anyone. <strong>It becomes the responsibility of members to invite the Holy Ghost to be with them</strong> <a href="../scriptures/gift-of-the-holy-ghost">Gift of the Holy Ghost</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>And perhaps the ordinance of the confirmation is to start that covenant: “receive the Holy Ghost now, and always as you remember Me.”</p>
<p>And why do we always want His spirit to be with us? Because the spirit is a proxy for Him: the Comforter, the Source of Truth, the Light and Life of the World. When we have that spirit, we are of the Kingdom of Heaven (on earth).</p>
<p>So when I take the sacrament every week, I’m making the covenant to always remember Him so that I can enjoy the <em>gift</em> of <em>receiving</em> the Holy Ghost always.</p>
<hr>
<p>Why is this relevant to me personally?</p>
<ul>
<li>the <em>gift</em> isn’t some separate power that I can offend or please. It’s not some separate God. Instead, the gift is a covenant. This changes my focus away from a relationship with the Holy Ghost and instead a relationship with the Savior. The purpose of the holy ghost is to point me to the Savior. And if I’m not feeling the spirit, it’s not about trying to please the Holy Ghost - I just need to begin remembering the savior in that moment.</li>
</ul>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>sacrament-symbols</category>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>symbol-receive</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/receive-the-holy-ghost.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 10:41:50 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 8 - Press Forward Continually</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/choosing-to-press-forward.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Obtaining the love of Christ is not easy:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I beheld others pressing forward, and they came forth and caught hold of the end of the rod of iron; and they did press forward through the mist of darkness, clinging to the rod of iron, even until they did come forth and partake of the fruit of the tree. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-8.24">1 Nephi 8.24</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Now, He loves us unconditionally. But it is up to us to come to Him.</p>
<p>He constantly invites us to come to Him, and because He gives us agency (<a href="../christianity/stop-trying-to-change-people.html">Stop trying to change people. Stop it.</a>), we have to choose to follow Him.</p>
<p>This choice isn’t an easy one. It’s a difficult one. Some of us get tired and let go. Or we get distracted by all there is around us. Whatever the case - God’s love for us is constant. It’s there. It’s available. It’s at the tree. It’s felt through meaningful prayer (<a href="../christianity/the-power-of-habitual-prayer.html">The Power of Habitual Prayer</a>). It’s felt through studying His words. It’s by building a relationship that we come to Him. It’s hard work, but it’s the way we experience the delicious fruit.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-the-tree-of-light.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The tree of life is also the tree of light. Always there</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>love</category>
  <category>love of God</category>
  <category>agency</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/choosing-to-press-forward.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2024 23:41:36 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 10 - Rely on the Redeemer</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-10-rely-on-the-redeemer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As people, we are consistently imperfect:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wherefore, all mankind were in a lost and in a fallen state, and ever would be save they should rely on this Redeemer. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-10.6">1 Nephi 10.6</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The blessing of this imperfection is a constant reminder that to become who we need to, we need to rely on the Savior.</p>
<p>This isn’t a one-time thing. Perhaps it’s like walking up a slippery hill. There are grips on our knee pads, but not on our shoes.</p>
<p>Kneel in prayer to rely on the Redeemer.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-ascend-the-hill-by-kneeling-in-prayer.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The only way up is down on your knees</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-10-rely-on-the-redeemer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2024 00:07:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 9 - Write with a Purpose</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-9-write-with-a-purpose.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The Book of Mormon has a purpose:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I have received a commandment of the Lord that I should make these plates, for the special purpose that there should be an account engraven of the ministry of my people. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-9.3">1 Nephi 9.3</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/img/dalle-writing-on-gold-plates.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Write with a purpose. Journal with a purpose.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Then the other plates had a different purpose:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>the other plates are for the more part of the reign of the kings and the wars and contentions of my people. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-9.4">1 Nephi 9.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>What purpose does my writing have? What is the purpose of this blog?</p>
<p>When we write, it helps to have a purpose. It guides the writing. How does writing for entertainment differ from writing to try to change someone’s life by inviting them to Christ? The Book of Mormon is written for the later.</p>
<p>Let us write. Write with a purpose.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-9-write-with-a-purpose.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 23:59:57 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
