<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2024 23:42:24 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 4 - Love and Despair</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-4-love-and-despair.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>2 Nephi 4 has two interesting scriptures:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And when I desire to rejoice, my heart groaneth because of my sins; nevertheless, I know in whom I have trusted.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>He hath filled me with his love, even unto the consuming of my flesh.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Can you imagine a human who has felt so much love to describe it as the consuming of his flesh, yet have perhaps a degree of self loathing because of his sins? That he’d like to be happy but he can’t because he knows what he’s done wrong?</p>
<p>I think anyone who is a human can empathize.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-peace-vs-despair.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Same person, same feelings"> # Meaning</p>
<p>Humanity is about building a relationship with God. God is about letting us have agency. He doesn’t expect us to be perfect. He expects us to be human, but guides us to perfection. In some sense He demands it, knowing we’ll fall short.</p>
<p>But we can take comfort in that He will bless us even when we feel undeserving.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-4-love-and-despair.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2024 23:42:24 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 4 - A Prophecy of Another Branch</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-4-prophecy-of-another-branch.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For behold, he truly prophesied concerning all his seed. And the prophecies which he wrote, there are not many greater. And he prophesied concerning us, and our future generations; and they are written upon the plates of brass. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-4.2">2 Nephi 4.2</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is another powerful reminder of things lost from the Bible, similar to <a href="../christianity/1-nephi-20-baptism-in-the-old-testament.html">1 Nephi 20 - Baptism in the Old Testament</a>. As we look at 2 Nephi 3:5, we see a link to the Joseph Smith Translation of Genesis.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>24 And Joseph said unto his brethren, I die, and go unto my fathers; and I go down to my grave with joy. The God of my father Jacob be with you, to deliver you out of affliction in the days of your bondage; for the Lord hath visited me, and I have obtained a promise of the Lord, <strong>that out of the fruit of my loins, the Lord God will raise up a righteous branch out of my loins</strong>; and unto thee, whom my father Jacob hath named Israel, a prophet; (not the Messiah who is called Shilo;) and this prophet shall deliver my people out of Egypt in the days of thy bondage. <a href="../scriptures/jst,-genesis-50.24">JST, Genesis 50.24</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Imagine if for 2000 years the entire world knew about this prophecy and the other things in 50:24-38 # Meaning</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-4-prophecy-of-another-branch.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 23:07:52 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 3 - Two Scriptures</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-3-two-scriptures.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wherefore, the fruit of thy loins shall write; and the fruit of the loins of Judah shall write; and that which shall be written by the fruit of thy loins, and also that which shall be written by the fruit of the loins of Judah, <strong>shall grow together</strong>, unto the confounding of false doctrines and laying down of contentions, and establishing peace among the fruit of thy loins, and bringing them to the knowledge of their fathers in the latter days, and also to the knowledge of my covenants, saith the Lord. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-3.12">2 Nephi 3.12</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The scriptures will grow together over time.</p>
<ul>
<li>Do we use the scriptures, both the Book of Mormon and the Bible, to lay down false doctrines and contentions?</li>
<li>Do we seek these books to understand true doctrine?</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-two-books.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Two books</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>I can apply this in my own life by seeking to use the scriptures to address false beliefs in my life. To challenge the thoughts of the day.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-3-two-scriptures.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 23:58:23 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Coalesce - Revelation first, then Agency</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/coalesce-revelation-first-then-agency.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Some believe in pre-destiny. That their life is predetermined.</p>
<p>Some believe there is no God and they have to do the best they can with what they’ve got, because that’s all they’ve got.</p>
<p>The truth lies somewhere in between. There <em>is</em> a God, <em>and</em> He wants us to be agents (<a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-58.28.html">Doctrine and Covenants 58.28</a>).</p>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-plan-a-and-b.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Life is filled with choices and many actions to perform"> In data science, there’s a concept called “coalesce”. In English it means to come together and make one whole. In software, it means to fill in missing data with a default value.</p>
<p>Forgive the nerd talk, but bear with me here: So if you have an empty spreadsheet, and you do the operation <code>coalesce(spreadsheet, 5)</code> it would return the spreadsheet’s value if you had data in the spreadsheet but the number 5 if you had a missing cell. So if you have 10 rows of data in Excel but 3 missing rows, the output would be the 7 original values with 3 cells now with 5 in them. It’s a way of handling missing data, because missing data creates problems.</p>
<p>What is the missing data in our personal lives? It’s “what do we do?” What do we do today? Tomorrow? Next year? What do we do today and tomorrow to prepare for the thing we may want to do next year?</p>
<p>I’ve realized the healthy way to have a relationship with personal revelation is to operate under the constraints of a coalesce. To be whole and one with the Lord, our goal should be to coalesce.</p>
<p>Some rely too much on the spirit. Hoping God will make a choice for us. But he gave us agency. He lost 1/3 of his children because he didn’t want to give up agency. And, by that right, he’s willing to lose you and me too if we’re not willing to exercise our agency. We just choose. This is life. And we must choose Him.</p>
<p>In many things, there is a commandment we can rely on. Don’t kill. Don’t steal. Be honest. Pay tithing.</p>
<p>That’s the priority.</p>
<p>Then there’s the gray area stuff: love our neighbor.</p>
<p>That’s the agency.</p>
<p>Then there’s the really gray area: have joy. Among this is “provide for a family” and “raise them the best way you can”.</p>
<p>So, use a coalesce. Your default value is what <em>you</em> want to do. That’s what you fill in.</p>
<p>Our life should be <code>coalesce(personal revelation, our agency)</code>.</p>
<p>Where there’s a commandment or personal revelation from the Lord, do it. Don’t wait. Do it. Follow the prompting. Otherwise, if you have no prompting or commandment to follow, make a choice! Learn. Experience. Enjoy.</p>
<p>I believe the Lord will support us when we follow a pattern of putting Him first, and then defaulting to doing many good things of our own free will and choice when He hasn’t given us instruction.</p>
<p>That doesn’t mean he doesn’t care what we do. He cares deeply. It’s just more like <a href="../scriptures/ether-2.23.html">Ether 2.23</a> where he wants us to come up with some good ideas.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>decisions</category>
  <category>revelation</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/coalesce-revelation-first-then-agency.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 09:47:06 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 4 Ask</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-4-ask.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>Do you believe in what Nephi came to know?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Yea, I know that God will give liberally to him that asketh. Yea, my God will give me, if I ask not amiss; therefore I will lift up my voice unto thee; yea, I will cry unto thee, my God, the rock of my righteousness. Behold, my voice shall forever ascend up unto thee, my rock and mine everlasting God. Amen. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-4.35">2 Nephi 4.35</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>What are the limitations we can put on the Lord? Here are a few that get me:</p>
<ul>
<li>The Lord wants me to struggle on this one</li>
<li>I don’t want to ask too much</li>
<li>This isn’t that big of a deal. I should pray about more important things instead.</li>
</ul>
<p>All three of these are easily contradicted by scriptures. He <em>does</em> want us to struggle but struggle <em>with</em> him and overcome (<a href="../scriptures/1-corinthians-10.13">1 Corinthians 10.13</a>). The Lord wants us to ask for all the blessings He’s capable of giving us (<a href="../scriptures/malachi-3.10">Malachi 3.10</a>), and pour out endless blessings.<sup>1</sup> And lastly, the Lord works by small and simple means (<a href="../scriptures/alma-37.7.html">Alma 37.7</a>).</p>
<p>Perhaps instead those three things should be exactly what we pray for:</p>
<ul>
<li>What can we struggle on together? (<a href="../scriptures/matthew-11.28-30.html">Matthew 11.28–30</a>)</li>
<li>What’s the gift that thou art willing to bless me with? (<a href="../scriptures/matthew-6.8.html">Matthew 6.8</a> )</li>
<li>What’s the smallest piece of help I could possibly ask for? (<a href="../scriptures/ether-2.23">Ether 2.23</a>)</li>
</ul>
<p>The phrase “ask not amiss” isn’t some indication that a secret code needs to be enacted. That to unlock the heavens, the prayer needs to be offered in the right way at the right time by the right person.</p>
<p>How can you ask amiss? The scriptures teach us. If we’re selfish, seek our own, are puffed up, are easily provoked, want revenge, are greedy, etc. then we’re asking amiss.</p>
<p>But if we’re trying to do our best to be good people and dealing with the challenging responsibilities of being a father, son, brother, uncle, cousin, friend, neighbor, coworker, manager, etc. then we’re just dealing with life.</p>
<p>What is life without these titles? Who doesn’t work? Who doesn’t have someone to care for?</p>
<p>It’s precisely <em>these</em> things that are worthy of our prayers and divine supplication.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-praying-in-a-jungle-2000-years-ago.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Pray</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p><a href="../christianity/the-power-of-habitual-prayer.html">The Power of Habitual Prayer</a> is a theme I’ve tried this year. I’ve grown deeply in finding healing by making sure I can have a private place to pray.</p>
<p>I’ve also seen how prayers have been answered in ways I didn’t expect. That something comes unexpectedly and it turns out to be really good. But it wasn’t in the plans.</p>
<p>This is kind of like a personal manna. God delivers. Not expected. But welcomed.</p>


</section>
<aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Is eternal life not the greatest gift we could ask for? If we’re willing to ask for that, then why not for help in our temporal life circumstances?↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</aside>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-4-ask.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 23:06:15 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 2 - Enticement is Agency</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-2-enticing-decisions.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>What’s enticing you right now?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wherefore, the Lord God gave unto man that he should act for himself. Wherefore, man could not act for himself save it should be that he was enticed by the one or the other. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-2.16">2 Nephi 2.16</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Can you make a decision without being presented at least two options?</p>
<p>If you feel like you made a decision on something, what did you decide and what was the alternative option?</p>
<p>If you’re torn about a decision, why? What’s on the other side?</p>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-enticing-apple.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Why that apple, of all the apples?"> # Meaning</p>
<p>Life is full of enticing things. Sometimes, self defeating thoughts can be enticing. We have a bias towards negativity as humans. But thankfully we always have a choice.</p>
<p>Recognize the behavior. And then find the perhaps less <em>enticing</em> but far more healthy thought pattern.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>decisions</category>
  <category>mental health</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-2-enticing-decisions.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 23:01:41 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Gathered as One</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/gathered-as-one.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="symbol" class="level1">
<h1>Symbol</h1>
<p>We take the sacrament as a congregation, as one unified body.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-one-congregation-feasting.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="We partake as one congregation"> # Scriptures</p>
<p>When the sacrament was first administered, there was one bread and one cup.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And as they were eating, Jesus took bread, and blessed it, and brake it, and gave it to the disciples, and said, Take, eat; this is my body. And he took the cup, and gave thanks, and gave it to them, saying, Drink ye all of it; <a href="../scriptures/matthew-26.26-27">Matthew 26.26–27</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Can you imagine being in that room with Him? Drinking the sacrament for the first time?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>There is one body, and one Spirit, even as ye are called in one hope of your calling; <strong>One Lord, one faith, one baptism,</strong> One God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all. But unto every one of us is given grace according to the measure of the gift of Christ. <a href="../scriptures/ephesians-4.1-7">Ephesians 4.1–7</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is what it means when we gather together. We are one. We all rely on the same One Savior. We’ve all made the same one baptismal covenant. We all worship the same One God.</p>
<p>We all renew the same One covenant, which is a covenant to love and serve each other with His love.</p>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>I gain strength looking around at people so incredibly different than me, but also so incredibly similar. The fact that all these people want to follow Christ too gives me strength.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>sacrament-symbols</category>
  <category>symbol-together</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/gathered-as-one.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 20:07:19 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 2 - His Capacity to Carry Our Burdens</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-2-he-carries-our-burdens.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>The Savior is known to have offered himself as a sacrifice for our sins:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Behold, he offereth himself a sacrifice for sin, to answer the ends of the law, unto all those who have a broken heart and a contrite spirit; and unto none else can the ends of the law be answered. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-2.7">2 Nephi 2.7</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But that’s not all He sacrificed himself for:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Surely he hath borne our griefs, and carried our sorrows: yet we did esteem him stricken, smitten of God, and afflicted. <a href="../scriptures/isaiah-53.4">Isaiah 53.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Did He specify which griefs? Which sorrows?</p>
<p>I think sometimes we can limit in our minds which sorrows. But since He doesn’t specify, it’s probably all sorrows. Yes. Actually, not probably. It <em>is</em> all sorrows.</p>
<p>The time in middle school you were teased and you cried. The time in college you failed that test and wondered what the future would hold. The time your loved one passed away. The time you got rejected in some interview/deal/relationship/etc. Those sorrows.</p>
<p>If you haven’t felt any of these sorrows, I question if you’ve even lived…</p>
<p>The Lord’s rest ironically comes when we take His yoke upon us. Just like he wants us to <a href="sacrament-symbols/receive-the-holy-ghost.md">Receive the Holy Ghost</a>, he wants us to receive His yoke. He wants us to join Him:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Come unto me, all ye that labour and are heavy laden, and I will give you rest. 29 Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me; for I am meek and lowly in heart: and ye shall find rest unto your souls. 30 For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light. <a href="../scriptures/matthew-11.28-30">Matthew 11.28–30</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/img/google-yoked-oxen.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Lookin yoked bruh</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>When praying, it may increase the power of a prayer by holding in mind the imagery of the Savior beckoning us to be by His side. To be yoked with him.</p>
<p>When we do, perhaps we’ll see how close He is to us. How much he knows us. But we have to come to Him to feel that. He comes to us to invite us, but it’s only when we turn to Him that we truly feel He is with us.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>adversity</category>
  <category>atonement</category>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>prayer</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-2-he-carries-our-burdens.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2024 23:27:51 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Isaiah 53.4</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/isaiah-53.4.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Surely he hath borne our griefs, and carried our sorrows: yet we did esteem him stricken, smitten of God, and afflicted.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>See <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/ot/isa/53?id=p4&amp;lang=eng#p4">Isaiah 53.4</a></p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>favorite scriptures</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/isaiah-53.4.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 2 - Redemption</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-2-redemption.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>Notice the words “in” and “through”:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wherefore, redemption cometh in and through the Holy Messiah; for he is full of grace and truth. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-2.6">2 Nephi 2.6</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This provides some meaningful words. Rambling a bit here:</p>
<ul>
<li>in: because of?</li>
<li>through: by means of</li>
</ul>
<p>How are these two words different? One, Christ is a Being. He’s not an “amorphous entity”. By means of what He did for us, we can be redeemed. But it’s also because of who He is (presently as the Living Christ) in granting us forgiveness.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-risen-christ-by-the-tomb-redemption.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Risen Christ"> # Meaning</p>
<p>Christ’s atonement is infinite. It’s empowering to know that he’s already suffered for my sins of today and yesterday as well as tomorrow and beyond. Meaning, he already knows the mistakes I’m going to choose to make, which is kind of trippy in a way, but also comforting thinking about how He still loves me and knows how I’ll falter. That brings me peace knowing He knows me, who I am today, who I’ll develop into tomorrow.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>redemption</category>
  <category>atonement</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-2-redemption.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 23:51:37 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 2 - Consecration</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-2-consecration.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>Lehi, now in America after a long journey, sits his son, Jacob, down for a chat. He told him all his hard times would be rewarded:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Nevertheless, Jacob, my firstborn in the wilderness, thou knowest the greatness of God; and he shall <strong>consecrate</strong> thine afflictions for thy gain. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-2.2">2 Nephi 2.2</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This reminds me of:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I say unto you that ye must pray always, and not faint; that ye must not perform any thing unto the Lord save in the first place ye shall pray unto the Father in the name of Christ, that he will <strong>consecrate</strong> thy performance unto thee, that thy performance may be for the welfare of thy soul. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-32.9.html">2-nephi-32.9</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>To consecrate is to “make or declare something sacred” (Oxford), or “to devote or dedicate exclusively to a purpose”.</p>
<p>From this lens, Jacob’s trials (like all his brothers and sisters) could be declared sacred (for the purposes of the Lord) and dedicated to the Lord’s purposes and cause.</p>
<p>Likewise, through prayer we can consecrate all of our acts. We can make them sacred devotions. What would your life be like if every day you dedicated it to the Lord? Where you did everything with a sacred purpose and cause?</p>
<p>And what if He made all those things consecrated for your spiritual gain?</p>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-consecration-gift-to-cloud.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Consecration feels fuzzy, but it’s just giving yourself to something greater. It’s a mindset"> # Meaning</p>
<p>I can find more ways to consecrate my day and actions. To give myself with greater purpose.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>consecration</category>
  <category>adversity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-2-consecration.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2024 23:52:02 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 1 - Shake off the Chains</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-1-shake-off-the-chains.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>Keeping the commandments brings blessings:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And he hath said that: Inasmuch as ye shall keep my commandments ye shall prosper in the land; but inasmuch as ye will not keep my commandments ye shall be cut off from my presence. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-1.20">2 Nephi 1.20</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Think about it. Keeping the commandments means being honest, being kind, being respectful, finding a way to help others. Not being lazy. Being productive.</p>
<p>Literally, nobody can prosper without keeping some commandment. Without finding a way to meet someone’s need.</p>
<p>I also like this verse:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Awake, my sons; put on the armor of righteousness. Shake off the chains with which ye are bound, and come forth out of obscurity, and arise from the dust. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-1.23">2 Nephi 1.23</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s a rallying cry we can all relate to. We are all bound with chains in life. But we don’t have to be. The call to “rise up” is a call to shake the chains to hold you bound. Arise from the dust!</p>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-breaking-free-from-the-chains.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Break free from the chains"> # Meaning</p>
<p>It makes me wonder: what are the chains that hold me bound? Perhaps there are limiting beliefs.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-1-shake-off-the-chains.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2024 23:47:32 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 1 - Obtaining a Promised Land</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-1-land-of-promise.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures-a-land-of-promise" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Scriptures: A Land of Promise</h1>
<p>I thought about the phrase “land of promise” in <a href="../christianity/1-nephi-2-receiving-a-promised-land.html">1 Nephi 2 - Receiving a promised land</a> and there’s the verse in <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.5.html">1 Nephi 5.5</a> where Lehi says “I have obtained a land of promise”. He says that years before arriving in the promised land.</p>
<p>But now, years later, he testifies:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>notwithstanding our afflictions, <strong>we have obtained a land of promise, a land which is choice above all other lands</strong>; a land which the Lord God hath covenanted with me should be a land for the inheritance of my seed. Yea, the Lord hath covenanted this land unto me, and to my children forever, and also all those who should be led out of other countries by the hand of the Lord. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-1.5">2 Nephi 1.5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>How long did it take for them to receive that land? Many years. And many hardships. Lehi complained and was chastised at some point (1 Nephi 16). So the journey isn’t without its struggles.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-land-of-promise.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Land of promise</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>The Lord is with us. Even if we complain and struggle, He wants to help us get to a better place, our promised lands.</p>
<p>We can be like Lehi and seek to obtain that personal vision. And receive a personal covenant of how the Lord wants to bless us in our lives.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>individual covenant</category>
  <category>covenant</category>
  <category>land of promise</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-1-land-of-promise.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2024 19:56:03 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 1 - Alternative Endings</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-1-alternative-endings.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>Lehi and his family were prompted to leave Jerusalem before King Nebuchadnezzar II destroyed it in 586 BCE.</p>
<p>There must be that lingering doubt, when following the Lord, as in “what would life have been like otherwise?”</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I have seen a vision, in which I know that Jerusalem is destroyed; and had we remained in Jerusalem we should also have perished. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-1.4">2 Nephi 1.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Lehi knew the answer: had they stayed they would have perished.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-paradise-vs-destruction.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">What if the alternative to the choices you made was actually a much worse life?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>We hardly ever get to know how it would otherwise have ended. What if you took job A over B? What if I hadn’t broken my wrist? What if I had moved into X house vs.&nbsp;Y - who would I have met?</p>
<p>I’m not sure we’re supposed to know how it could otherwise have turned out. I’m not sure it matters much, either. Because I’m sure there were a lot of good people who weren’t prompted like Lehi to leave. (Consider how Abinadi had to stay.)</p>
<p>So I take this as “that’s interesting.” In this case, Lehi got to know the alternative ending to the story. He got to learn that he had avoided destruction in Jerusalem and could instead finish his days peacefully in his promised land.</p>
<p>We also often compare our lives to how perhaps it could have been better (thanks social media). Do you ever wonder if it could have been worse had you not made that good choice in your life?</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>decisions</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>hindsight</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-1-alternative-endings.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2024 22:24:18 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 22 - His Covenants will be the key of the Gathering of Israel</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-22-gathered-by-his-covenants.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>There is so much doctrine packed in here. Nephi is talking about the Lord doing a “marvelous work”</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it [the marvelous work] shall also be of worth unto the Gentiles; and not only unto the Gentiles but unto all the house of Israel, <strong>unto the making known of the covenants of the Father of heaven unto Abraham</strong>, saying: In thy seed shall all the kindreds of the earth be blessed. And I would, my brethren, that ye should know that all the kindreds of the earth cannot be blessed unless he shall make bare his arm in the eyes of the nations. Wherefore, the Lord God will proceed to make bare his arm in the eyes of all the nations, <strong>in bringing about his covenants and his gospel unto those who are of the house of Israel</strong>. Wherefore, he will bring them again out of captivity, and they shall be gathered together to the lands of their inheritance; and they shall be brought out of obscurity and out of darkness; and they <strong>shall know that the Lord is their Savior and their Redeemer, the Mighty One of Israel.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-22.9-12">1 Nephi 22.9–12</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Lord will restore His covenants. It doesn’t explicitly say “baptism, the sacrament, the oath and covenant of the priesthood, the endowment, and the sealing ordinance”, but that’s what Nephi is referring to.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-image-wheat-into-a-silo.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The Lord will gather us into His silo. This is His work, not ours.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Why doesn’t the Book of Mormon mention the sealing ordinance? The Melchizedek priesthood (the name of it)? The endowment? I’m not sure. But it’s fascinating how Joseph Smith translated this book but also received revelations to help finalize the structure of the church. # Meaning</p>
<p>This teaches me that…</p>
<ul>
<li>The Lord cares about people who reject him. He will do His work among them. He won’t leave me even if I leave Him. That’s a powerful concept.</li>
<li>The covenants are the most important thing to focus on in the scriptures. Everything else is just context about how to best live them.</li>
<li>I am gathered when I keep my covenants. They are the thing that help me understand and connect with the Lord.</li>
</ul>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>gathering of israel</category>
  <category>Abrahamic Covenant</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-22-gathered-by-his-covenants.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2024 23:28:38 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 21 - I Have Graven Thee</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-21-he-has-not-forgotten-you.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>The Lord reminds us he had not forgotten us:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>But, behold, Zion hath said: The Lord hath forsaken me, and my Lord hath forgotten me—but he will show that he hath not. 15 For can a woman forget her sucking child, that she should not have compassion on the son of her womb? Yea, they may forget, yet will I not forget thee, O house of Israel. 16 Behold, I <strong>have graven thee upon the palms of my hands</strong>; thy walls are continually before me. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-21.14-16">1 Nephi 21.14–16</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-graven-thee-on-the-palms.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Graven thee</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<ul>
<li>In hard moments it’s important to remember He is the way. He is in charge. He has not forgotten us.</li>
</ul>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-21-he-has-not-forgotten-you.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2024 00:38:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 20 - Baptism in the Old Testament</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-20-baptism-in-the-old-testament.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>The Isaiah chapters in Nephi often get skipped. But if you skip them, we miss out on important doctrine, like how “baptism” appears in the Nephi version of Isaiah 48 but not in the King James Version.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Hearken and hear this, O house of Jacob, who are called by the name of Israel, and are come forth out of the waters of Judah, or <strong>out of the waters of baptism</strong>, who swear by the name of the Lord, and make mention of the God of Israel, yet they swear not in truth nor in righteousness. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-20.1">1 Nephi 20.1</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-river-jordan-baptism.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Baptism</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>But if you compare to Isaiah 48, that line is not mentioned:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Hear ye this, O house of Jacob, which are called by the name of Israel, and are come forth out of the waters of Judah, which swear by the name of the Lord, and make mention of the God of Israel, but not in truth, nor in righteousness. <a href="../scriptures/isaiah-48.1">Isaiah 48.1</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The only reference to baptism in the Old Testament is found only in the chapter heading of 1 Kings 7:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The molten sea (baptismal font) rests on the backs of twelve oxen. <a href="../scriptures/1-kings-7">1 Kings 7</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is clearly one of the “plain and precious” things taken, or lost in translation, from the Bible:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>they have taken away from the gospel of the Lamb many parts which are plain and most precious; and <strong>also many covenants of the Lord have they taken away</strong>. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-13.26">1 Nephi 13.26</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But we know they practiced baptism in the Old Testament because Nephi lived and taught it, and the Pearl of Great Price talks about Adam’s baptism and ordination into the priesthood:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass, when the Lord had spoken with Adam, our father, that Adam cried unto the Lord, and he was caught away by the Spirit of the Lord, and was carried down into the water, and was laid under the water, and was brought forth out of the water. 65 And thus he was baptized, and the Spirit of God descended upon him, and thus he was born of the Spirit, and became quickened in the inner man. 66 And he heard a voice out of heaven, saying: Thou art baptized with fire, and with the Holy Ghost. This is the record of the Father, and the Son, from henceforth and forever; 67 And thou art after the order of him who was without beginning of days or end of years, from all eternity to all eternity. 68 Behold, thou art one in me, a son of God; and thus may all become my sons. Amen. <a href="../scriptures/moses-6.64-68">Moses 6.64–68</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<ul>
<li>It was cool to notice this today, as that verse popped out to me and that word “baptism”. It makes me wonder what else was taken from these Isaiah chapters</li>
<li>How could Joseph Smith have ideated that baptism was in the Old Testament? All records we have are that Joseph wasn’t very literate or well known in the Bible. He didn’t even know that Jerusalem had a wall and had to ask Emma (<a href="../book-review/saints-book-1-the-standard-of-truth-1815-1846.html">Saints Book 1 The Standard of Truth 1815-1846</a>) This strengthens my testimony that he was inspired in translating it</li>
<li>It makes sense to me how valuable the Book of Mormon is to answer these longstanding questions.</li>
<li>Those who are of the house of Israel are those who are baptized. The baptized are adopted into the Abrahamic family. This is is consistent with Galatians 3:</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For as many of you as have been baptized into Christ have put on Christ. 28 There is neither Jew nor Greek, there is neither bond nor free, there is neither male nor female: for ye are all one in Christ Jesus. 29 And if ye be Christ’s, then are ye Abraham’s seed, and heirs according to the promise. <a href="../scriptures/galatians-3.27-29">Galatians 3.27–29</a></p>
</blockquote>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>old testament</category>
  <category>Abrahamic Covenant</category>
  <category>baptism</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-20-baptism-in-the-old-testament.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 23:59:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 19 - Yieldeth Himself</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-19-yieldeth-himself.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>On Sunday I was thinking about <a href="../sacrament-symbols/bread-given-freely-like-his-life.html">Bread given freely, like His life</a>. It’s powerful to read this verse today:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And the God of our fathers, who were led out of Egypt, out of bondage, and also were preserved in the wilderness by him, yea, the God of Abraham, and of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, <strong>yieldeth himself</strong>, according to the words of the angel, as a man, into the hands of wicked men, to be lifted up, according to the words of Zenock, and to be crucified, according to the words of Neum, and to be buried in a sepulchre, according to the words of Zenos, which he spake concerning the three days of darkness, which should be a sign given of his death unto those who should inhabit the isles of the sea, more especially given unto those who are of the house of Israel. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-19.10">1 Nephi 19.10</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Also <a href="../sacrament-symbols/bread-in-the-oven.html">Bread in the Oven</a> post touches here.</p>
<p>He gave His life freely. He yielded himself.</p>
<p>So much doctrine is packed in this one verse:</p>
<ul>
<li>Christ had all power. He was a deity.</li>
<li>He obeyed the father.</li>
<li>He fulfilled prophesy.</li>
<li>He was the God of Abraham. He is distinct from the Father.</li>
<li>It was prophesied he would resurrect. Prophets in America knew this.</li>
<li>There is a space between death and the resurrection. Christ lived in that space for 3 days.</li>
<li>There are prophets who have testified of the Lord whom we don’t have records from.</li>
<li>Jesus delivered the Israelites. → the Israelites then delivered him unto the cross.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-cattle-ranch-gate.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The Lord is the rancher. He controls the gate. He delivers. We’re just wandering without him</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>Every scripture in the Book of Mormon can contain some or many truths about the Savior. There’s always something to learn.</p>
<p>Humility is the process of putting the Lord’s wishes above my own, as He put the Father’s wishes above perhaps his own (yet they are one).</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-19-yieldeth-himself.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 23:19:39 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 18 - The Power of Prayer</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-18-prayer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>Nephi has two powerful verses about prayer:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And I, Nephi, did go into the mount oft, and I did pray oft unto the Lord; wherefore the Lord showed unto me great things. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-18.3">1 Nephi 18.3</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>When we pray often, we are shown great things. And then after he’s tied up and being beaten by his brothers. According to what he wrote, this is the first thing he did when he was released:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass that I prayed unto the Lord; and after I had prayed the winds did cease, and the storm did cease, and there was a great calm. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-18.21">1 Nephi 18.21</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>Do I turn to the Lord the moment something goes wrong? <a href="christianity/turn-to-god-not-your-idols.md">Turn to God in All Things, and Not Your Idols</a></p>
<p>The winds in our life can cease when we turn to God.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>prayer</category>
  <category>adversity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-18-prayer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 23:24:13 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 17 - He will strengthen us</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-17-strength.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>Consider how the Lord provided for Nephi and his people</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And so great were the blessings of the Lord upon us, that while we did live upon raw meat in the wilderness, our women did give plenty of suck for their children, and were strong, yea, even like unto the men; and they began to bear their journeyings without murmurings.<br>
And thus we see that the commandments of God must be fulfilled. And if it so be that the children of men keep the commandments of God he <strong>doth nourish them, and strengthen them</strong>, and provide means whereby they can accomplish the thing which he has commanded them; wherefore, he did provide means for us while we did sojourn in the wilderness. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-17.2-3">1 Nephi 17.2–3</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-1-nephi-17-journey-in-wilderness.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Journeying"> # Meaning</p>
<p>The Lord intends to strengthen me to overcome the trials ahead, not to take them away. The purpose of the life is to be strengthen. Whenever we feel overwhelmed, we can take those things to the Lord.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>strength</category>
  <category>trust in the Lord</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-17-strength.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 18:08:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
