<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 23:59:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 20 - Baptism in the Old Testament</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-20-baptism-in-the-old-testament.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>The Isaiah chapters in Nephi often get skipped. But if you skip them, we miss out on important doctrine, like how “baptism” appears in the Nephi version of Isaiah 48 but not in the King James Version.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Hearken and hear this, O house of Jacob, who are called by the name of Israel, and are come forth out of the waters of Judah, or <strong>out of the waters of baptism</strong>, who swear by the name of the Lord, and make mention of the God of Israel, yet they swear not in truth nor in righteousness. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-20.1">1 Nephi 20.1</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-river-jordan-baptism.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Baptism</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>But if you compare to Isaiah 48, that line is not mentioned:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Hear ye this, O house of Jacob, which are called by the name of Israel, and are come forth out of the waters of Judah, which swear by the name of the Lord, and make mention of the God of Israel, but not in truth, nor in righteousness. <a href="../scriptures/isaiah-48.1">Isaiah 48.1</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The only reference to baptism in the Old Testament is found only in the chapter heading of 1 Kings 7:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The molten sea (baptismal font) rests on the backs of twelve oxen. <a href="../scriptures/1-kings-7">1 Kings 7</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is clearly one of the “plain and precious” things taken, or lost in translation, from the Bible:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>they have taken away from the gospel of the Lamb many parts which are plain and most precious; and <strong>also many covenants of the Lord have they taken away</strong>. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-13.26">1 Nephi 13.26</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But we know they practiced baptism in the Old Testament because Nephi lived and taught it, and the Pearl of Great Price talks about Adam’s baptism and ordination into the priesthood:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass, when the Lord had spoken with Adam, our father, that Adam cried unto the Lord, and he was caught away by the Spirit of the Lord, and was carried down into the water, and was laid under the water, and was brought forth out of the water. 65 And thus he was baptized, and the Spirit of God descended upon him, and thus he was born of the Spirit, and became quickened in the inner man. 66 And he heard a voice out of heaven, saying: Thou art baptized with fire, and with the Holy Ghost. This is the record of the Father, and the Son, from henceforth and forever; 67 And thou art after the order of him who was without beginning of days or end of years, from all eternity to all eternity. 68 Behold, thou art one in me, a son of God; and thus may all become my sons. Amen. <a href="../scriptures/moses-6.64-68">Moses 6.64–68</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<ul>
<li>It was cool to notice this today, as that verse popped out to me and that word “baptism”. It makes me wonder what else was taken from these Isaiah chapters</li>
<li>It makes sense to me how valuable the Book of Mormon is to answer these longstanding questions.</li>
<li>Those who are of the house of Israel are those who are baptized. The baptized are adopted into the Abrahamic family. This is is consistent with Galatians 3:</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For as many of you as have been baptized into Christ have put on Christ. 28 There is neither Jew nor Greek, there is neither bond nor free, there is neither male nor female: for ye are all one in Christ Jesus. 29 And if ye be Christ’s, then are ye Abraham’s seed, and heirs according to the promise. <a href="../scriptures/galatians-3.27-29">Galatians 3.27–29</a></p>
</blockquote>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>old testament</category>
  <category>Abrahamic Covenanf</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-20-baptism-in-the-old-testament.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 23:59:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Peloton</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/peloton.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I grew up with exercise equipment in my house, and like most equipment for most people, I didn’t use it. Part of the reason was it was hard to get going.</p>
<p>There’s nothing easier than hopping on an exercise bike. Having been a runner most of my life, when I first got the Peloton I realized how nice it was to get a solid workout in 20 minutes. It’s just so easy with the little kilojoule calculator there.</p>
<p>And it could be any exercise bike, really, but I’m grateful for the one I have.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-stationary-bike.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Maybe I’ll get a real bike someday</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/peloton.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 22:56:23 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Shift</title>
  <dc:creator>x </dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/shift.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 








<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/shift.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 22:34:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Holiday Demand Forecasting using XGBoost</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/demand-forecasting-using-xgboost.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://doordash.engineering/2023/08/31/how-doordash-improves-holiday-predictions-via-cascade-ml-approach/">How DoorDash Improves Holiday Predictions via Cascade ML Approach - DoorDash Engineering Blog</a></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Transform your raw data, removing spikes</li>
<li>Fit a trend like to the transformed data</li>
<li>Predict tomorrow using transformed predicfions</li>
<li>reverse The transformation to get expected numbers.</li>
</ol>
<p>It’s kinda of the principle behind differencing: it’s making more stationary a time series.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-doordash-holiday-xgboost.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Hi</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>data science</category>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>time series</category>
  <category>forecasting</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/demand-forecasting-using-xgboost.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 15:59:16 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Compounding Interest of Reading</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-compounding-interest-of-reading.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m on my way to get 52 books read this year. I think I can do it.</p>
<p>But it’s not to finish 52 books. It’s to read two hours of fifty two books. Why?</p>
<p>Because of compounding interest. One book doesn’t level you up. But multiple books over time will affect you for a long while to come.</p>
<p>If you improve just 1% each day for 365 days, and that improvement compounds, then you’ll have improved 37x over a year. (invest $100 and gain 1% each day and reinvest that money is $137 by the end of the year).</p>
<p>So don’t worry what any one book gives you. Just keep investing. A few will pay off big, and the many “wasted” will have little downside.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-image-compound-interest-and-reading-a-book.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Image: compound interest and reading a book</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>reading</category>
  <category>investing</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-compounding-interest-of-reading.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 12:17:17 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Power of a Good Book</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-power-of-a-good-book.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Last night I went to a tapas style restaurant. I got 5 things. Then we opted for one more: battered cod tacos. Our taste buds rewarded us. That’s why we came.</p>
<p>Before that I was telling my wife, “I don’t see why my friend didn’t like the sushi. It’s fine. I just don’t know how to evaluate if something is worth it or not. Because it’s tasty, I’d recommend it…” This came off the heels of multiple times recently where I’ve gone out with people who are foodies that criticize the meal I’m enjoying and I’m left wondering: am I a food plebe?</p>
<p>Experiencing this last night was poignant. The whole meal was good. Not bad. Just good.</p>
<p>Then came the fish tacos.</p>
<p>That’s how it is with reading. You need to read a lot before the good and the bad start filtering out.</p>
<p>And like fish tacos, maybe there are even better ones out there, but I needed this one to point me in the direction of what’s possible.</p>
<p>And to some degree, there’s a dulling of sensitivities. If you haven’t read good literature in a long while perhaps you assume it’s all fine and “why <em>not</em> finish this book?”</p>
<p>But this year I’m trying to read many authors across many genres to tackle just that: find the books I really enjoy reading. And then ask myself, “why? What was special there?” So that I know what to look for next.</p>
<p>Last night I began <a href="../book-review/the-old-man-and-the-sea.html">The Old Man and the Sea</a> and it was a fish taco moment. I don’t know how I’ve avoided this book so long. I’m sure I read it in like sixth grade, but does that even count? And why have I largely avoided fiction for most of my adult life? I suppose having studied something very technical in college it pushed me to stop using that side of my brain. But getting back to good books, written with such depth and creative imagination, renew me with an awareness of the dullness of business books I’ve been dwelling in.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-old-man-and-the-fish-tacos.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">An Old Man and His Tacos</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And now, for ChatGPT to answer the prompt: “in the style of Ernest Hemingway, write three paragraphs about a man eating fish tacos”:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In the style of Ernest Hemingway, characterized by his terse and direct prose, the tale unfolds on a weathered pier stretching into the gray, restless sea. The man, solitary and rugged, sits at the edge where the wood meets the water, a plate of fish tacos beside him. His hands, calloused and strong, deftly assemble the tacos with an economy of movement that speaks of a life shaped by necessity rather than choice. The fish, freshly caught, bears the scent of the ocean, a fragrance as old as time, mingling with the sharp tang of lime and cilantro.</p>
<p>Around him, the world seems to hold its breath, the only sounds are the soft lapping of waves against the pilings and the distant cries of gulls, wheeling like specters in the overcast sky. He bites into a taco, the crispness of the tortilla giving way to the tender fish within, a simplicity that belies the depth of flavors. There’s a harmony here, between man and nature, a momentary peace found in the act of eating, of sustaining oneself with the bounty of the sea.</p>
<p>As he eats, his gaze is drawn to the horizon, where the gray of the sea blends indistinguishably with the sky. There’s a contemplation in his eyes, a man adrift in his thoughts as he is in life, finding solace in the simple pleasure of a meal. The tacos, humble yet fulfilling, become a metaphor for existence itself—uncomplicated in its components, yet profound in its satisfaction. In this moment, on this pier, the man and the sea are one, their stories intertwined in the quiet, unspoken understanding that life, in all its forms, is a series of solitary moments shared with the world.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Dang…“life shaped by necessity rather than choice” and “The tacos, humble yet fulfilling, become a metaphor for existence itself—uncomplicated in its components, yet profound in its satisfaction.” I’m glad Ernest is somewhere in there, AI. You may have a soul after all.</p>
<p>See also: <a href="../lists/reading-ethos.html">Reading Ethos</a></p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>reading</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-power-of-a-good-book.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 11:48:38 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1984</title>
  <dc:creator>x </dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/1984.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 








<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/1984.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 11:27:42 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Private GPT</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/private-gpt.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="private-gpt" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Private GPT</h1>
<p><a href="https://www.privategpt.io/">PrivateGPT</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-privategpt.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Private GPT</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Chat with your notes.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XFiof0V3nhA?si=wPsCtfPbYuB9MQvm" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>ai tools</category>
  <category>privacy</category>
  <category>open source</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/private-gpt.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 10:02:48 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>LM Studio</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/lm-studio.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="description" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>description</h1>
<p><a href="https://lmstudio.ai/">LM Studio - Discover, download, and run local LLMs</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-lm-studio.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">LM Studio</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>ai tools</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/lm-studio.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 09:54:19 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>GPT4All</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/gpt4all.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="description" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>description</h1>
<p><a href="https://gpt4all.io/index.html">GPT4All</a> train and deploy customized LLMs.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-gpt4all.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Gpt4all screenshot</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="similar-tools" class="level1">
<h1>similar tools</h1>
<p>Seems like a different use case than <a href="../tech/lm-studio.html">LM Studio</a>, but hard to say. <a href="../tech/lm-studio.html">LM Studio</a> is likely focused on people wanting to download and use the open source models, where this is to help you train and fine tune locally.</p>
<p>Use it to connect with your notes:</p>
<p><a href="https://medium.com/@vikastiwari708409/how-to-use-gpt4all-llms-with-langchain-to-work-with-pdf-files-f0f0becadcb6">How to Use GPT4All with Langchain to Chat with Your Documents | by Vikas Tiwari | Medium</a></p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/X8QbEENUZIo" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>ai tools</category>
  <category>edge device</category>
  <category>privacy</category>
  <category>open source</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/gpt4all.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 09:49:48 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Beam AI</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/beam-ai.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="description" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>description</h1>
<p>Runs GPT locally, has tons of templates, can interact with your screen. Run ChatGPT plus locally.</p>
<p>I have not used it. Just thought it’s cool. # commentary I don’t see why Open AI can’t build something like this, but they’re focused on much higher value problems such as solving enterprise hunger.</p>
<p>So we’ll see niche tools like this that pop up and solve the needs of a few - satisfying the developer costs of some indie programmers. thinking of Innovators Dilemma, there’s just not enough juice in this lemon for Open AI to squeeze, but plenty for a small fish.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-get-beam-ai.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Beam AI</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>ai tools</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>local ai</category>
  <category>privacy</category>
  <category>edge device</category>
  <category>closed source</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/beam-ai.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 09:44:08 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Compliments</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/compliments.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m grateful for compliments. The ones I receive and the ones I can give.</p>
<p>The cheapest thing you can give someone is a compliment. Yet it may be the most valuable gift to be given.</p>
<p>I’m reading <a href="../book-review/influence-the-psychology-of-persuasion.html">Influence The Psychology of Persuasion</a> which talks about “reciprocity”. People feel someone obligated to help you when you give them something, even if it’s nominal. Isn’t a compliment a gift?</p>
<p><a href="../book-review/how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people.html">How to Win Friends and Influence People</a> also discusses the benefits of being kind, and putting yourself in another’s shoes. Kindness far exceeds the benefits of criticism. A compliment is a way to think about what that person may want to hear and to give them that. Not in an insincere way, but in a sincere way.</p>
<p>People act how they want to be treated. If they show up to play basketball they want to be told they’re good at basketball. If they work on a task for you, it’s because they want to be told they’re good at that task. It doesn’t hurt to be nice. To give a compliment. So give away.</p>
<p>Being human is recognizing what other people aspire for and recognize that goodness in them. So notice. Notice what they’re after. Then give. Give freely, for so did He (<a href="../sacrament-symbols/bread-given-freely-like-his-life.html">Bread given freely, like His life</a>).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-compliment-giving.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Giving a compliment is giving life to someone</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <category>charity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/compliments.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 23:46:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 19 - Yieldeth Himself</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-19-yieldeth-himself.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>On Sunday I was thinking about <a href="../sacrament-symbols/bread-given-freely-like-his-life.html">Bread given freely, like His life</a>. It’s powerful to read this verse today:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And the God of our fathers, who were led out of Egypt, out of bondage, and also were preserved in the wilderness by him, yea, the God of Abraham, and of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, <strong>yieldeth himself</strong>, according to the words of the angel, as a man, into the hands of wicked men, to be lifted up, according to the words of Zenock, and to be crucified, according to the words of Neum, and to be buried in a sepulchre, according to the words of Zenos, which he spake concerning the three days of darkness, which should be a sign given of his death unto those who should inhabit the isles of the sea, more especially given unto those who are of the house of Israel. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-19.10">1 Nephi 19.10</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Also <a href="../sacrament-symbols/bread-in-the-oven.html">Bread in the Oven</a> post touches here.</p>
<p>He gave His life freely. He yielded himself.</p>
<p>So much doctrine is packed in this one verse:</p>
<ul>
<li>Christ had all power. He was a deity.</li>
<li>He obeyed the father.</li>
<li>He fulfilled prophesy.</li>
<li>He was the God of Abraham. He is distinct from the Father.</li>
<li>It was prophesied he would resurrect. Prophets in America knew this.</li>
<li>There is a space between death and the resurrection. Christ lived in that space for 3 days.</li>
<li>There are prophets who have testified of the Lord whom we don’t have records from.</li>
<li>Jesus delivered the Israelites. → the Israelites then delivered him unto the cross.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-cattle-ranch-gate.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="The Lord is the rancher. He controls the gate. He delivers. We’re just wandering without him"> # Meaning</p>
<p>Every scripture in the Book of Mormon can contain some or many truths about the Savior. There’s always something to learn.</p>
<p>Humility is the process of putting the Lord’s wishes above my own, as He put the Father’s wishes above perhaps his own (yet they are one).</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-19-yieldeth-himself.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 23:19:39 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Old Man and the Sea</title>
  <dc:creator>Ernest Hemingway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/the-old-man-and-the-sea.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>2024-02-02</p>
<ul>
<li>thank goodness they’re not as intelligent as those who kill them, though they’re more noble and able</li>
<li>Let him believe I am more man than I AM and I will be so</li>
<li>“The thousand times he had proved it didn’t matter now. He needs to prove it again anew that he’s a man”</li>
</ul>
<p>Storytelling</p>
<ul>
<li>I love how he speaks a thought, then follows up with reality. Like “come on, catch the hook” “but the hook did not catch”</li>
<li>Repetitive words used in new ways evoke new meaning</li>
<li>Keep it simple. <a href="../posts/mark-cuban-mogul-support.html">Mark Cuban Mogul Support</a> - don’t use a big word when a simpler one will do. He evokes strong emotion without much fanciful language.</li>
<li>Your mind fills in the blanks. He encodes the intuition of 50 years of fishing in plain words. “I’ve got enough line…” is not a calculation. <a href="../book-review/wool.html">Wool</a> and <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a> are much more</li>
</ul>
<p>2024-02-01 - first you borrow. Then you beg. - “This too was a fiction” - “Relics of his wife” - he waits to reveal his wife. - I was born for this. - He could think of nothing except endure <img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-the-old-man-and-the-sea.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="The Old Man and The Sea"></p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <category>fiction</category>
  <category>classics</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/the-old-man-and-the-sea.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 21:27:44 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Export your Libby Timeline to Obsidian</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/export-your-libby-timeline-to-obsidian.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I love reading and I love writing. Both are integral parts of learning. The reading to receive new ideas, the writing to cement those ideas to something.</p>
<p>As I stood up my blog I wondered how to get past books on here. There’s a way!</p>
<p>I now use Audible and Spotify audiobooks, but most of my past reads come from Libby.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-libby-icon.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Libby</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Here’s how you do it using Python:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Open Libby app and figure out how to export your timeline. Somewhere in settings. It’ll produce a CSV.</li>
<li>Go through that CSV and creat a column “read” that identified the ones you actually began (sigh…so many books I placed holds on but never read….)</li>
<li>Run this python script and it’ll create an obsidian markdown file for each. Tweak it to match your preferences. I personally use <code>quarto</code> to blog so I have a naming convention for the files and metadata.</li>
<li>Or! Just ask ChatGPT to do this for you lol.</li>
</ol>
<pre><code>from datetime import datetime, timedelta
import pandas as pd
import os
import zipfile
import re

# Load the provided spreadsheet using pandas
file_path = "~/Downloads/libbytimeline-activities.csv"
df = pd.read_csv(file_path)

# Parse the timestamp into the format yyyy-mm-dd and rename the column to 'date'
df["timestamp_raw"] = df["timestamp"]
df["timestamp"] = pd.to_datetime(df["timestamp"], format="%m/%d/%y %H:%M")
# create a stringed date
df["date"] = df["timestamp"].dt.strftime("%Y-%m-%d")

df[["date", "timestamp_raw"]]

# Custom column: Filter rows where read == 1 (went through spreadsheet to filter out those I had borrowed but never read).
df = df[df["read"] == 1]

# De-duplicate by title, keeping the most recent record (sorted by date)
df = df.sort_values("timestamp", ascending=False).drop_duplicates("title")

# Create a new column 'created' with today's date in yyyy-mm-dd format
today = datetime.now().strftime("%Y-%m-%d")
df["created"] = today

# Create a new column 'date-finished' that's the timestamp's date + 21 days
df["date-finished"] = (df["timestamp"] + timedelta(days=21)).dt.strftime("%Y-%m-%d")

# Prepare for markdown file creation
output_directory = os.path.expanduser("~/Desktop/markdown_files")
os.makedirs(output_directory, exist_ok=True)

# Loop through each item in the dataframe and create a markdown file
for index, row in df.iterrows():
    markdown_content = f"""
---
title: {row['title']}
description: _{row['title']}_ by {row['author']}. Published by {row['publisher']}, with ISBN {row['isbn']}. Read on {row['date']}
date: {row['date']}
categories: book-review
created: {row['created']}
draft: false
author: {row['author']}
book-year: 1000
book-time: 0
date-start: {row['date']}
date-finished: {row['date-finished']}
pct-complete: 0
---

![]({row['cover']}){{.preview-image}}
"""
    filename = re.sub(r"[^\w]", "-", row["title"]).lower()
    filename = re.sub(r"-+", "-", filename)
    file_path = os.path.join(output_directory, f"{filename}.md")
    with open(file_path, "w") as file:
        file.write(markdown_content.strip())
    print(f"Created {file_path}")

# Zip the markdown files
zip_file_path = os.path.expanduser("~/Desktop/markdown_files.zip")
with zipfile.ZipFile(zip_file_path, "w") as zipf:
    for root, dirs, files in os.walk(output_directory):
        for file in files:
            zipf.write(os.path.join(root, file), file)</code></pre>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>tutorial</category>
  <category>python</category>
  <category>libby</category>
  <category>quarto</category>
  <category>blogging</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/export-your-libby-timeline-to-obsidian.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 14:32:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Basketball</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/basketball.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Just played some ball tonight. Not sure who invented this game, but it’s really come a long way.</p>
<p>The cool thing is that you can be horrible at shooting and still find a way to contribute. There are a lot of skills and abilities that make a good team.</p>
<p>I play with the same 20 guys, and it’s amazing how different combinations of 5 people play so differently. The flow, the passing, the defense - it all varies with who’ve you got on the court. And that’s what makes it fun. Sometimes you contribute more. Sometimes less.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/Dalle-basketball.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Basketball</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’ve played it my whole life, though never well. I played in rec leagues in college. In rec leagues in high school. And now with a bunch of folks who just love the game. And that’s why it’s fun: it brings people together.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/basketball.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 23:44:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 18 - The Power of Prayer</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-18-prayer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>Nephi has two powerful verses about prayer:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And I, Nephi, did go into the mount oft, and I did pray oft unto the Lord; wherefore the Lord showed unto me great things. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-18.3">1 Nephi 18.3</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>When we pray often, we are shown great things. And then after he’s tied up and being beaten by his brothers. According to what he wrote, this is the first thing he did when he was released:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass that I prayed unto the Lord; and after I had prayed the winds did cease, and the storm did cease, and there was a great calm. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-18.21">1 Nephi 18.21</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>Do I turn to the Lord the moment something goes wrong? <a href="christianity/turn-to-god-not-your-idols.md">Turn to God in All Things, and Not Your Idols</a></p>
<p>The winds in our life can cease when we turn to God.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>prayer</category>
  <category>adversity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-18-prayer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 23:24:13 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Loop</title>
  <dc:creator>Jacob Ward</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/the-loop.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-the-loop.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The Loop</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/the-loop.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 22:41:22 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Influence The Psychology of Persuasion</title>
  <dc:creator>Robert Cialdini</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/influence-the-psychology-of-persuasion.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>2024-01-30 - Ackerman method from <a href="../book-review/never-split-the-difference.html">Never Split the Difference</a> applies to the concept of anchoring. Better to anchor at $2 then tell them $200 off than play a joke at $10000 but only offer $200. - Reciprocity - the small things compound over time. Give more than you expect to get. - “Because”. Giving reasons is persuasive, that word is a trigger.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-influence-the-psychology-of-persuasion.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Influence</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/influence-the-psychology-of-persuasion.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 20:31:02 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 17 - He will strengthen us</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-17-strength.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>Consider how the Lord provided for Nephi and his people</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And so great were the blessings of the Lord upon us, that while we did live upon raw meat in the wilderness, our women did give plenty of suck for their children, and were strong, yea, even like unto the men; and they began to bear their journeyings without murmurings.<br>
And thus we see that the commandments of God must be fulfilled. And if it so be that the children of men keep the commandments of God he <strong>doth nourish them, and strengthen them</strong>, and provide means whereby they can accomplish the thing which he has commanded them; wherefore, he did provide means for us while we did sojourn in the wilderness. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-17.2-3">1 Nephi 17.2–3</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-1-nephi-17-journey-in-wilderness.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Journeying"> # Meaning</p>
<p>The Lord intends to strengthen me to overcome the trials ahead, not to take them away. The purpose of the life is to be strengthen. Whenever we feel overwhelmed, we can take those things to the Lord.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>strength</category>
  <category>trust in the Lord</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-17-strength.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 18:08:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
