<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 21:38:47 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 27 The Purpose of the Book of Mormon</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-27-the-purpose-of-the-book-of-mormon.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>This chapter doesn’t lay about all the purposes of the Book of Mormon, but it lays out some.</p>
<p>Purpose: help people eat and be filled. The souls who aren’t fed are like hungry men who dream of eating but awake empty.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And all the nations that fight against Zion, and that distress her, shall be as a dream of a night vision; yea, it shall be unto them, even as unto a hungry man which dreameth, and behold he eateth but he awaketh and his soul is empty; or like unto a thirsty man which dreameth, and behold he drinketh but he awaketh and behold he is faint, and his soul hath appetite; yea, even so shall the multitude of all the nations be that fight against Mount Zion. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-27.3">2 Nephi 27.3</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The book is a revelation. It’s a miracle in itself. It’s a witness of all things, and a testament of its translator.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And behold the book shall be sealed; and in the book shall be a revelation from God, from the beginning of the world to the ending thereof. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-27.7">2 Nephi 27.7</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It will be a revelation of the doctrines that have been taught since the foundation of the world and will be taught until the end of it:<sup>1</sup></p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And the day cometh that the words of the book which were sealed shall be read upon the house tops; and they shall be read by the power of Christ; and all things shall be revealed unto the children of men which ever have been among the children of men, and which ever will be even unto the end of the earth. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-27.11">2 Nephi 27.11</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Evidence that this is the Lord’s work, because he turned a plow boy into a translator of a sealed book:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Then shall the Lord God say unto him: The learned shall not read them, for they have rejected them, and I am able to do mine own work; wherefore thou shalt read the words which I shall give unto thee. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-27.20">2 Nephi 27.20</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Lord will do a marvelous work through this book. It’ll be the means of converting people to Him and His gospel:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Therefore, I will proceed to do a marvelous work among this people, yea, a marvelous work and a wonder, for the wisdom of their wise and learned shall perish, and the understanding of their prudent shall be hid. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-27.26">2 Nephi 27.26</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>This teaches me that the Lord is doing His work. That I have a role in this work.</p>


</section>
<aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>it’s incredible how when you read this you want to know what those hidden mysteries are. When in reality it’s the simple things that have always been taught: the gospel of faith, repentance, baptism, and receiving the Holy Ghost.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</aside>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-27-the-purpose-of-the-book-of-mormon.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 21:38:47 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Freedom of Religion</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/freedom-of-religion.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m grateful for the freedom of religion. I’m reading <a href="../book-review/the-happiest-man-on-earth.html">The Happiest Man on Earth</a> right now and cannot fathom the horrid experiences Eddie had to endure.</p>
<p>When we (as humans) start labeling and blaming groups of people for our problems, we begin dehumanizing them and they’re no longer worth anything to us. And if we have power, we can choose to destroy them.</p>
<p>It’s incredible how depraved humanity can become. It happened to the Germans, but it can happen anywhere. It happened in the U.S. with slavery and civil rights failures.</p>
<p>I’m grateful for the freedom of religion. It hasn’t always been free. My ancestors were shot at in Missouri and driven from their home in Nauvoo to cross the plains in the winter with nothing but dirt to eat to pacify their hunger.</p>
<p>They crawled on their hands in the frozen tundra because it’s all they could do.</p>
<p>Some survived. But not all.</p>
<p>Today I enjoy freedoms they didn’t have. The freedom to not have to cross a frozen tundra on my hands and feet because I’m a member of <a href="../concepts/the-church-of-jesus-christ-of-latter-day-saints.html">The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints</a>.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>family history</category>
  <category>pioneers</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/freedom-of-religion.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 21:33:18 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How I Learn and How to Hack the Audio Book and Speed Reading Game</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/how-i-learn.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’ve been overdosing slightly on learning lately.</p>
<p>Ever since I got off social media, I got into writing (<a href="../tech/a-knife-to-a-gun-fight.html">A Knife to a Gun Fight: Why I’m off Social Media</a>), and listening to audio books.</p>
<p>Podcasts are fine, but they’re about as quality as top-of-mind thinking. Books are usually far more instructive because each sentence is reviewed at least a few times if not a hundred times during the editing process.</p>
<p>I noticed that once I started binging books instead of posts, my happiness and satisfaction increased.</p>
<p>Here’s a strategy I’m using for learning.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Get Audible and Spotify subscriptions. It has books that aren’t available on Libby (which I also use).</li>
<li>Stock up on free books using Libby. Hold times vary, but can be a few weeks or months for popular titles. Note: you can supply multiple library accounts.</li>
<li>For short books not on Libby, check Audible free catalog. If it’s not in the Audible free catalog, check Spotify Premium listening, which is 15 hours per month. If you listen to short books on Spotify, you can get 2-3 books in 15 hours. (It’s 15 book hours, not listening hours.) Also, if your phone is locked, you can go beyond the 15 hours (don’t report this…). But once you re open the app the 15 hour limit will halt you. 2-3 books would otherwise be $20-45 dollars depending on the cost of the audio book. $12 for Spotify premium is a deal.</li>
<li>Use Audible credits for books you can’t find on Libby or Spotify. Remember, Audible is $15 per month. So don’t waste it on a $4 book. Buy the expensive books or &gt;15 hour books with the credits.</li>
<li>With all the cash savings, and if you still have time, now you can buy the remaining books you want on either Audible and Spotify.</li>
</ol>
<p>Most books are on Libby. Domain specific books and cutting edge releases books are on Audible. Lots of great in between books on Spotify Premium.</p>
<p>I don’t know why but after 50 books you get a sense for what books are going to be available where.</p>
<p>Lastly, on Chrome I use the SwiftRead extension for speed reading and on iOS the <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/outread-speed-reading/id778846279">Outread</a> app.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>life hacks</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/how-i-learn.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 16:18:34 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Happiest Man on Earth</title>
  <dc:creator>Eddie Jaku</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/the-happiest-man-on-earth.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>2024-03-15</p>
<ul>
<li>he escaped and was shot at and returned</li>
<li>1 hour of rest is two days of survival. Conserving energy.</li>
<li>Running to the wire.</li>
<li>I could not have survived without friends. Without Kurt.</li>
<li>Shave heads to be free from lice.</li>
<li>Bromide in the coffee. Chemically castrate.</li>
<li>one louse meant the whole house to be burned.</li>
<li>Examined by the weight of your buttocks</li>
<li>The body is the best machine.</li>
<li>“Don’t you have a soul?” → he wasn’t so courageous when he was alone. He never hit me again.</li>
<li>My education saved me.</li>
<li>Where there is hope there is life.</li>
<li>I know many who took their own life when they were liberated because they had nothing to live for.</li>
<li>Hides in a sewage pipe.</li>
<li>Crawled out of a cave to a road.</li>
<li>Finds Kurt. Always a miracle.</li>
<li>Old anti semitic attitudes are hard to fade. “Greedy Jews” after he gets a job.</li>
<li>Sulfer baths.</li>
<li>Rescues 3 women from suicide. Duty of the fortunate to help the suffering. Simple act of kindness → saved the life of these women.</li>
<li>Found someone in his suit.</li>
</ul>
<p>Happiness - you’ll never be happy with comparison. - Loved saved me. - Happiness comes from inside. Happiness doubles each time you share it.</p>
<p>2024-03-14</p>
<ul>
<li>Germans made a religion of logic, and it turned them cruel</li>
<li>The dichotomy that you could be fined 200 franks for littering a cigarette butt and yet they threw children into the river,</li>
<li>Crystallnacht. Broken glass.</li>
<li>What would have happened had he not returned home that night?</li>
<li>“I made the worst decision”. It’s what you say, but the decision itself to visit family was perhaps a good one. Resulting.</li>
<li>“Are you hungry?” → the French did the most to help Jews.</li>
<li>1936 for Spanish people leaving the Spanish civil war.</li>
<li>15,000 prison</li>
<li>Trains filled with fumes</li>
<li>Doctor who used a razor to suicide over a latrine</li>
<li>2.5 months to walk through France, to get caught while using the toilet. Parachuter.</li>
<li>Escape bottom of train. Week hopping on and off trains.</li>
<li>Train car with 44 liters of water for the whole train. His dad rationed 155 cups.</li>
<li>“go tell your mother how much you love her. Do it for your new friend, Eddie, who cannot”. Sent to gas chambers.</li>
<li>How could Hitler make enemies of friends, then civilized men into inhuman zombies. How could Hitler create such hate?</li>
<li>Go to sleep naked. Wake up with naked</li>
<li>Rags were more precious than gold.</li>
<li>Germans were detailed and record keepers, which made them killers.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-the-happiest-man-on-earth.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The Happiest Man on Earth</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <category>ww2</category>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <category>biography</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/the-happiest-man-on-earth.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 15:56:22 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Kids jumping on me</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/kids-jumping-on-me.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It won’t be long before they don’t jump on me anymore. I can’t help but think of how quickly it’ll have all gone by.</p>
<p>But I do cherish it. The tackle time. The giggles. The tickles. They need it. I need it.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/kids-jumping-on-me.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2024 23:19:13 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 26 - pride</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-26-pride.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And the Gentiles are lifted up in the pride of their eyes, and have stumbled, because of the greatness of their stumbling block, that they have built up many churches; nevertheless, they put down the power and miracles of God, and preach up unto themselves their own wisdom and their own learning, that they may get gain and grind upon the face of the poor. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-26.20">2 Nephi 26.20</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>I think I’ve always assumed that Nephi saw the restoration and then saw the second coming. And that’s it. That’s kind of how it reads.</p>
<p>But as I ponder this I wonder how much he saw. Did he see 2024? Did he see what my people would be going through? Probably. Perhaps.</p>
<p>Assuming he did, and that this was written about today, what are the churches that have risen up to get gain? Probably people with pride in their heart.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-26-pride.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2024 23:16:17 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Devin the AI coder</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/devin-the-ai-coder.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.cognition-labs.com/blog">Blog</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Devin is hooked up to a terminal, the internet, and the code base</li>
<li>Can solve some problems and to end</li>
<li>Let’s you help be involved in the process</li>
</ul>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>ai tools</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/devin-the-ai-coder.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2024 21:15:17 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 26</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-26.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>Nephi sees what happens to his people 600 years into the future. They suffer a lot, and are almost destroyed.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>But the Son of Righteousness shall appear unto them; and he shall heal them, and they shall have peace with him, until three generations shall have passed away, and many of the fourth generation shall have passed away in righteousness. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-26.9">2 Nephi 26.9</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>The Savior heals. He is the One Who Comes. Who has come. Who will come.</p>
<p>It doesn’t matter anymore to me <em>when</em> he’ll return. Just <em>that</em> he’s retuning. This is a beautiful perspective.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-26.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 23:51:15 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for A sleeping baby</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/a-sleeping-baby.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Every night I put my daughter down to bed. It’s a sweet moment. She lays helplessly in my arms. I helplessly hold her.</p>
<p>Babies come into the world with so much trust. Trust I’ll do right by her.</p>
<p>And seeing her sleep is the best part.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/a-sleeping-baby.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 23:43:36 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The 6 Types of Working Genius</title>
  <dc:creator>Patrick Lencioni</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/the-6-types-of-working-genius.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Summary:</p>
<ul>
<li>about 70% of an instructive story and 30% the true content. The story is really cringe/cheesy but helps introduce the ideas.</li>
<li>Back 30% presents the concrete definitions. It lays out how a team can truly work together as a team to complement each other’s strengths.</li>
</ul>
<p>2024-03-11</p>
<p><a href="https://www.shortform.com/blog/the-6-types-of-working-genius/">The 6 Types of Working Genius: Book Overview | Shortform Books</a></p>
<p>We all have things that either energize or drain us. If we’re aware, we can complement each other.</p>
<p>Three phases of work/a task: ideation, activation, and implementation. Each task requires two types of genius.</p>
<ul>
<li>Ideation
<ul>
<li>Wonder: Ask why? Ask “is there a better way?”</li>
<li>Innovation: figure out solutions.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Activation
<ul>
<li>Discernment: use intuition and judgment in figuring out good/bad ideas</li>
<li>Galvanize/rally people/buy-in</li>
</ul></li>
<li>implementation
<ul>
<li>Enable: volunteer. Help people. Empower.</li>
<li>Tenacity: cross the finish line. Execute. Pound obstacles.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>Six type of genius more concretely defined:</p>
<ul>
<li>Wonder: Involved the ability to ponder, speculate, and question the state of things. Asking the questions that provoke answer and action. People with this genius are naturally inclined to do these things, to lose themselves in observing the world around them and wondering if things shouldn’t be different or untapped potential that should be tapped.</li>
<li>Innovation: come up with new ideas or solutions. They’re drawn to origination, creativity and ingenuity, even with little context or directions. Though every type is a genius, these are the people who are most often referred to as geniuses because many of their ideas seem to come out of thin air.</li>
<li>Discernment: related to sanctity, intuition, and uncanny judgment. People with this genius have the natural ability to assess an idea or situation even without a lot of data or expertises. Using pattern recognition and gut feel they’re able to provide valuable advice and feedback around most subjects in a way that transcends their levels of specific knowledge or information.</li>
<li>Galvanizing: is about rallying, motivating, or provoking people to take action around an idea or an initiative. People with this genius are naturally inclined to inspire or enlist people to get involved in an endeavor. They don’t mind persuading people to rethink or change their plans to embark on something worthwhile.</li>
<li>Enabling: providing people with support and assistance in a way that it is needed. People with this genius are adept at responding to the needs of others without conditions or restrictions. They’re naturally inclined to help others accomplish their goals and can often anticipate what people might need before they ask. Individuals with this genius are frequently unaware that this is a genius at all.</li>
<li>Tenacity: is about the satisfaction of pushing things across the finish line to completion. They’re not only capable of and naturally inclined to finish projects to ensure they’re completed to specification. They gain energy by pushing through obstacles and seeing the impact of their work and they find joy from crossing tasks off their list and getting closure.</li>
</ul>
<p>Categories of genius - each person has two geniuses, two competencies, and two frustrations. (Per their research)</p>
<ul>
<li>Genius: it energizes you. Joy, energy, and passion.</li>
<li>Competency: it neither energizes nor drains you. Can do fairly well. But we will eventually grow weary if we can do our geniuses.</li>
<li>Frustration: it drains you. Struggle. Hate it. You can spent a ton of time here without getting to burnout, or failure.</li>
</ul>
<p>Genius activation modes: you’ll probably have two responsive and two disruptive geniuses.</p>
<ul>
<li>Responsive: respond to an external stimulus to be put into action. Need to be activated by an event.</li>
<li>Disruptive: initiate or provoke change when they see a need for it. More proactive.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-the-6-types-of-working-genius.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Book cover</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <category>productivity</category>
  <category>personality</category>
  <category>culture</category>
  <category>team building</category>
  <category>teamwork</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/the-6-types-of-working-genius.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 20:57:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>News Notes for 2024-03-11</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/news/2024-03-11-news-notes.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Mar/8/gpt-4-barrier/">The GPT-4 barrier has finally been broken</a></p>
<ul>
<li>this doesn’t even mention Llama or apple’s Ferret <a href="https://github.com/apple/ml-ferret">ferret</a></li>
<li><a href="https://generativeai.pub/hushed-arrival-of-apples-open-source-multimodal-llm-called-ferret-a-commitment-to-open-and-239a0285a866">Hushed Arrival of Apple’s Open Source Multimodal LLM called Ferret: A Commitment to Open and Responsible AI or Strategic Power Play? | by Miz Causevic | Generative AI</a></li>
</ul>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/news/2024-03-11-news-notes.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 19:30:57 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Light GBM Documentation</title>
  <dc:creator>x </dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/light-gbm-documentation.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’ve been a long-time XGBoost user, so I want to upskill.</p>
<p><a href="https://lightgbm.readthedocs.io/en/stable/">Welcome to LightGBM’s documentation! — LightGBM 4.0.0 documentation</a></p>
<p>2024-03-14</p>
<section id="experiments" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="experiments">Experiments:</h2>
<p>Features:</p>
<p>Differences:</p>
<ul>
<li>Grow’s leaf wise, not level wise.</li>
<li>Memory management</li>
<li>uses histograms rather than exact splits.</li>
<li>Better default category management.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-light-gbm-documentation.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Light GBM</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <category>upskilling</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>data science</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/light-gbm-documentation.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 16:19:29 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Forecasting: Principles and Practice</title>
  <dc:creator>Rob Hyndman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/forecasting-principles-and-practice.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>#Forecasting #timeseries #datascience #machinelearning #ForecastingPrinciplesAndPractice</p>
<p><a href="https://otexts.com/fpp3/intro.html">Chapter 1 Getting started | Forecasting: Principles&nbsp;and&nbsp;Practice (3rd&nbsp;ed)</a></p>
<p>2024-03-15</p>
<p><a href="https://otexts.com/fpp3/data-methods.html">1.4 Forecasting data and methods | Forecasting: Principles&nbsp;and&nbsp;Practice (3rd&nbsp;ed)</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Two types of models: incorporate external data or is only based on time events.</li>
<li>Judgmental forecasts vs qualitative forecasts. (Superforecasters )</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Occasionally, old data will be less useful due to structural changes in the system being forecast; then we may choose to use only the most recent data</p>
</blockquote>
<p>2024-03-11</p>
<ul>
<li>People have always wanted to forecast, such as ancients using the shape of sheep liver to predict the future. Tarot cards, prophets, etc have been religious and spiritual forecasters.</li>
<li>Forecasting has always been a guessing game.</li>
<li>Sometimes you can use algorithms to mine historical data for forecasting, but that assumes the future will be like the past.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-forecasting-principles-and-practice.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Forecasting</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <category>data science</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>upskilling</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/forecasting-principles-and-practice.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 10:38:10 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for I’m grateful for logicians</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/im-grateful-for-logicians.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It’s great fun reading <a href="../book-review/mere-christianity.html">Mere Christianity</a> because I’ve thought about several of these things before and am now just seeing him write about it much more effectively. I’m grateful for people who are good writers.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/im-grateful-for-logicians.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 23:48:46 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 21.6</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-21-the-wolf-and-the-lamb.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The wolf also shall dwell with the lamb, and the leopard shall lie down with the kid, and the calf and the young lion and fatling together; and a little child shall lead them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>See <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/2-ne/21?id=p6&amp;lang=eng#p6">2 Nephi 21.6</a></p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>favorite scriptures</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-21-the-wolf-and-the-lamb.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 20-25 Lesson Plan</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-20-25-lesson-plan.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And, notwithstanding we believe in Christ, we keep the law of Moses, and look forward with steadfastness unto Christ, until the law shall be fulfilled. 25 For, for this end was the law given; wherefore the law hath become dead unto us, and we are made alive in Christ because of our faith; yet we keep the law because of the commandments. 26 And we talk of Christ, we rejoice in Christ, we preach of Christ, we prophesy of Christ, and we write according to our prophecies, that our children may know to what source they may look for a remission of their sins. 27 Wherefore, we speak concerning the law that our children may know the deadness of the law; and they, by knowing the deadness of the law, may look forward unto that life which is in Christ, and know for what end the law was given. And after the law is fulfilled in Christ, that they need not harden their hearts against him when the law ought to be done away. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-25.24-27">2 Nephi 25.24–27</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Law of Moses: rules when they’re kids.</p>
<ul>
<li>the purpose of the law.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>come follow me lesson plan</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-20-25-lesson-plan.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 23:58:03 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Book Summaries</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/book-summaries.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="../book-review/beyond-band-of-brothers.html">Beyond Band of Brothers: The War Memoirs of Major Dick Winters</a></p>
<p>Leadership from the bayonette. 10 points of leadership by dick winters.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Strive to be a leader of character, competence, and courage.</li>
<li>Lead from the front. Say, “Follow me!” and then lead the way.</li>
<li>Stay in top physical shape—physical stamina is the root of mental toughness.</li>
<li>Develop your team. If you know your people, are fair in setting realistic goals and expectations, and lead by example, you will develop teamwork.</li>
<li>Delegate responsibility to your subordinates and let them do their jobs. You can’t do a good job if you don’t have a chance to use your imagination or your creativity.</li>
<li>Anticipate problems and prepare to overcome obstacles. Don’t wait until you get to the top of the ridge and then make up your mind.</li>
<li>Remain humble. Don’t worry about who receives the credit. Never let power or authority go to your head.</li>
<li>Take a moment of self-reflection. Look at yourself in the mirror every night and ask yourself if you did your best.</li>
<li>True satisfaction comes from getting the job done. The key to a successful leader is to earn respect—not because of rank or position, but because you are a leader of character.</li>
<li>Hang tough!—Never, ever give up.</li>
</ol>
<p><a href="../book-review/how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people.html">How to Win Friends and Influence People</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-how-to-win-friends-bullet-points.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">How to win friends</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>personal development</category>
  <category>lists</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/book-summaries.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 21:36:34 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2 Nephi 25 - We Talk of Christ</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-25-talk-of-christ.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<p>There is one purpose of a law: to prevent something. Or to ensure something happens. But you really can’t prevent bad things from happening by creating a law because laws are just rules. They define what’s bad.</p>
<p>Consider the law of Moses. It defined what was bad. The Ten Commandments. The ordinances. The many rituals and performances.</p>
<p>But the law was dead.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And, notwithstanding we believe in Christ, we keep the law of Moses, and look forward with steadfastness unto Christ, until the law shall be fulfilled. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-25.24">2 Nephi 25.24</a></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For, for this end was the law given; wherefore the <strong>law hath become dead</strong> unto us, and we are made alive in Christ because of our faith; yet we keep the law because of the commandments. 26 And we talk of Christ, we rejoice in Christ, we preach of Christ, we prophesy of Christ, and we write according to our prophecies, that our children may know to what source they may look for a remission of their sins. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-25.25-26">2 Nephi 25.25–26</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Forgetting even the spirit of the law, we can just focus on Christ. Just men need no law. # Meaning</p>
<p>The goal of following Christ isn’t to follow him. It’s to become like him. To experience what He experienced. To feel what He felt. The law is dead once you know that and pursue that.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>commandments</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2-nephi-25-talk-of-christ.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 23:48:47 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Sun on turf</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/sun-on-turf.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Growing up I played a lot of sports, namely football and lacrosse. One of the best things about playing lacrosse was that it happened in the spring, as the snow was melting and the town warming.</p>
<p>When it was cold in the early season, players would lay close to the artificial turf. It was soft, and retained the heat of the sun. It was sometimes the best way to warm up.</p>
<p>I think of that warmth when I lay in my backyard.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/sun-on-turf.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 23:46:34 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Setting up a New Mac</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/setting-up-a-new-mac.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Things I like to do:</p>
<p>Terminal: - Home brew - Zsh - Power level 10k - gh cli - Lazygit cli</p>
<p>Mac Applications I download: - alfred: - rectangle: <code>brew install rectangle</code>. Screen location manager - Flycut: <code>brew install flycut</code>. Clipboard manager</p>
<section id="zsh-aliases" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="zsh-aliases">Zsh aliases:</h2>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/setting-up-a-new-mac.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 12:36:15 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
