<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 23:59:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for In Awe of AI</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/in-awe-of-ai.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today I’m grateful to be in awe of AI.</p>
<p>I went to makersuite.google.com and fed Gemini 1.5 a 115 page pdf investor report and it retuned a summary with core elements with page references.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet blockquote">
<p lang="en" dir="ltr">
✨ Today, we're making Gemini 1.5 Pro available via the Gemini API in a public preview, along with native audio (speech) understanding. And we're also addressing many developer asks.<a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/BuildWithGemini?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#BuildWithGemini</a> → <a href="https://t.co/l3OHZAElwX">https://t.co/l3OHZAElwX</a> <br><br>See what's being launched 🧵⬇️ <a href="https://t.co/MMvF8KvITL">pic.twitter.com/MMvF8KvITL</a>
</p>
— Google for Developers (<span class="citation" data-cites="googledevs">@googledevs</span>) <a href="https://twitter.com/googledevs/status/1777732045319573812?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">April 9, 2024</a>
</blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>It’s pretty incredible. I’m just in awe and slightly terrified but incredibly excited nonetheless to see what AI can do. <a href="../book-review/the-coming-wave.html">The Coming Wave</a> is worth the read. And a systemic shift in how everyone does work is coming, per <a href="../book-review/power-and-prediction.html">Power and Prediction</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/screenshot-google-ai-studio.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Get ready</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>ai tools</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/in-awe-of-ai.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 23:59:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Power and Prediction</title>
  <dc:creator>Joshua Gans, Jay Agrawal, Avi Goldfarb</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/power-and-prediction.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>2024-04-13</p>
<ul>
<li>power is scarcity. AI power?</li>
<li>Those with power prevent system changes. But those who adopt systemic shifts will disrupt those who are stuck in the old ways.</li>
<li>systemic shifts. Companies need to rethink their businesses around AI. What can change? What’s too prohibitive to change? How do regulations change?</li>
</ul>
<p>2024-04-13</p>
<ul>
<li>airports: a decision. Security. Risk ca reward.
<ul>
<li>Highest security is manually reviewing all things.</li>
<li>Allow the machine to review things with some probability of missing a knife.</li>
<li>Let everyone in.</li>
<li>Cost: how much time people spend.</li>
<li>Costs: a plane crashing into another building.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Rules vs decisions.
<ul>
<li>Rules are pre-determined or general decisions instead of making them personalized and relevant in the moment.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>2024-04-12</p>
<ul>
<li>the between time. Lightbulb took 20 years before 50% of houses had it.
<ul>
<li>ChatGPT</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Point solutions
<ul>
<li>lower cost of power. No change to factory system</li>
<li>Can improve a single procedure without changing the system which embeds it.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Application
<ul>
<li>Individual electric drives on each machine. Swappable. If one stops it doesn’t stop the others. Modularity the factory but still keep it the same layout.</li>
<li>Can enable a single thing to do more things.</li>
<li>Enables a new procedure without changing the system in which it’s embedded.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>System solutions → change how the system is designed → steam vs electricity. Exploit by decoupling power source from factory element. → layout the machine how it’s supposed to and get the power to where it is.
<ul>
<li>Enables new procedures or changes existing procedures by changing dependent procedures.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>Ai point solution: - improves a single decision without affecting other decisions AI Application solution - Enables new decision or changes how a decision is made without affecting other solutions AI system solution - Improves or enables new decisions only if changes to how decisions are made is implemented</p>
<p>Chapter 3</p>
<ul>
<li>prediction: concert information you have to information you need</li>
<li>Ripe for adoption (business and customers are already familiar with risky decisions.) system shift: needs to change how people do things to be more efficient.</li>
<li>Randomized</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-power-and-prediction.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Power and Prediction</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>economics</category>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>data science</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/power-and-prediction.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 21:40:40 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for My work team</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/my-work-team.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Joining my current company has been pretty great. Here are the things I’ve liked about it so far:</p>
<ul>
<li>people are kind.</li>
<li>They’re open to each other’s ideas.</li>
<li>They invite each other to lunch in big parties.</li>
<li>They laugh</li>
<li>They encourage each other</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s just a positive place. Where does this come from? It can only come from the top.</p>
<p>Reading <a href="../book-review/thinking-fast-and-slow.html">Thinking, Fast and Slow</a>, there’s a strong correlation between creative thinking and happiness. Having read things like <a href="../book-review/elon-musk.html">Elon Musk</a> and <a href="../book-review/steve-jobs.html">Steve Jobs</a> and one of the conclusions in the Elon book is “working for jerks is perhaps a necessity to get their high level of thinking.” There’s also the set of people who don’t want to work like that - where they treat each other with kindness and respect.</p>
<p>Here’s to my coworkers and those who created the work environment where people who are kind thrive.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-seaotter-beach-data-science.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">My slack profile - we’re the seaotter team</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>work</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/my-work-team.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 23:03:55 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My Advice for New Career People</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/my-advice-for-new-career-people.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’ve worked for five companies in 9 years. The keys for me for job and life satisfaction are now pretty basic:</p>
<ul>
<li>Is my manager supportive and someone I like spending time with?</li>
<li>Is the work continuously interesting? Will I develop skills that are likely to bring interesting opportunities in the future?</li>
<li>Is there incentive alignment between what I offer and what the company needs?</li>
</ul>
<p>This blog post will attempt to describe my thoughts on what makes for a fulfilling career. It’s a hard question. Maybe something in here is valuable as you search for your “ideal” career.</p>
<section id="likely-useless-career-advice" class="level1">
<h1>Likely useless career advice</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>….I’ve been writing this for two hours and I’m not sure any of it makes sense. Skip to the “books to read” section if you get lost. At this point I’m too lazy to edit any of the below but don’t want to delete it. Sunk costs baby…</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Some say a job should help you 1) earn or 2) learn and if neither then leave. But that framework doesn’t work because you can learn anything anywhere. If you’re not learning things you enjoy learning about, that’s moot.</p>
<p>Also, knowledge is accretive. As I look back on jobs I didn’t love, I still learned things. I wasn’t a fan of the type of consulting I was doing 10 years ago, but I’ve now started a consulting firm and having had that experience is helpful. So it’s all kind of gray. I didn’t like pulling weeds as a kid but I’m now pulling weeds as a homeowner so yea, I’m glad I know how to do that.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-is-life-anyway" class="level1">
<h1>what is life anyway?</h1>
<p>Per <a href="../book-review/guide-to-decision-making.html">Guide to Decision Making</a>, “resulting” may apply if you say you made a good decision because you enjoyed a job. By the same token you made a bad decision because you didn’t enjoy the job.</p>
<p>The reality is that “all or nothing thinking” is more of a cognitive bias, per <a href="../book-review/the-coddling-of-the-american-mind.html">The Coddling of the American Mind</a> and <a href="../book-review/the-worry-cure.html">The Worry Cure</a>. And so, you’re going to learn things as long as you’re remotely interested in learning things. Whether they satisfy your <a href="../book-review/the-6-types-of-working-genius.html">Working Genius</a> is another matter.</p>
<p>Can you land your dream job? Or is it a myth? 30-40% of first time marriages end in divorce. And not all of the remaining 70-60% are blissfully happy either. But many of those 70% ARE blissfully happy. Or they will be. Or they were and they will be again maybe or something…</p>
<p>Marriage and work are similar: they’re a type of relationship.</p>
</section>
<section id="professional-and-life-happiness" class="level1">
<h1>Professional and Life happiness</h1>
<p>Happiness to me comes in two forms: doing the best I can with the circumstances I have (the cards I’ve been dealt) and choosing environments that are healthy (the game that gives me the cards).</p>
<p>This is life. Some games are fun to me. Others less fun by definition. But any game may be better than no game. Unless the game involves a high risk of me breaking my spine. Nuance.</p>
<p>Point is: it takes a long while to find what environments you thrive in. Any company can offer just one or potentially many environments depending on their size or the role.</p>
<p>So if you don’t know what you’re interested in, you must explore. You try.</p>
</section>
<section id="experiment-your-way-to-a-happy-career" class="level1">
<h1>Experiment Your Way to a Happy Career</h1>
<p>You can “try” by doing it yourself. Do you want to be a teacher? Go try to volunteer teaching. Do you want to be a coder? Spend 20 hours trying to build an app. Do you want to be a doctor? Volunteer with doctors.</p>
<ul>
<li>Reading about an industry or job is kind of helpful.</li>
<li>Talking to people in the field is more helpful.</li>
<li>Engaging with people is the better form.</li>
<li>But actually doing the work is the only way to know.</li>
</ul>
<p>So you can lower the risk of not liking a job by trying to do it without actually having to get the job.</p>
<p>You can get a pretty good sense by doing little projects similar to what the real work is going to be. Don’t be dictated because you don’t yet have the role.</p>
</section>
<section id="dont-not-try-something-because-of-a-dumb-reason" class="level1">
<h1>Don’t Not Try Something Because of a Dumb Reason</h1>
<p>And that’s kind of the great myth: the myth of titles and credentials. That you need to be experienced at something to be able to do that thing.</p>
<p>I once spent a single week shadowing dentists in an open room in Honduras. I was a Spanish translator for these American dentists that came through. I felt pretty confident by the end that I could probably do one of the fillings just because it really wasn’t that complicated. And the dentists told me so. Once you look at 100 cavities in a mouth it’s not hard to spot them. This was the easiest way to de-myth this job: watching and observing.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>It was actually really boring. Once you’ve seen 100 cavities you’ve seen them all I think. Glad I figured that out quickly! But I know there’s someone out there that disagrees with me and I’m glad they’ll be drilling my teeth and not me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>90% of most people jobs could be taught via apprenticeship, like the good old days. Today’s world of credentials makes people think they’re incapable of doing a pretty simple task: putting a drill into someone’s tooth. But before you invest 8 years of your life in dental school, why not go be a dental hygienist for 1 year? Instead of doing a coding bootcamp, why not just code in your basement for a month after hours? This is the way to find what you like.</p>
<p>Whether you enjoy doing that thing that created value for people can only be discovered by doing it.</p>
</section>
<section id="people-hire-you-because-you-offer-a-service-or-value.-period." class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>People Hire you Because you offer a service or value. Period.</h1>
<p>Your real job is to create value for people. It’s not a title. It’s not a credential. It’s not mandated or necessary in society. And if you were born 100 years before today or 100 years after the job may not exist. So think about opportunities in this way.</p>
<p>A healthier way to thinking about corporate life is: what creates value? Is there a reasonable exchange of goods for my offering?</p>
<p>I’m capable of many offerings. But they’re hiring for one offering. That’s life.</p>
<p>If I were selling apricots, and someone was offering me peanuts, would I exchange my apricots for their peanuts? Well, if we were the only two people sure.</p>
<p>But maybe I feel like I can get some avocados for my apricots. So can I find an avocado dealer? Do they even like apricots? Do they already have enough apricots? And if yes to all the above, are they even in the mood to exchange for apricots today? Lastly, do they like me?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-exchange-of-goods.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Work is just an exchange of goods</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Getting a job is more of a negotiation than anything. And everything in work is a negotiation. Read <a href="../book-review/never-split-the-difference.html">Never Split the Difference</a> and that becomes quite apparent. It’s nothing fancy. It’s not a title. It’s not a degree. It’s just doing little activities.</p>
<p>And after you’ve 1000 similar activities you’re soon labeled a data scientist or a farmer. And if you circled the right boxes on an exam and got a piece of paper you’re now a doctor/dentist. But the paper or the title don’t make you good at that thing. My point: create value, not titles.</p>
</section>
<section id="in-sum" class="level1">
<h1>In Sum</h1>
<p>So yes. I’ve gone on a rant here. But hey this is my blog. I’m trying to talk about the deeper issues at how to choose a profession or a company within that profession. I’m trying to break away from the titles and credentials that blind our thinking away from the more important questions of “what activities bring me joy” and “how will I know if?” And “will someone pay me for doing this activity?” And “how do I find an environment of people that will enable me to do valuable activities and make it a pleasant place to work?” (PS, don’t work for <a href="../book-review/elon-musk.html">Elon Musk</a>…unless you enjoy is working style.)</p>
<p>Long story short: make sure the company hiring you actually needs your skills to run their business. Strive to find better opportunities by putting yourself out there and trying new things. And find people you like working with. All the rest is just a bonus.</p>
<p>The most dangerous thing is to get all those good things on your first job because then you try to self actualize per Maslov’s hierarchy of needs. “Don’t it always seem to go That you don’t know what you got ’til it’s gone?” (<a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=big+yellow+taxi+lyrics&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;hl=en-ca&amp;client=safari&amp;si=AKbGX_rdaVK-rhf5KHnOAD2drrRmADv7R3TkES869sRtvhJtAOFIxRuJ9oGiG6TvSdbxEwjlbUdo-jivJcsfmZzA84yEzB3d-vLGFPTy5juD3yV4riCQxI1XJ6ZQGPnEjGqh-qYE7AaZxecxMD6ZV9wfd6ykO8ZaKA%3D%3D&amp;ictx=1&amp;ved=2ahUKEwi176q45LuFAxVsKkQIHdMLBT4QjukCegQIIxAE">Lyrics</a>) So if you get a “bad” job just know it’s part of the process and one day 10 years from now you’ll probably be grateful you had that job anyway.</p>
<p>If I didn’t actually answer your questions that’s because some questions are a perennial debate. Some popular people hate the idea of work-life balance, some embrace it. Go figure. And keep searching to find someone who sees work and career the same way you do, because there are millions of jobs in the work. Hundreds of millions. # Books to read</p>
<p>It helps to get perspective when choosing where you want to work.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="../book-review/how-to-decide-simple-tools-for-making-better-choices.html">How to Decide: Simple Tools for Making Better Choices</a> - have a decision framework</li>
<li><a href="../book-review/the-6-types-of-working-genius.html">The 6 Types of Working Genius</a> - understand who you are.</li>
<li><a href="../book-review/overcoming-the-five-dysfunctions-of-a-team.html">Overcoming the Five Dysfunctions of a Team</a> - it helps to recognize a good company by first understanding a bad company.</li>
<li><a href="../book-review/the-old-man-and-the-sea.html">The Old Man and the Sea</a> - a job is a job at the end of the day. It’s just fishing.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="practical-questions" class="level1">
<h1>Practical Questions</h1>
<p>Things I’d think about in your shoes:</p>
<ul>
<li>what loosely sounds interesting? Who perhaps knows someone with that type of role? How do I get 15 min with that person, or a quick email? (Use 6 degrees of separation to your advantage)</li>
<li>do I have an ideal salary? What’s realistic? (Levels.fyi, don’t over or undersell yourself. Figure out market rates and if your job will support your desired lifestyle in a location)</li>
<li>what’s the entry level job that gets me some experience 50% in the right direction that I’m interested in?</li>
<li>where will I learn?</li>
<li>Does this company offer flexibility to try new things?</li>
</ul>
<p>Sometimes job searching is helped by thinking by contrast:</p>
<ul>
<li>what can someone not pay me $500k per year to do? $300k? $100k? (Nobody could pay me $500k to be an investment banker and work 100 hour weeks. Maybe they could pay me $2M and I’d do it for 2 years ya know? But $500 isn’t enough.)</li>
</ul>
<p>As you’re interviewing:</p>
<ul>
<li>what incentivizes people on a daily basis?</li>
<li>will this job be around in 2 years? Why? Why not? Why might they fire me in 6 months for things 100% outside of my control? (Recessions, business strategy shifts, etc)</li>
<li>how essential is my skillset to what they do?</li>
<li>what relationship do people have with my would-be manager?</li>
</ul>
<p>Questions to potentially ask your hiring manager:</p>
<ul>
<li>How do you see me fitting into this role?</li>
<li>Why might this role not be a good fit for me?</li>
<li>Who’s the highest ranking person who’s quit or been fired recently and why?</li>
<li>How do you define success for this role?</li>
</ul>
<p>Questions to ask your peers you’re interviewing with:</p>
<ul>
<li>describe your relationship with your manager?</li>
<li>describe the communication patterns of the team?</li>
<li>describe how decisions are made? What’s a recent decision that was made? describe your role in how the team made that decision?</li>
</ul>
<p>Other thoughts:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="../posts/2022-11-18-writing-a-tech-resume/index.html">Writing a Tech Resume</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>career advice</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/my-advice-for-new-career-people.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 20:19:05 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for The Peak of a Hike</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/the-peak-of-a-hike.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It’s that moment where you stop walking because you walked to the destination you can no longer approximate.</p>
<p>It’s called a peak.</p>
<p>Human nature loves peaks. They’re exclusive. Interestingly, they’re probably far more tracked than random grassy spots in your neighborhood park. Because everyone wants to get to the peak.</p>
<p>I’m grateful I can hike. That I can choose random destinations. And that I can go to them.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-mountain-from-top-of-peak.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The peak looking at a peak</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/the-peak-of-a-hike.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 23:56:43 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Coming Wave</title>
  <dc:creator>x </dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/the-coming-wave.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>2024-04-09</p>
<ul>
<li>anyone with access to a DNA lab can destroy the world.</li>
<li>Alexnet by Hinton</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-the-coming-wave.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The Coming Wave</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/the-coming-wave.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 14:31:57 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Warm naps on the couch</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/warm-naps-on-the-couch.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today the family was watching General Conference on TV. I joined them and hopped under a cozy blanket. Suddenly, I felt off. Like I didn’t belong in the room. Like I didn’t belong awake.</p>
<p>And so I departed slowly into another realm. This is happiness.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-warm-naps.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Warm naps</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/warm-naps-on-the-couch.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2024 23:10:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Customer Service Agents</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/customer-service-agents.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today I reached out to a customer support agent.</p>
<p>It took 90 minutes before the chat finally connected me to them. But they responded! And I think they solved my problem. TBD.</p>
<p>But it was great being able to reach out to someone I don’t even know who just answered my question!</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/customer-service-agents.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2024 00:13:14 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Microsoft Copilot notes</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/microsoft-copilot-notes.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Three copilots:</p>
<ul>
<li>copilot.Microsoft.com</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/3Nb0FEe3kKw?si=Q8A2T101zA9pxx1B">YouTube MS ignite</a></p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3Nb0FEe3kKw?si=Q8A2T101zA9pxx1B" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<ul>
<li>uses RAG on the Microsoft graph</li>
<li>Copilot can make a PowerPoint from a Doc</li>
<li>TeamsKit</li>
<li>plugins and graph connectors. Maybe plugin is right? Maybe graph connector is right.</li>
<li>Not very useful PowerPoints unless tied to data</li>
<li>LLMs are only as accurate as the data.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/7JRaFAYSOgI?si=9NrnsVCO0rGrlAHh">YouTube create awesome documents</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Edit and revise</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/_nf56aMPdZE?si=Z6UR5qKPOvKb4y4d">YouTube | Excel tutorial</a></p>
<ul>
<li>20-30 second</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/AhywEEHg6Es?si=PDLQGwIJgaBxivbz">YouTube | MS Cop featurs</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/screenshot-write-speech-from-doc.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Write speech</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/oYijejDXLZQ?si=J-08luV6mNJPEgIU">YouTube | Microsoft Loop is cool</a></p>
<ul>
<li>loop is cool. Makes collaborating across applications on a single thing easy.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/Xv_TmtRLHJY?si=H1N_UkWSli2xLJsG">YouTube | Global Enterprise</a></p>
<ul>
<li>you can have it “sound like me” in outlook</li>
<li>41:35 copilot studio</li>
<li>Can use open AIs GPTs</li>
</ul>
<section id="azure-open-ai" class="level1">
<h1>Azure open ai</h1>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/obfs_LEzPHo?si=AorIJwEutzw3UVIR">YouTube</a></p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/obfs_LEzPHo?si=AorIJwEutzw3UVIR" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<ul>
<li>BRK206 Vector search and state of the art retrieval for generative ai apps</li>
<li>BRK205 multimodal</li>
</ul>
<p>Things to explore:</p>
<ul>
<li>TeamsKit</li>
<li>Azure OpenAI</li>
</ul>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/microsoft-copilot-notes.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 21:57:30 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Gentleman in Moscow</title>
  <dc:creator>Amor Towles</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/a-gentleman-in-moscow.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>2024-04-06</p>
<ul>
<li>cool setup. Guy stuck in</li>
<li>Gentlemen use a desk</li>
<li>We put attachment into things. But at the end they’re just things.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-a-gentleman-in-moscow.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Gentleman in Moscow</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/a-gentleman-in-moscow.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 20:19:37 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Jacob 1 - Viewing Christ</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/jacob-1-viewing-christ.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wherefore, we would to God that we could persuade all men not to rebel against God, to <strong>provoke him</strong> to anger, but that all men would believe in Christ, and <strong>view his death,</strong> and suffer his cross and bear the shame of the world; wherefore, I, Jacob, take it upon me to fulfil the commandment of my brother Nephi. <a href="../scriptures/jacob-1.8">Jacob 1.8</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Christ was clearly angry when he flipped the market at the temple. And it’s said he’s a “jealous” God and has his wrath and such.</p>
<p>God won’t be mocked. But he’s the first to love and forgive us. So when we bring upon us his wrath, I see this as we’re bringing upon ourselves the consequences of our own actions. The wrath was determined when He made the law. But it’s better said “we bring upon ourselves the wrath of breaking his commandments” than “provoke him to anger”, for Charity sufferers long and is Kind and is not easily provoked. For He is Charity.</p>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>It’s much healthier for me to see the commandments as immutable as gravity. Drop something, it’ll brake. Face the wrath of the hardwood floor. But God is quite in control. Quite loving. Quite fair and just.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/jacob-1-viewing-christ.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 00:15:22 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Mentors</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/mentors.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’ve had a lifelong mentor, Daron Shepard, for nearly two decades now. We first met when I was a sophomore in high school and he just joined the high school coaching staff.</p>
<p>Our relationship since that time has been many one on one phone calls. Sometimes he’s called me when he didn’t know how much I needed it.</p>
<p>And today he’s been calling me as a professional coach. Each time I talk with him I come away with better ideas on how to see things more clearly.</p>
<p>He’s like the giving tree. I keep coming back to him at different phases and he keeps helping me in new ways.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-new-england-woods.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">We’d go on walks through the Connecticut woods when I was home from college</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>relationships</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/mentors.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2024 23:56:25 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>LLMs need to call Functions</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/news/llms-need-to-call-functions.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/andrewyng_microsoft-absorbs-inflection-nvidias-new-activity-7181717345814421504-E1hR?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_ios">Andrew Ng on LinkedIn: Microsoft Absorbs Inflection, Nvidia’s New GPUs, Managing AI Bio Risk, and… | 38 comments</a></p>
<ul>
<li>LLms guess what functions to call, such as running a calculation in Python or a function to do a web search.</li>
<li>Efficient Tool Use with Chain-of-Abstraction Reasoning, Gao et al.&nbsp;(2024)</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/issue-243/">Microsoft Absorbs Inflection, Nvidia’s New GPUs, Managing AI Bio Risk, and more</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/how-agents-can-improve-llm-performance/?utm_campaign=The%20Batch&amp;utm_source=hs_email&amp;utm_medium=email">Four AI Agent Strategies That Improve GPT-4 and GPT-3.5 Performance</a></p>
<ul>
<li>AI agenic workflows can help AI achieve 95% code quality vs zero shot.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/agentic-design-patterns-part-2-reflection/?ref=dl-staging-website.ghost.io">Agentic Design Patterns Part 2: Reflection</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Here’s code intended for task X: [previously generated code] Check the code carefully for correctness, style, and efficiency, and give constructive criticism for how to improve it.</li>
<li>Next, we can prompt the LLM with context including (i) the previously generated code and the constructive feedback and (ii) ask it to use the feedback to rewrite the code</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://www.deeplearning.ai/the-batch/agentic-design-patterns-part-3-tool-use/?ref=dl-staging-website.ghost.io">Agentic Design Patterns Part 3: Tool Use</a></p>
<p><a href="https://mad.firstmarkcap.com/">FirstMark | 2024 MAD (ML/AI/Data) Landscape</a> - there are too many tools for any one person or organization to know what to do with. It’s a full time job just to understand what’s out there.</p>
<p>https://www.linkedin.com/posts/luke-b_data-nerds-what-technology-should-you-learn-activity-7181698703722729472-N03S?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_ios</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/screenshot-mad-first-mark-cap.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Data landscape</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://deepmind.google/research/publications/85521/">Gecko: Versatile Text Embeddings Distilled from Large Language Models - Google DeepMind</a></p>
<ul>
<li>gecko is a text embedding model that can do more with 256 tokens than most can with 700+</li>
</ul>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>ai tools</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/news/llms-need-to-call-functions.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2024 21:06:11 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Wet Suits</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/wet-suit.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’ve been going to the beach for four years and have never gotten deep into the water. It’s frigid. I’ll skimboard along the surface or the little crash but never felt a need to go into the water. Besides, it’s freezing.</p>
<p>That’s not to say I wouldn’t want to if it’s warm - I love to body surf and boogie.</p>
<p>Recently I went back to the beach but with a wet suit in hand. Suddenly everything was better. The <a href="../gratitude/skimboarding.html">Skimboarding</a> was better because I wasn’t afraid of falling and getting a rash, or I wasn’t afraid of being cold. I could take the waves head on. And then I just went right out into the water and had the best boogie of my life on a solid wave.</p>
<p>It was incredible. I mourned that I’ve wasted 4 years.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-wet-suit.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Get out there!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>nature</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/wet-suit.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 23:26:42 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Jacob 2 - Give Freely</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/Jacob-2-give-freely.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="scriptures" class="level1">
<h1>Scriptures</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Think of your brethren like unto yourselves, and be familiar with all and free with your substance, that they may be rich like unto you. <a href="../scriptures/jacob-2.17">Jacob 2.17</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="meaning" class="level1">
<h1>Meaning</h1>
<p>Reading <a href="../book-review/building-a-story-brand.html">Building a Story Brand</a>, I was impressed by the author’s philosophy on giving away things. His time. Resources. Knowledge. He challenged the notion that in business you should charge for everything. Instead he sought to give away as much as he could. His business has grown pretty well.</p>
<p>There’s also the principle of reciprocity, well studied in <a href="../book-review/influence-the-psychology-of-persuasion.html">Influence The Psychology of Persuasion</a>. When we give, people feel a social debt and want to repay it even more than what was given.</p>
<p>Both of these things are taught by the Savior’s desire for us to give freely, “It is more blessed to give than to receive.” (<a href="../scriptures/acts-20.35">Acts 20.35</a>)</p>
<p>Consider the design: instill in people a desire to repay debts. When one person gives, other people give more back. Then the first person wants to give because a surplus was given to them. And then and then and then. More giving.</p>
<p>I reviewed this in <a href="../gratitude/marriage.html">I’m Grateful for Marriage</a>, the parable of the no-elbow people. Better to give.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>charity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/Jacob-2-give-freely.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 23:18:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to Sign in with iCloud Calendar on Outlook for iOS</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/how-to-sign-in-with-icloud-calendar-on-outlook-for-ios.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>How do I add an iCloud account to iOS Outlook without it being a public calendar?</p>
<p>It was easy to add any gmail accounts but I didn’t know how to add my iCloud calendar to iOS Outlook. Part of the issue is my iCloud account is actually my gmail email address so I can’t sign in with this or it’ll load my gmail calendar.</p>
<p>Solution:</p>
<ul>
<li>go to iOS settings &gt; iCloud &gt; get your <code>@icloud.com</code> name. If you use your gmail account for iCloud there’s still this <code>@icloud</code> account.</li>
<li>Attempt to log into iOS Outlook calendar. Apple will then make you create an app-specific password for iOS Outlook</li>
<li>Use this password.</li>
</ul>
<p>Done. Pain solved.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>tutorial</category>
  <category>tips and tricks</category>
  <category>to my future self</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/how-to-sign-in-with-icloud-calendar-on-outlook-for-ios.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 20:54:28 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Why you should log with Aimstack</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/why-you-should-log-with-aimstack.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’ve long idolized <a href="https://aimstack.io/">Home | AimStack</a>. It’s a tool that allows you to track metrics and hyperparameters and a whole bunch of stuff. It lets you compare across experiments.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/screenshot-aimstack.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Aim landing lage</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I first built my own version of this in <code>RShiny</code> back in 2017 so I could compare AUC across experiments.</p>
<p>I was using <code>h2o.ai</code> at the time which had this great flow for monitoring an individual experiment but made it impossible to compare across experiments.</p>
<p>Then my company Capital One built <code>rubicon</code>: <a href="https://github.com/capitalone/rubicon-ml">GitHub - capitalone/rubicon-ml: Capture all information throughout your model’s development in a reproducible way and tie results directly to the model code!</a>. This was cool and they open sourced it. It tracks parameters.</p>
<p>But it pales in comparison to <code>aim</code>.</p>
<p>Aim can do all these things:</p>
<ul>
<li>Track hyperparameters</li>
<li>Track learning curves (like a metric over time such as when building DL models and you’re watching how the error decreases with each epoch)</li>
<li>Track any <code>plotly</code> plot, which means you can put any EDA charts nicely organized in one place</li>
<li>it captures all your <code>logging.info</code> calls so you don’t need to use a remote logging thing like <code>cloud watch</code> to monitor long runs</li>
<li>It has its own loggers if you want to differentiate</li>
<li>It lets you take notes on an experiment</li>
<li>If lets you compare across experiments</li>
<li>It lets you use locally or remotely as a remote API</li>
<li>It tracks images, etc.</li>
<li>it connects with ML packages like <code>xgbost</code> to auto log.</li>
<li>It can even convert <code>MLFlow</code> data.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s incredible. Use it. It’s free.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>logging</category>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>data pipeline</category>
  <category>ml pipeline</category>
  <category>data science</category>
  <category>monitoring</category>
  <category>ml-tools</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/why-you-should-log-with-aimstack.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 22:15:37 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Configurations for ML Pipelines</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/configurations-for-ml-pipelines.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Configuring an ML pipeline means you have 15 different things that could change at any time and you create a way to easily change those 15 things. Those 15 things could be file paths, data filtering steps, models you want to use, etc.</p>
<p>Any researcher constantly asks themselves: but what if I switch X?</p>
<p>And so the researcher starts to configure a pipeline.</p>
<section id="config-methods-ive-used" class="level1">
<h1>Config Methods I’ve Used</h1>
<p>First time I built a config it was in VBA. I had a text file I loaded in that could be overwritten based on setting someone chose.</p>
<p>Second time I config’d something was in Python. I used <code>ConfigParser</code> per my Manager David Mantilla’s suggestion. It was pretty good for 2017. But unwieldy. Don’t use this. It had cool string substitutions but there are better tools now.</p>
<p>Third thing I saw was using a Python constants.py file. Just import Python variables from another module. This is nice because you can import model objects or such. Dicts. Whatever. Seems great. But it’s Python code. Config files shouldn’t be code. They should be configs. Every great software follows this, like <code>k8s</code> helm charts or whatever. Google loves using <code>Protobufs</code>. Configs shouldn’t be code, because if they’re code they’re dangerous. You start doing crazy things with them.</p>
<p>Fourth thing I did was to use YAML which is very clean. Lots of people like YAML. This gets unwieldy if you need 100 configs for different customers, for example. Can you imagine managing 100 yaml files? What if you need to update one param? Then you need to update 100 files. Rough. So then you start setting “default” blocks and settings.</p>
<p>I also used Pydantic to read in the YAML file and validate types. Gotta validate types. What’s an int vs a string? Well, this mean that we needed to design the pipeline to rely on some <code>config</code> class. We had to pass this config object around everywhere. Not super idea but gets the job done.</p>
<p>Fifth thing was to use one default YAML. This solved the issue of redundancy across all the 100 YAML files. (If you only have one model, you probably need only 1 YAML file so this may not be your problem.) But this still kinda stinks. It’s in a file.</p>
<p>Sixth thing was some eng’s on my team saw a better way and build a CRUD database. This made it so we didn’t have to do a code change to update a config. That means that people outside the team could edit a config. Awesome. But we still have 100 web pages that could change. Kinda sux. And we still had a default setting - essential. Benefits of a crud are migrations. You can get rid of one option across 100 configs more easily.</p>
<p>Problem with 100 YAML or 100 web pages is that if you want to change things or run experiments, you need to literally clone the config file. Now you have 15 versions of the same config file with slight modifications and you can’t remember what’s going on. So you delete them all eventually and just pick one.</p>
<p>Seventh thing: shove everything into environment variables. Create a <code>.env</code> file and load with <code>dotenv()</code> but that gets messy because env files don’t support data type validation. Validation is essential, lest you try to encode a Boolean in your env file only to realize environment variables only support strings and then you have a “False” rendering as true in your “if os.get(MY_BOOL)” call just because it exists as a valid string. Blech… 🤮</p>
</section>
<section id="hydra" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Hydra?</h1>
<p>I’m writing this because I just learned about <code>hydra</code> . Remember: I use this site for note taking. Here’s what I just learned.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/screenshot-hydra-configs.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Hydra!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://hydra.cc/">Hydra | Hydra</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Hydra is Python open source maintained by Facebook</li>
<li>If built to configure pipelines, in particular ML pipelines but could be used for anything.</li>
<li>It uses <code>dataclasses</code> and <code>yaml</code> files, so I’m thinking I was smart for what I did with my fourth option.</li>
<li>But it quickly allows you to override config files from the command line or from editing the yaml file directly.</li>
</ul>
<p>This demo is slick:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tEsPyYnzt8s?si=2T58Ix4ZAo-N75y0" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</section>
<section id="why-i-like-hydras-design" class="level1">
<h1>Why I like Hydra’s design</h1>
<ul>
<li>This seems really nice because it avoids the headache of changing code.</li>
<li>Also, you can create a simple bash loop to execute 5 different experiments - while retaining only one config file</li>
<li>Also, I used to think that having a system of record is pretty important: I need to save the configs that were used for this run. That tells me how the pipeline or experiment was configured. I still think that’s true: but I believe that should be done via logging instead of managing 15 config files.</li>
<li>My new belief is that experiments should be ephemeral to keep the code clean. Have one prod <code>yaml</code> file and then everything else is ephemeral. Log everything: log the created yaml file with all defaults filled inso you can recreate it if necessary.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="my-ideal-world" class="level1">
<h1>My Ideal World</h1>
<p>Hydra doesn’t solve the “you shouldn’t have to do a git push to update prod”. If everything is a <code>yaml</code> file then to update prod you need to do a code change.</p>
<p>Google doesn’t seem to mind using code changes because everything is a protobuff. Code changes are nice because they’re reviewed.</p>
<p>But code changes are slow. And non-coders can do them.</p>
<p>So I believe one prod config should live in a UI with a database backend. But then that should be serialized to <code>yaml</code> and loaded via something like hydra.</p>
<p>I also believe experiments should be launched programmatically. Meaning I should be able to kick off 10 experiments training 10 models using a bash script. I can then log this experiment using <a href="../tech/why-you-should-log-with-aimstack.html">Why you should log with Aimstack</a> and I can log the full config there.</p>
<p>Also, I’d throw <code>hydra</code> in with <code>metaflow</code> .</p>
<p>How do you configure? # Appendix</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/optuna/easy-hyperparameter-management-with-hydra-mlflow-and-optuna-783730700e7d">Easy Hyperparameter Management with Hydra, MLflow, and Optuna | by NT | Optuna | Medium</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>configuration</category>
  <category>software engineering</category>
  <category>ml pipeline</category>
  <category>ml-tools</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/configurations-for-ml-pipelines.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 21:50:43 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Brave New World</title>
  <dc:creator>Aldous Huxley</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/brave-new-world.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>2024-04-04 summary</p>
<ul>
<li>This and <a href="../book-review/1984.html">1984</a> are two books everyone should read. This book was written 93 years ago and it’s eerily prescient of what’s happening in society. The pursuits of happiness and the role of the state and technology to those ends are evergreen topics. The pains that John felt entering a society but choosing true happiness over contrived ones.</li>
<li>Parallels today: people escaping to social media and TikTok like soma</li>
<li>People wanting government to solve all their problems → the 20,000 alphas who wanted the government to step in</li>
<li>People feeling adrift without an internal purpose and happy to just accept what comes their way or what society conditions them to believe → independent thinkers banished to islands</li>
<li>Over optimization of Silicon Valley trying to optimize everything in their life</li>
<li>Linda and John’s fates as they enter a world they don’t belong to. Adrift.</li>
<li>Society gawking at the savage like we gawk at social media.</li>
<li>The whole thing just captures human behavior so brilliantly.</li>
</ul>
<p>2024-04-01</p>
<ul>
<li>started it</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-brave-new-world.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Brave new world</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/brave-new-world.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 20:46:08 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Easter</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/easter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-he-is-risen.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">He is Risen</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’m grateful for Easter. I’m grateful for the knowledge of a Savior. That He died, and rose from the dead. That He lives.</p>
<p>A belief in Jesus is a belief in quite a number of wonderful things:</p>
<ul>
<li>All people will live eternally. We will all get bodies because of Him.</li>
<li>Death is not the end, but just another step in an everlasting life</li>
<li>Sickness and pain is only temporary. In the hereafter there are joys untold awaiting us.</li>
<li>A God is willing to die for us. We are worth His love. His sacrifice. Each one of us.</li>
<li>There is unimaginable power in this universe that we can’t imagine even tapping. Who on earth can raise the dead? Not even the most brilliant doctor. But for Christ, it’s what He will do.</li>
<li>Families and beloved relationships will perpetuate beyond the grave.</li>
<li>There is always hope even in the darkest days. Christ was among an oppressed people. He was rejected by those he came to serve. He was crucified. But then he rose from the dead and it was finished.</li>
</ul>
<p>There are even many more blessings.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/easter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 23:20:53 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
