<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.554</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 21:36:55 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>New business Checklist</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/new-business-checklist.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Getting paid is easy. Getting paid the right way is harder.</p>
<p>You don’t need to have an LLC.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Get an address. You can use your own, but safer to pay $10/mo for a postal box. I use Ipostal.com</li>
<li>File an LLC. Use Incfile. Get it done right if you’re doing this business with a partner.</li>
<li>Using the EIN, go register a small business bank account. I chose Chase only because they do</li>
<li>Create a website.</li>
<li>Accounting software (Freshbooks)</li>
<li>On Freshbooks you can connect to strip. You need a website first.</li>
<li>Get an email provider. (Outlook or Google) You don’t need a website to do email, but you do need a domain. You can have anyone host your website, anyone register your name, and anyone do your email. But the company that registers your url will be the place where you manage your DNS records to set up your email.</li>
<li>Track your expenses separately. They’re all a tax write off.
<ol type="1">
<li>Get a separate credit card, perhaps a small business credit card, for just this purpose.</li>
</ol></li>
<li></li>
</ol>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/new-business-checklist.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 21:36:55 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Failure and Countermeasures - Robert Rogers</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/failure-and-countermeasures-robert-rogers.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Robert rogers.</p>
<p>What leads to death? And what are preparatory countermeasures?</p>
<section id="defining-death-for-me" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="defining-death-for-me">Defining death for me:</h2>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/failure-and-countermeasures-robert-rogers.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 13:46:31 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My Advice for New Career People</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/my-advice-for-new-career-people.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The keys for me for job satisfaction are now pretty basic:</p>
<ul>
<li>Is my manager supportive and someone I like spending time with?</li>
<li>Is the work continuously interesting? Will I develop skills that are likely to bring interesting opportunities in the future?</li>
<li>Is there incentive alignment between what I offer and what the company needs?</li>
</ul>
<p>This blog post will attempt to describe my thoughts on what makes for a fulfilling career. It’s a hard question. Maybe something in here is valuable as you search for your “ideal” career.</p>
<section id="likely-useless-career-advice" class="level1">
<h1>Likely useless career advice</h1>
<p>Now for a stream of consciousness about corporate employment…</p>
<p>Some say a job should help you 1) earn or 2) learn and if neither then leave. But that framework doesn’t really work because you can learn anything anywhere.</p>
<p>Knowledge is accretive. As I look back on jobs I didn’t love, I still learned things. I wasn’t a fan of the type of consulting I was doing 10 years ago, but I’ve now started a consulting firm and having had that experience is helpful. So it’s all kind of gray. I didn’t like pulling weeds as a kid but I’m now pulling weeds as a homeowner so yea, I’m glad I know how to do that.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-is-life-anyway" class="level1">
<h1>what is life anyway?</h1>
<p>Per <a href="../book-review/guide-to-decision-making.html">Guide to Decision Making</a>, “resulting” may apply if you say you made a good decision because you enjoyed a job. By the same token you made a bad decision because you didn’t enjoy the job.</p>
<p>The reality is that “all or nothing thinking” is more of a cognitive bias, per <a href="../book-review/the-coddling-of-the-american-mind.html">The Coddling of the American Mind</a> and <a href="../book-review/the-worry-cure.html">The Worry Cure</a>. And so, you’re going to learn things as long as you’re remotely interested in learning things. Whether they satisfy your <a href="../book-review/the-6-types-of-working-genius.html">Working Genius</a> is another matter.</p>
</section>
<section id="i-want-my-dream-job-though" class="level1">
<h1>I want my “dream” job though</h1>
<p>Can you land your dream job? Or is it a myth? 30-40% of first time marriages end in divorce. And not all of the remaining 70-60% are blissfully happy either. But many of those 70% ARE blissfully happy. Or they will be. Or they were and they will be again maybe or something…</p>
<p>Marriage and work are similar: they’re a type of relationship.</p>
<p>Happiness in a relationship takes both people being committed to the happiness of the other. One sided relationships eventually crumble. But if both people remain committed to the other’s happiness, and other certain caveats…, the marriage will prove valuable to both for their whole lives.</p>
</section>
<section id="professional-and-life-happiness" class="level1">
<h1>Professional and Life happiness</h1>
<p>Happiness to me comes in two forms: doing the best I can with the circumstances I have (the cards I’ve been dealt) and choosing environments that are healthy (the game that gives me the cards).</p>
<p>It’s about 1) what you’re doing and 2) the environment and context you’re doing it in.</p>
<p>This is life. Some games are fun to me. Others less fun by definition. But any game may be better than no game. Unless the game involves a high risk of me breaking my spine. Nuance.</p>
<p>Point is: it takes a long while to find what environments you thrive in. Any company can offer just one or potentially many environments depending on their size or the role.</p>
<p>So if you don’t know what you’re interested in, you must explore. You try.</p>
</section>
<section id="finding-the-best-environment" class="level1">
<h1>Finding the best environment</h1>
<p>First on the environment.</p>
<p>Jane Austen is better at this than me. Take all those sisters in Pride and Prejudice who have varying views on love and stability. Some sisters believe in true love. Others think it’s a myth and instead choose financial stability. Of course true love wins in the end.</p>
<p>I suppose work is very similar: you’re going to get out of it what you believe is possible. After all: you work with and for people.</p>
<p>It will take time and risks to figure out what environments you thrive in, kind of like dating. The interview is part of the process. Bring in a company is another part. Talking to friends in other companies is a third part. Thinking grass is greener is a fourth part, and so forth. That’s life.</p>
<p><em>Your needs</em> also change in your career. As you change, your preferences change. It’s up to you to learn how to match your preferences with your environments, and how to accommodate your preferences within your environments.</p>
<p>If you don’t like your roommate, you can leave early or wait till your contract expires or etc etc. or you can try to work it out and get to know your roommate. All are options. Which you choose is up to you. In the end, a good environment takes two. But it also takes one to instigate change for the better for both. Reciprocity.</p>
</section>
<section id="experiment-your-way-to-a-happy-career" class="level1">
<h1>Experiment Your Way to a Happy Career</h1>
<p>Then there’s the <em>thing you’re doing.</em></p>
<p>You can “try” anything by doing it yourself. Do you want to be a teacher? Go try to volunteer teaching. Do you want to be a coder? Spend 20 hours trying to build an app. Do you want to be a doctor? Volunteer with doctors.</p>
<p>Four ways of learning what you like emerge. The quality of the information is ordered top to bottom while the amount of time it takes to get that information is bottom to top:</p>
<ul>
<li>Reading about an industry or job is kind of helpful.</li>
<li>Talking to people in the field is more helpful.</li>
<li>Following and shadowing those people is even more useful.</li>
<li>But actually doing the work is the only way to really know.</li>
</ul>
<p>You can read about 50 jobs to see what piques your interest and help you learn what’s out there. Next, you can increase the chance of pursuing a job you like by trying to do it without actually having to get the job.</p>
<p>You can get a pretty good sense by doing little projects similar to what the real work is going to be.</p>
</section>
<section id="dont-not-try-something-because-of-a-dumb-reason" class="level1">
<h1>Don’t Not Try Something Because of a Dumb Reason</h1>
<p>A lot of people think they shouldn’t do something because they’re not good enough. Even professionals. (Tiger Woods just had his worst round of his life, but I’m guessing he’s still better than you.)</p>
<p>Or they think they shouldn’t try something because they’re not yet credentialed. “Don’t try this at home kids”. It’s what we’re taught.</p>
<p>And that’s kind of the great myth: the myth of titles and credentials. That you need to be experienced at something to be able to do that thing. But that’s a lie. Instead, you should only pursue the credential if it offers you something you can’t otherwise get (due to red tape). And until you get the credential, you’re just spending a few hours every day learning stuff and maybe passing an exam at the end. So if you ignore the exam, what’s stopping you from just picking up the activities today you may find rewarding?</p>
<p>I once spent a single week shadowing dentists in an open room in Honduras. I was a Spanish translator for these American dentists that came through. I felt pretty confident by the end that I could probably do one of the fillings just because it really wasn’t that complicated. And the dentists told me so. Once you look at 100 cavities in a mouth it’s not hard to spot them. This was the easiest way to de-myth this job: watching and observing.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>It was actually really boring. Once you’ve seen 100 cavities you’ve seen them all I think. Glad I figured that out quickly! But I know there’s someone out there that disagrees with me and I’m glad they’ll be drilling my teeth and not me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>90% of most people’s jobs could be taught via apprenticeship, like the good old days. Today’s world of credentials makes people think they’re incapable of doing a pretty simple task: putting a tool into someone’s tooth. But before you invest 8 years of your life in dental school, why not go be a dental hygienist for 1 year? Instead of doing a coding bootcamp, why not just code in your basement for a month after hours? This is the way to find what you like.</p>
<p>Whether you enjoy doing that thing that created value for people can only be discovered by doing it.</p>
</section>
<section id="people-hire-you-because-you-offer-a-service-or-value.-period." class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>People Hire you Because you offer a Service or Value. Period.</h1>
<p>Your real job is to create value for people. It’s not a title. It’s not a credential. It’s not mandated or necessary in society. And if you were born 100 years before today or 100 years after the job may not exist. So think about opportunities in this way.</p>
<p>A healthier way to thinking about corporate life is: what creates value? Is there a reasonable exchange of goods for my offering?</p>
<p>I’m capable of many offerings. But they’re hiring for one offering. That’s life.</p>
<p>If I were selling apricots, and someone was offering me peanuts, would I exchange my apricots for their peanuts? Well, if we were the only two people sure.</p>
<p>But maybe I feel like I can get some avocados for my apricots. So can I find an avocado dealer? Do they even like apricots? Do they already have enough apricots? And if yes to all the above, are they even in the mood to exchange for apricots today? Lastly, do they like me?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-exchange-of-goods.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Work is just an exchange of goods</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Getting a job is more of a negotiation than anything. And everything in work is a negotiation. Read <a href="../book-review/never-split-the-difference.html">Never Split the Difference</a> and that becomes quite apparent. Work is nothing fancy. It’s not a title. It’s not a degree. It’s just doing little activities.</p>
<p>And after you’ve 1000 similar activities you’re soon labeled a data scientist or a farmer. And if you circled the right boxes on an exam and got a piece of paper you’re now a doctor/dentist. But the paper or the title don’t make you good at that thing. My point: create value, not titles.</p>
</section>
<section id="in-sum" class="level1">
<h1>In Sum</h1>
<p>So yes. I’ve gone on a rant here. But hey this is my blog. I’m trying to talk about the deeper issues at how to choose a profession or a company within that profession. I’m trying to break away from the titles and credentials that blind our thinking away from the more important questions of “what activities bring me joy” and “how will I know it?” And “will someone pay me for doing this activity?” And “how do I find an environment of people that will enable me to do valuable activities and make it a pleasant place to work?” (PS, some say to not work for <a href="../book-review/elon-musk.html">Elon Musk</a>…unless you enjoy his working style.)</p>
<p>Long story short: make sure the company hiring you actually needs your skills to run their business. Strive to find better opportunities by putting yourself out there and trying new things. And find people you like working with. All the rest is just a bonus.</p>
<p>The most dangerous thing is to get all those good things on your first job because then you try to self actualize per Maslov’s hierarchy of needs. “Don’t it always seem to go That you don’t know what you got ’til it’s gone?” (<a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=big+yellow+taxi+lyrics&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;hl=en-ca&amp;client=safari&amp;si=AKbGX_rdaVK-rhf5KHnOAD2drrRmADv7R3TkES869sRtvhJtAOFIxRuJ9oGiG6TvSdbxEwjlbUdo-jivJcsfmZzA84yEzB3d-vLGFPTy5juD3yV4riCQxI1XJ6ZQGPnEjGqh-qYE7AaZxecxMD6ZV9wfd6ykO8ZaKA%3D%3D&amp;ictx=1&amp;ved=2ahUKEwi176q45LuFAxVsKkQIHdMLBT4QjukCegQIIxAE">Lyrics</a>) So if you get a “bad” job just know it’s part of the process and one day 10 years from now you’ll probably be grateful you had that job anyway.</p>
<p>If I didn’t actually answer your questions that’s because some questions are a perennial debate. Some popular people hate the idea of work-life balance, some embrace it. Go figure. And keep searching to find someone who sees work and career the same way you do, because there are millions of jobs in the work. Hundreds of millions.</p>
</section>
<section id="books-to-read" class="level1">
<h1>Books to read</h1>
<p>It helps to get perspective when choosing where you want to work.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="../book-review/how-to-decide-simple-tools-for-making-better-choices.html">How to Decide: Simple Tools for Making Better Choices</a> - have a decision framework</li>
<li><a href="../book-review/the-6-types-of-working-genius.html">The 6 Types of Working Genius</a> - understand who you are.</li>
<li><a href="../book-review/overcoming-the-five-dysfunctions-of-a-team.html">Overcoming the Five Dysfunctions of a Team</a> - it helps to recognize a good company by first understanding a bad company.</li>
<li><a href="../book-review/the-old-man-and-the-sea.html">The Old Man and the Sea</a> - a job is a job at the end of the day. It’s just fishing.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="practical-questions" class="level1">
<h1>Practical Questions</h1>
<p>Things I’d think about in your shoes:</p>
<ul>
<li>what loosely sounds interesting? Who perhaps knows someone with that type of role? How do I get 15 min with that person, or a quick email? (Use 6 degrees of separation to your advantage)</li>
<li>do I have an ideal salary? What’s realistic? (Levels.fyi, don’t over or undersell yourself. Figure out market rates and if your job will support your desired lifestyle in a location)</li>
<li>what’s the entry level job that gets me some experience 50% in the right direction that I’m interested in?</li>
<li>where will I learn?</li>
<li>Does this company offer flexibility to try new things?</li>
</ul>
<p>Sometimes job searching is helped by thinking by contrast:</p>
<ul>
<li>what can someone not pay me $500k per year to do? $300k? $100k? (Nobody could pay me $500k to be an investment banker and work 100 hour weeks. Maybe they could pay me $2M and I’d do it for 2 years ya know? But $500 isn’t enough.)</li>
</ul>
<p>As you’re interviewing:</p>
<ul>
<li>what incentivizes people on a daily basis?</li>
<li>will this job be around in 2 years? Why? Why not? Why might they fire me in 6 months for things 100% outside of my control? (Recessions, business strategy shifts, etc)</li>
<li>how essential is my skillset to what they do?</li>
<li>what relationship do people have with my would-be manager?</li>
</ul>
<p>Questions to potentially ask your hiring manager:</p>
<ul>
<li>How do you see me fitting into this role?</li>
<li>Why might this role not be a good fit for me?</li>
<li>Who’s the highest ranking person who’s quit or been fired recently and why?</li>
<li>How do you define success for this role?</li>
</ul>
<p>Questions to ask your peers you’re interviewing with:</p>
<ul>
<li>describe your relationship with your manager?</li>
<li>describe the communication patterns of the team?</li>
<li>describe how decisions are made? What’s a recent decision that was made? describe your role in how the team made that decision?</li>
</ul>
<p>Other thoughts:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="../posts/2022-11-18-writing-a-tech-resume/index.html">Writing a Tech Resume</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>career advice</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/my-advice-for-new-career-people.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 20:19:05 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to Sign in with iCloud Calendar on Outlook for iOS</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/how-to-sign-in-with-icloud-calendar-on-outlook-for-ios.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>How do I add an iCloud account to iOS Outlook without it being a public calendar?</p>
<p>It was easy to add any gmail accounts but I didn’t know how to add my iCloud calendar to iOS Outlook. Part of the issue is my iCloud account is actually my gmail email address so I can’t sign in with this or it’ll load my gmail calendar.</p>
<p>Solution:</p>
<ul>
<li>go to iOS settings &gt; iCloud &gt; get your <code>@icloud.com</code> name. If you use your gmail account for iCloud there’s still this <code>@icloud</code> account.</li>
<li>Attempt to log into iOS Outlook calendar. Apple will then make you create an app-specific password for iOS Outlook</li>
<li>Use this password.</li>
</ul>
<p>Done. Pain solved.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>tutorial</category>
  <category>tips and tricks</category>
  <category>to my future self</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/how-to-sign-in-with-icloud-calendar-on-outlook-for-ios.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 20:54:28 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Book Summaries</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/book-summaries.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="../book-review/beyond-band-of-brothers.html">Beyond Band of Brothers: The War Memoirs of Major Dick Winters</a></p>
<p>Leadership from the bayonette. 10 points of leadership by dick winters.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Strive to be a leader of character, competence, and courage.</li>
<li>Lead from the front. Say, “Follow me!” and then lead the way.</li>
<li>Stay in top physical shape—physical stamina is the root of mental toughness.</li>
<li>Develop your team. If you know your people, are fair in setting realistic goals and expectations, and lead by example, you will develop teamwork.</li>
<li>Delegate responsibility to your subordinates and let them do their jobs. You can’t do a good job if you don’t have a chance to use your imagination or your creativity.</li>
<li>Anticipate problems and prepare to overcome obstacles. Don’t wait until you get to the top of the ridge and then make up your mind.</li>
<li>Remain humble. Don’t worry about who receives the credit. Never let power or authority go to your head.</li>
<li>Take a moment of self-reflection. Look at yourself in the mirror every night and ask yourself if you did your best.</li>
<li>True satisfaction comes from getting the job done. The key to a successful leader is to earn respect—not because of rank or position, but because you are a leader of character.</li>
<li>Hang tough!—Never, ever give up.</li>
</ol>
<p><a href="../book-review/how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people.html">How to Win Friends and Influence People</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-how-to-win-friends-bullet-points.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">How to win friends</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>personal development</category>
  <category>lists</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/book-summaries.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 21:36:34 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Costly Mistake</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/a-costly-mistake.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>“This is the moment I’ve been waiting for”…until it wasn’t.</p>
<p>Several years ago as a budding data scientist I got excited by using a massive compute cluster. This is it. This is when I get to do Big Data Science, baby!</p>
<p>A few thousand dollars later, I realized my hundred-dollar-an-hour cluster wasn’t doing the thing I hired it to do.</p>
<p>My patient manager David Mantilla ssh’d into my cluster and discovered that out of the 64 cores I paid for, I was using only 1.</p>
<p>A good manager goes a long way. He just laughed as I stared in horror at my gross misconduct.</p>
<p>Be kind to the noobs. Because you still are one in many ways…</p>
<p>#nerdtalk #dev #datascience #lessonslearned</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>life lessons</category>
  <category>data science</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/a-costly-mistake.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 21:29:50 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Implementing Culture</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/implementing-culture.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>One of the most important asset a company wields is its culture.</p>
<p>A culture is hard to define, but you know it when you see it. It’s the collective personality and written and unwritten rules of engagement. Since corporate employment is a social contract of two at-will parties, the culture emerges from the rules of conduct in which the employer is satisfied with continuing employment of the employee.</p>
<p>Values are lip service without implementation. Assume your company has the value “be kind”. Everyone has a different interpretation of what that means to them.</p>
<p>How do you know what a good culture is? People know the values of the culture and can highlight practices examples of it. The culture should live naturally, but also mechanically. Meaning, an employee will be kind while holding the door open for someone (be kind), but also provide explicit growth-oriented feedback.</p>
<p>Signs of a bad culture are therefore evident in the opposite of my definition. Like Lord of the Flies, employees are fending for survival and constantly exploring the boundaries because there are now rules of government. Employees that can’t recount what the values are or demonstrate how the company mechanically employs them are hoping for natural demonstration but get confused when they get mixed signals.</p>
<p>Toxic cultures can achieve financial success. “Toxic” has no concrete definition, but probably reveals people trying to survive on the island rather than thrive in a civilization. It stands, therefore, that a great culture will endure the battles of business, and come out tighter. At some point it won’t matter how bright your people are, how clever your IP is, or how many customers you have: culture is the rudder.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-large-boat-small-rudder.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">A small boat with a large rudder will get where it needs to go. But a large boat with a small rudder is doomed</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>interviewing</category>
  <category>culture</category>
  <category>business</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/implementing-culture.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2024 13:58:42 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Nothing to Lose</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/nothing-to-lose.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>There was a moment when I had everything to lose. When I was junior in high school, I was scared I’d be cut from the lacrosse team. There was only one coach and he didn’t have space for everybody. Coach held try outs.</p>
<p>My dad was traveling the week of try outs. I gave him a call. “What if I don’t make the team?”</p>
<p>He waits till I finish. And in a way characteristic of my Dad, he re-emphasizes the question. “<em>What</em> if? You go out there, you play your hardest, you give it your all. The rest is out of your hands. If you get cut, you get cut.”</p>
<p>He didn’t give me false praise or reassurance. He gave me perspective on life. He gave me “nothing to lose.”</p>
<p>I never worked harder in my athletics than that week. I just didn’t want to get cut.</p>
<p>Well, I passed try outs. So did everyone else because it was just a coaching trick to motivate us…but that’s beside the point. But my dad’s advice was never lost on me.</p>
<p>I had low confidence the whole season. Yet my coach took a surprising interest in me. I got playing time as a junior. I was a part time defender.</p>
<p>Little did I know, nor could I ever have imagined as a defender who could barely pass or catch, that in my coach’s last game, I would be sitting on the wrong side of the field. I would be standing, as a defender, right in front of the opposing team’s goalie crease. I’m not quite sure how I got there as the whole season I always sprinted off the field whenever we transitioned from defense to offense.</p>
<p>My coach always yelled at me. “Stay on the field!! It’s a fast break!” But I was always terrified of dropping the ball. I was great at defense. Great at scooping the ball. Great at passing it to an offender. This was my safe place.</p>
<p>Yet here I was, in the final minutes of the game. We had three, they had five. And I’m on the crease. What was I doing here?</p>
<p>My eyes and voice called to my teammate who saw me. My teammate who knew full well I had no intention of actually catching the ball. My teammate who would love to pass it to me if he had any assurance I’d actually catch it. I could see his eyes lock with mine and it only takes 8 years playing a sport to recognize that split-second glance, “Are you going to actually catch this?” My eyes asserted in that moment with my stick extended and ready “I really don’t know. But I’m wide open and I’m on the crease. And you have the defender and not me. So make a call.”</p>
<p>To my surprise he actually passed it. It didn’t have to be a just perfunctory vanity motion to please the coach. Because I’ve called for the ball many times in that wrote script, “oh please pass it I swear it’s worth all our time okay I did my thing now you guys go score because I’m outta here!”</p>
<p>I catch. I turn. I dunk. 4-5.</p>
<p>What just happened?</p>
<p>I asked Teddy later why he actually passed it to me. “I figured, what the heck? Maybe he’ll catch it!!” We both laughed. He had nothing to lose.</p>
<p>I didn’t know it then, but it was the last goal anybody would score for my coach. It was the last game of the season. The last game of his 35 year career at our school. I was wholly undeserving.</p>
<p>And that’s when you stand most to gain.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>memories</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/nothing-to-lose.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 11:53:31 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Personal Constitution</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/personal-constitution.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="preamble" class="level1">
<h1>Preamble</h1>
<p>In the spirit of the book <a href="../book-review/principles.html">Principles</a>, with a goal toward increased productivity through self-awareness and accountability, I cement here a personal constitution. I publish this publicly for all to read that I might benefit from their feedback.</p>
</section>
<section id="foundational-principles" class="level1">
<h1>Foundational Principles</h1>
<p><strong>Improvement through self awareness</strong>. As perhaps <a href="../book-review/socrates-a-life-worth-living.html">Socrates</a> said, “an unexamined life is not worth living”. To add my own twist: an examined life refines what’s worth living for. Like a chef with a fine palette, a self awareness acquired through reading, personal coaching, cognitive therapy, and above all journaling and hearing yourself talk, refines</p>
<p><strong>Trust thyself: I can’t grow unless I test my opinions.</strong> “Success&nbsp;in life is the&nbsp;result of good judgment.&nbsp;Good judgment&nbsp;is usually the&nbsp;result of experience.&nbsp;Experience&nbsp;is usually the&nbsp;result of bad judgment.” <a href="https://www.tonyrobbins.com/tony-robbins-quotes/">Tony Robbins</a> Alberto Savoia teaches in <a href="../book-review/the-right-it.html">The Right It: Why So Many Ideas Fail and How to Make Sure Yours Succeeds</a> the YODA framework - Your Own DAta. Only your own data is trustworthy. Intuition gets me to the point of knowing what data I need to collect. After intuition, there’s my opinion about what might happen, someone else’s opinion about what might happen, someone else’s data, and my own data. With limited time and the infeasability of collecting omniscient data (discussed in <a href="../book-review/how-to-decide-simple-tools-for-making-better-choices.html">How to Decide: Simple Tools for Making Better Choices</a> (Annie Duke)), I want to collect as much data as I can from other people’s mistakes by reading and learning. My value to the world, however, will come when I recognize that for a problem at hand that there is either data gathered via the Aristotlean methold of empirical evidence or Socratic method of reasoning by degrees. Judgment is used to determine whether data is worth being collected. In absence of data, “If we have data, let’s look at data. If all we have are opinions, let’s go with mine.” Jim Barksdale, CEO of Netscape (<a href="../book-review/trustworthy-online-controlled-experiments-a-practical-guide-to-ab-testing.html">Trustworthy Online Controlled Experiments: A Practical Guide to A/B Testing</a>). I will be unafraid to share my opinion, even if perceived as stupid or wrong.</p>
<p><strong>Assume Kindness, Give Kindness, Give and Seek Forgiveness.</strong> In a multi-cultural world, it’s hard to know what word might offend someone. I learned this by learning “Honduran” Spanish. The word for “Wednesday” in one culture might be a curse word in another. Inadvertantly, if I’m to share an opinion with the best of intentions, I may offend someone unwittingly due to the way I shared it or the way they interpreted it. Everyone communicates differently. Assume kindness means to assume they don’t intend harm. Give kindness means to speak with good intention. Giving and seeking forgiveness is the process of recognizing that in assuming or giving kindness, I’ll fall short but I can recover and let things go. Regardless of culture, we’re all human and want good feelings. We can operate in a way that cultivates these good feelings - a universal language.</p>
<p><strong>Vulnerability is recognizing weakness, which is the foundation of true, enduring strength</strong>. As discussed in <a href="../book-review/dare-to-lead.html">Dare to Lead</a> and <a href="../book-review/overcoming-the-five-dysfunctions-of-a-team.html">Overcoming the Five Dysfunctions of a Team</a>, teams fail when they’re not vulnerable, vulnerable in the sense that they’re self aware to share their strengths and weaknesses and ask for help in their weaknesses. A toxic environment is one that fails to recognize weakness, because like a limp knee that causes first hip, then shoulder issues appear. A powerful Christian teaching states, “I&nbsp;give&nbsp;unto men weakness that they may be humble;…for if they humble themselves before me, and have faith in me, then will I make&nbsp;weak&nbsp;things become strong unto them.” (<a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/ether/12?lang=eng&amp;id=p27#p27">Ether 12:27</a>). From this point of view, weakness is actually a gift. It’s a gift to rely on God (in my opinion, which is most often found in the goodness and grace of others) and ask for help. The Alcoholics Anonymous group recognizes the power of asking for help.</p>
</section>
<section id="principled-behaviors" class="level1">
<h1>Principled Behaviors</h1>
<p><strong>Opinions deserve to be dissected, and everyone is filled with biases.</strong> <strong>Challenging Opinions: Put out opinions, and challenge others’</strong>: “Strong opinions, loosely held” is a mantra in tech and means something different to everyone. I interpret this as “everyone <em>has</em> an opinion, most choose to let the most dominant opinion run the conversation”. “strong” means you recognize you actually do have an opinion, even if you don’t care. By sharing an opinion, you’re putting it out there to be challenged. Being willing to change it with new evidence is “loosely-held”. It’s demonstrated in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WY73exaVpyw">Elon Musk</a> changing his opinion of how to design Starship while talking to a reporter. Speak, be open to challenges, and adjust. If I don’t challenge opinions, I’m at risk of “I told you so” syndrome later, except you didn’t tell them and instead you inflate your internal ego and did nothing to solve the problem.</p>
<p><strong>Challenge theory, challenge data collection.</strong> As discussed in <a href="../book-review/scientific-freedom.html">Scientific Freedom</a> (Donald Braben), peer review is dying and failing the scientific process. As discussed in <a href="../book-review/the-coddling-of-the-american-mind.html">The Coddling of the American Mind</a> (Jonathan Haidt,&nbsp;Greg Lukianoff), cancel culture is crushing open and free discussion, opinions and movements usually driven by cognitive distortions. As demonstrated in <a href="../book-review/the-quest-for-cosmic-justice.html">The Quest for Cosmic Justice</a> (Thomas Sowell), there is usually strong contra-evidence to very dogmatic political beliefs about “how things should be”. If we reason with evidence like Sowell, challenge our beliefs like Haidt/Lukianoff, and seek to establish real, empirical truth like Braben, we’ll approach problems like <a href="../book-review/how-to-decide-simple-tools-for-making-better-choices.html">Duke</a> by considering all possibilitys, evaluating costs, and challenging internal biases. Data collection is difficult, and the procedures by which you collect data and draw conclusiosn from it must be challenged so that inferences can</p>
<p><strong>If I have an issue I’ll bring it to the problem first.</strong> If I have a conflict (see next section) with someone, I seek to resolve it behind closed doors first. It takes two people to resolve a conflict. If the conflict cannot be resolved behind closed doors, or repeatedly re-occurs despite my best efforts, I’ll proceed to a more defensive stance, which often resolves in me processing it through journaling.</p>
<p><strong>If I sense an issue, I seek to reassure those around me.</strong> I’ve been in several great organizations, and several toxic organizations. Once, 2 weeks after joining a team I interviewed everyone on the team. I could tell immediately that 6/12 were incredibly dissatisfied even if they didn’t say it. One of them went so far as to tell me they hated their boss. Within a year, 5/12 had left the team to go somewhere else in the org. On another occassion, I joined a team and within one week of joining, one person asked me to unionize. Again, a lot of discord. Within 6 weeks 10 of the 20 data scientists in the company were fired, including the disgruntled. In a third cirucmstance, a lot of disgruntled employees foment amongst themselves, each trying to solve their problems with management. Management doesn’t recognize even direct requests for changes in behavior. In all three of these circumstances, I work quickly to bring up the issues. I speak directly with management. I speak in the first person, keeping confidences, and only doing so usually at my own personal risk. I try to resolve what I have experienced, and what I have control over. Sometimes, people don’t want to change. Usually this results in failed organizations, but not always. In all three of these circumstances, I have witness failed organizations. The first was in a large organization where the manager got a horrible “do not recommend” rating from their peers. The second was an organization that lost all of its remaining data science talent. The third was an organization that lost multiple long-tenured teammates, even key leaders, that went on to get top jobs at other top companies. Belief: if talent gets a great job at a great company elsewhere, the company is doing something wrong.</p>
</section>
<section id="my-conflict-style" class="level1">
<h1>My Conflict Style</h1>
<p>Conflict, to me, isn’t a dirty word if two people have good intentions. It becomes dirty when both parties have bad intentions. It’s at its worst when one has good intentions and the other has bad.</p>
<p>As the youngest child of peaceful parents, my conflict style is to observe and self-reflect.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-ill-fail" class="level1">
<h1>How I’ll Fail</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>After doing a ton of work on myself, I’ve grown to an awareness of how I operate. There are past scars.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>I’ve been told I’m stupid before.</strong></p>
<p><strong>I’ve been fired before.</strong> This leads</p>
<p>I hyperfocus on the negative.</p>
<p>I reason by extremes.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/personal-constitution.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 10:06:03 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Trajectory and Mindset</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/trajectory-and-mindset.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Tony Robbins has said:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>What we can or cannot do, what we consider possible or impossible, is rarely a function of our true capability. It is more likely a function of our beliefs about who we are. <a href="https://www.tonyrobbins.com/tony-robbins-quotes/">Tony Robbins Quotes, Read These Famous Quotes from Tony Robbins</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The book <a href="../book-review/mindset.html">Mindset</a> talks about “fixed” vs “growth” mindsets. My post <a href="../posts/decisions-are-rivers.html">Decisions are Like Hopping on a River Raft</a> - decisions take you down to known endpoints.</p>
<p>Bring those two concepts together and on one hand there’s a trajectory - where you’re capable of going given your decisions (and mindset) and your mindset - how you perceive your circumstances.</p>
<p>Someone recently told me, “It’s not what you go through but how you perceive what you’re going through that matters.”</p>
<p>I believe perception is powerful. Any negative situation can be reframed for a positive. This is mindset.</p>
<p>But the other component is also important: where your circumstances will take you if pursued every day for the next 30 years.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-mountain-in-a-mountain-range.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Are you aimed toward the valley or the mountain? Neither is better, but one is probably better to you</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>If you’re an extremely happy person but you don’t take action to get out of a minimum wage job, such as spend time on self improvement, you’re going to stay in your minimum wage job (nothing wrong with that, just trying to illustrate a point).</p>
<p>And so, to get what you want out of life you can’t just assume things will get better without any change on your part. You can 1) change your mindset or 2) change your trajectory.</p>
<p>I’ve wondered whether at times in my career I was complacent or not, or whether I was growing doing what I was doing. That’s not a helpful question. Because if you’re too myopic you can miss that you doing your multiplication tables isn’t going to change anyone’s life, but if you can’t do multiplication you can’t be a machine learning engineer.</p>
<p>Most days in our work are steps. Steps towards something.</p>
<p>A spaceman can’t land on the moon unless they build a rocket. They won’t make a rocket unless they choose to land on the moon. And by choosing the moon they’re choosing to <em>not</em> open a Chinese restaurant.<sup>1</sup></p>
<p>Some roles have upper bounds. Staying at that upper bound isn’t a bad thing. It’s just a thing. Other roles open up different opportunities the longer you stick around, opportunities you won’t get else where perhaps.</p>
<p>So if you’re feeling stuck, ask:</p>
<ul>
<li>Where will I be if I stay with this for the next two years?</li>
<li>Is that directionally where I want now to head?</li>
<li>Is there something about my mindset I can change today to help me reframe so that I don’t miss the opportunities already around me?</li>
</ul>
<p>HTH.</p>


<section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Who has more impact? Well as cool as it is to land on the moon, it doesn’t actually do anything practically useful. A restaurant prevents millions of people from starving throughout its existence.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>career</category>
  <category>career advice</category>
  <category>decisions</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/trajectory-and-mindset.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 13:31:55 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Team Misfits</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/team-misfits.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I once played a game of pickup basketball with my football captain. He was a linebacker. All state. And got drafted to play in college. He was an incredible athlete.</p>
<p>But he moved like a clunky robot while playing basketball and couldn’t make a layup for his life.</p>
<p>Sometimes that’s how we are. As leaders, we should aim to help find where the misfits thrive.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-football-player-in-a-basketball-game.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Out of place</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>life lessons</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/team-misfits.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 10:06:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>World’s Longest Drive</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/worlds-longest-drive.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>There’s a fun $75,000 purse for the winner of the World’s Longest Drive.</p>
<p>These guys are averaging 400y in contest, which is an attempt to drive straight. This guy wins (ofc) but his first round is the best. 432.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Gv3YACYV648?si=jXXsfxfHxpmcpHFZ" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Apparently the record is 515 set in 1974 by Mike Austin, a 64 year old.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>It’s kind of crazy that since 1974 the record for longest drive hasn’t been broken.</li>
<li>Tech helps, but old school can sometimes be the way. Form over gear all day.</li>
</ol>
<p>But Berkshire broke that record per his Instagram account. Here’s the full scoop:</p>
<p><a href="https://golf.com/news/kyle-berkshire-worlds-longest-drive/">Inside Kyle Berkshire’s quest to hit the longest drive of all time</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/screenshot-world-longest-drive.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">579 yards</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>sports</category>
  <category>golf</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/worlds-longest-drive.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2024 20:40:56 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Iceberg Theory - Theory of Omission</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-iceberg-theory-theory-of-omission.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Hemingway introduced through his writing style the <a href="https://www.ijfmr.com/papers/2023/1/1646.pdf">Iceberg Theory</a>. It was something I noticed while reading <a href="../book-review/the-old-man-and-the-sea.html">The Old Man and the Sea</a>. You feel the depth of emotion from the “actions and dialogue”, rather than explicit descriptions.</p>
<p>It’s fun to contrast that with <a href="../concepts/frank-herbert.html">Frank Herbert</a>’s style which is “lay out the environment, have dialogue, then draw conclusions in the mind”.</p>
<p>Both styles speak to the thought that the writing is more interesting the less you write about. They call this “negative space” in drawing. A sketch is interesting when the mind can fill in the gaps. As an artist, you just want to make enough dots that they can connect them themselves. This connecting process is the freedom and interest the mind craves. It doesn’t want to be coddled (<a href="../book-review/the-coddling-of-the-american-mind.html">The Coddling of the American Mind</a>).</p>
<p>Back to the book. The Old Man and the Sea can be summarized in one sentence: a tired, old, and recently-unlucky man catches the biggest of his life and it gets eaten before he makes it home.</p>
<p>That’s the surface story, and it’s rather boring when thought of that way. But you just <em>feel</em> so much while reading it. You feel for the old man through the young boy. You feel for him as he teeters between passing out and existing. You remember the breaking points in your own life and want the man desperately to succeed. Luck, however, was not on his side.</p>
<p>“Talk less. Smile more.” - Hamilton</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-old-man-and-marlin.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Let their mind wander</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>storytelling</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>creativity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-iceberg-theory-theory-of-omission.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2024 12:44:41 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Compounding Interest of Reading</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-compounding-interest-of-reading.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m on my way to get 52 books read this year. I think I can do it.</p>
<p>But it’s not to finish 52 books. It’s to read two hours of fifty two books. Why?</p>
<p>Because of compounding interest. One book doesn’t level you up. But multiple books over time will affect you for a long while to come.</p>
<p>If you improve just 1% each day for 365 days, and that improvement compounds, then you’ll have improved 37x over a year. (invest $100 and gain 1% each day and reinvest that money is $137 by the end of the year).</p>
<p>So don’t worry what any one book gives you. Just keep investing. A few will pay off big, and the many “wasted” will have little downside.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-image-compound-interest-and-reading-a-book.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Image: compound interest and reading a book</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>reading</category>
  <category>investing</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-compounding-interest-of-reading.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 12:17:17 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Power of a Good Book</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-power-of-a-good-book.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Last night I went to a tapas style restaurant. I got 5 things. Then we opted for one more: battered cod tacos. Our taste buds rewarded us. That’s why we came.</p>
<p>Before that I was telling my wife, “I don’t see why my friend didn’t like the sushi. It’s fine. I just don’t know how to evaluate if something is worth it or not. Because it’s tasty, I’d recommend it…” This came off the heels of multiple times recently where I’ve gone out with people who are foodies that criticize the meal I’m enjoying and I’m left wondering: am I a food plebe?</p>
<p>Experiencing this last night was poignant. The whole meal was good. Not bad. Just good.</p>
<p>Then came the fish tacos.</p>
<p>That’s how it is with reading. You need to read a lot before the good and the bad start filtering out.</p>
<p>And like fish tacos, maybe there are even better ones out there, but I needed this one to point me in the direction of what’s possible.</p>
<p>And to some degree, there’s a dulling of sensitivities. If you haven’t read good literature in a long while perhaps you assume it’s all fine and “why <em>not</em> finish this book?”</p>
<p>But this year I’m trying to read many authors across many genres to tackle just that: find the books I really enjoy reading. And then ask myself, “why? What was special there?” So that I know what to look for next.</p>
<p>Last night I began <a href="../book-review/the-old-man-and-the-sea.html">The Old Man and the Sea</a> and it was a fish taco moment. I don’t know how I’ve avoided this book so long. I’m sure I read it in like sixth grade, but does that even count? And why have I largely avoided fiction for most of my adult life? I suppose having studied something very technical in college it pushed me to stop using that side of my brain. But getting back to good books, written with such depth and creative imagination, renew me with an awareness of the dullness of business books I’ve been dwelling in.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-old-man-and-the-fish-tacos.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">An Old Man and His Tacos</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And now, for ChatGPT to answer the prompt: “in the style of Ernest Hemingway, write three paragraphs about a man eating fish tacos”:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In the style of Ernest Hemingway, characterized by his terse and direct prose, the tale unfolds on a weathered pier stretching into the gray, restless sea. The man, solitary and rugged, sits at the edge where the wood meets the water, a plate of fish tacos beside him. His hands, calloused and strong, deftly assemble the tacos with an economy of movement that speaks of a life shaped by necessity rather than choice. The fish, freshly caught, bears the scent of the ocean, a fragrance as old as time, mingling with the sharp tang of lime and cilantro.</p>
<p>Around him, the world seems to hold its breath, the only sounds are the soft lapping of waves against the pilings and the distant cries of gulls, wheeling like specters in the overcast sky. He bites into a taco, the crispness of the tortilla giving way to the tender fish within, a simplicity that belies the depth of flavors. There’s a harmony here, between man and nature, a momentary peace found in the act of eating, of sustaining oneself with the bounty of the sea.</p>
<p>As he eats, his gaze is drawn to the horizon, where the gray of the sea blends indistinguishably with the sky. There’s a contemplation in his eyes, a man adrift in his thoughts as he is in life, finding solace in the simple pleasure of a meal. The tacos, humble yet fulfilling, become a metaphor for existence itself—uncomplicated in its components, yet profound in its satisfaction. In this moment, on this pier, the man and the sea are one, their stories intertwined in the quiet, unspoken understanding that life, in all its forms, is a series of solitary moments shared with the world.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Dang…“life shaped by necessity rather than choice” and “The tacos, humble yet fulfilling, become a metaphor for existence itself—uncomplicated in its components, yet profound in its satisfaction.” I’m glad Ernest is somewhere in there, AI. You may have a soul after all.</p>
<p>See also: <a href="../lists/reading-ethos.html">Reading Ethos</a></p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>reading</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-power-of-a-good-book.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 11:48:38 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Export your Libby Timeline to Obsidian</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/export-your-libby-timeline-to-obsidian.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I love reading and I love writing. Both are integral parts of learning. The reading to receive new ideas, the writing to cement those ideas to something.</p>
<p>As I stood up my blog I wondered how to get past books on here. There’s a way!</p>
<p>I now use Audible and Spotify audiobooks, but most of my past reads come from Libby.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-libby-icon.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Libby</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Here’s how you do it using Python:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Open Libby app and figure out how to export your timeline. Somewhere in settings. It’ll produce a CSV.</li>
<li>Go through that CSV and creat a column “read” that identified the ones you actually began (sigh…so many books I placed holds on but never read….)</li>
<li>Run this python script and it’ll create an obsidian markdown file for each. Tweak it to match your preferences. I personally use <code>quarto</code> to blog so I have a naming convention for the files and metadata.</li>
<li>Or! Just ask ChatGPT to do this for you lol.</li>
</ol>
<pre><code>from datetime import datetime, timedelta
import pandas as pd
import os
import zipfile
import re

# Load the provided spreadsheet using pandas
file_path = "~/Downloads/libbytimeline-activities.csv"
df = pd.read_csv(file_path)

# Parse the timestamp into the format yyyy-mm-dd and rename the column to 'date'
df["timestamp_raw"] = df["timestamp"]
df["timestamp"] = pd.to_datetime(df["timestamp"], format="%m/%d/%y %H:%M")
# create a stringed date
df["date"] = df["timestamp"].dt.strftime("%Y-%m-%d")

df[["date", "timestamp_raw"]]

# Custom column: Filter rows where read == 1 (went through spreadsheet to filter out those I had borrowed but never read).
df = df[df["read"] == 1]

# De-duplicate by title, keeping the most recent record (sorted by date)
df = df.sort_values("timestamp", ascending=False).drop_duplicates("title")

# Create a new column 'created' with today's date in yyyy-mm-dd format
today = datetime.now().strftime("%Y-%m-%d")
df["created"] = today

# Create a new column 'date-finished' that's the timestamp's date + 21 days
df["date-finished"] = (df["timestamp"] + timedelta(days=21)).dt.strftime("%Y-%m-%d")

# Prepare for markdown file creation
output_directory = os.path.expanduser("~/Desktop/markdown_files")
os.makedirs(output_directory, exist_ok=True)

# Loop through each item in the dataframe and create a markdown file
for index, row in df.iterrows():
    markdown_content = f"""
---
title: {row['title']}
description: _{row['title']}_ by {row['author']}. Published by {row['publisher']}, with ISBN {row['isbn']}. Read on {row['date']}
date: {row['date']}
categories: book-review
created: {row['created']}
draft: false
author: {row['author']}
book-year: 1000
book-time: 0
date-start: {row['date']}
date-finished: {row['date-finished']}
pct-complete: 0
---

![]({row['cover']}){{.preview-image}}
"""
    filename = re.sub(r"[^\w]", "-", row["title"]).lower()
    filename = re.sub(r"-+", "-", filename)
    file_path = os.path.join(output_directory, f"{filename}.md")
    with open(file_path, "w") as file:
        file.write(markdown_content.strip())
    print(f"Created {file_path}")

# Zip the markdown files
zip_file_path = os.path.expanduser("~/Desktop/markdown_files.zip")
with zipfile.ZipFile(zip_file_path, "w") as zipf:
    for root, dirs, files in os.walk(output_directory):
        for file in files:
            zipf.write(os.path.join(root, file), file)</code></pre>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>tutorial</category>
  <category>python</category>
  <category>libby</category>
  <category>quarto</category>
  <category>blogging</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/export-your-libby-timeline-to-obsidian.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 14:32:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Become a Data Scientist in 10 Weeks</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/a-10-week-self-guided-data-science-intro-course.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>How do you get a job in data science if you currently aren’t a data scientist?</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-tip no-icon">
<div class="callout-body d-flex">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container">
<p>The simplest thing you can do to get experience is do 5 Kaggle competitions and use ChatGPT like crazy to learn how to code, annalyze data, and build models. Use the ChatGPT code interpreter for $20/month and see how it works. Test its limits. If you’re new to data science, you won’t understand where it’s wrong, so just ask it: “how might this answer you gave me be wrong?”</p>
<p>The rest of this focuses on how to master the fundamentals, which will take you much farther and give you a foundation to build off of. But when in doubt, “doing” data science is much better than “learning” data science from books. Always strike a balance in your efforts: it takes far less time to read and learn principles, but it’s far more valuable to try “doing” a data science project with code.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="my-path-to-ds" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>My path to DS</h1>
<p>I asked this question while working as an analyst 8 years ago and wanting to break into data science. I wrote about it back then (lost the post), so I’m gonna revisit it now.</p>
<p>I was asked this question today: “how do I get started and get a job in data science if I don’t have any experience?” You may then wonder “I can’t get experience without a job…this is a chicken-and-egg problem.” False.</p>
<p>Simple: get experience. For free. In 10 weeks. Write a good resume. Network like crazy: connect with real people (and not just spam). Get rejected probably 20-30 times, learn from each rejection, keep learning and presto, you’ll finally have an offer. It’s honestly just a numbers game. Everyone “ahead” of you is an imposter just like you. Just figure out enough basics and you’ll be ready for your first job.</p>
<p>There are a million ways to do this, and a million blog posts like this one. But here’s my suggestion. Enjoy!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-plato-socrates-archimedes-and-r-a-fisher.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Some O.G. Data scientists</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="no-single-data-science-definition" class="level1">
<h1>No Single Data Science Definition</h1>
<p>Look at 10 job postings for data science and you’ll see 10 unique definitions for a data scientist. Roughly, I’d categorize them as such:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Human decision support: someone who supports others in their decision making. This would be their boss, their team, etc. Decisions are: should we shut this line of business down? Are our customers churning and how do we prevent that?</li>
<li>Machine Decision Support: someone who helps machines make automated decisions, like whether to approve an online credit card application, recommend a YouTube video, etc.</li>
<li>Product developer: someone who uses data to build a web product or service. This is similar to machine decision support, but the role might be in a SaaS capacity.</li>
</ol>
<p>Most of these things below will help with 1-2. Today, AI products are all the rage and I offer one week on deep learning to get you interested in 3. That being said, all the principles in each one of these sections is important in any field you pursue. # Mindset</p>
<p>While doing the following, on weeks 2-10, write one blog post to outline what you learned.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Where did you start? Why was it hard to learn? What did you want to know?</li>
<li>What concepts were new to you?</li>
<li>Do something with that knowledge. Search the internet to find data you can write about.</li>
</ol>
<p>If you don’t get very far, just move on to the next topic. Breadth is better early on to find out what you enjoy. Don’t get caught up in the details. Skim more. Write more. Worry less. You got this.</p>
<p>In all things, use ChatGPT to tutor you. Ask it questions. Be relentless. Have it explain things to you like you’re five.</p>
<p>Balancing learning between real books and ChatGPT is the best combo. ChatGPT is a better teacher, and the books have real info in them you can more fully trust. Using both together will get you there faster.</p>
<p>If any of the books below don’t vibe for you, there are a million free books out there. Find a simpler one and the same topic (and post in the comments so I can add it!)</p>
</section>
<section id="week-1-prepare-to-share" class="level1">
<h1>Week 1: Prepare to Share</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>By creating a blog you demonstrate the following: you like to learn, you can communicate, you can do hard things, you’re naturally curious, you’re contributing to the ecosystem. Lots of ways to show those things, but having a blog is at least one way.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Set up a blog.
<ul>
<li>Medium.com</li>
<li>Substack.com</li>
<li>(Harder) Or use <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a> and publish on GitHub</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Find 5 blogs by top data scientists. Read their posts. See what they write about.</li>
<li>Your first blog post is about what you like about these 5 blogs.</li>
<li>Share your blog post on all social media. LinkedIn, Twitter, Facebook.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="week-2-storytelling" class="level1">
<h1>Week 2: Storytelling</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>You can’t get credit for great data science work unless you can tell a story. Now that you have a blog, learn how to write about data.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://tellingstorieswithdata.com/">Telling Stories with Data</a></li>
<li>Find three data-focused blogs that use charts and analysis. Economist, FiveThirtyEight, DataIsBeautiful, etc.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="week-3-analytics-and-data-intuition" class="level1">
<h1>Week 3: Analytics and Data Intuition</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>To be able to make predictions about the future, you first need to understand how to understand the past.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Analytics is the foundation of data science. It’s the process of manipulating data and reshaping it to see it in new ways.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://wesmckinney.com/book/">Python for Data Analysis, 3E</a> - written by the creator of <code>pandas</code></li>
<li><a href="https://r4ds.hadley.nz/">R for Data Science (2e)</a> - written by the creator of <code>dplyr</code>, the best data manipulation language ever.</li>
</ul>
<p>Both these books are great. Read both. It’s good to learn early that there are multiple right ways of doing your analysis the wrong way 😉. Seeing how to think in two languages is actually easier than getting stuck on one.</p>
<p>Related: understand the bias in your data.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://datasciencehorizons.com/thinking-clearly-data-scientist-guide-understanding-cognitive-biases/">Thinking Clearly: A Data Scientist’s Guide to Understanding Cognitive Biases [eBook] – Data Science Horizons</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.analyticsinsight.net/top-5-biases-data-science/">Top 5 Biases in Data Science to Know for Model’s Accuracy</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="week-4-data-visualization" class="level1">
<h1>Week 4: Data Visualization</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Learning how to make a plot is like learning how to write. Learn how colors work. When to use them. When to use a bar vs.&nbsp;a line chart. How to make ideas shine.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://jjallaire.github.io/visualization-curriculum/">Visualization Curriculum</a></li>
<li><a href="https://r-graphics.org/">R Graphics Cookbook, 2nd edition</a></li>
</ul>
<p>This is after analytics because analytics is more important (knowing what to look for and how to think about data) than plotting it.</p>
<p>There are two types of plots: those for you to learn from and those for others to learn from. First, learn what’s in the data. Learn for yourself.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Look at the plot. Look at the plot. No seriously, look at the plot.” Chris Peterson, Capital One</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Second, plot for other people. After you’ve learned something by sifting out all the noise, learn how to communicate that externally.</p>
<p>Beautiful plotting is really hard and time consuming. Details can take hours. Focus on the basics at first. The simplest plot focuses on “what’s the one thing I want someone to take away from this?”</p>
</section>
<section id="week-5-get-data-you-dont-yet-have" class="level1">
<h1>Week 5: Get Data You Don’t Yet Have</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>If you work at a company &gt; 50 people, your company’s data is probably stored in a database. Learning how to get this data so you can do data analytics and visualization will help you be self sufficient.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Analytics is more important than this, because someone else may be able to get you the data. Or, once you know analytics then you can use SQL to <em>do</em> analytics.</p>
<p>Three primary ways to get data include the following:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>SQL (from a database, returns a spreadsheet like table)</li>
<li>API (get data from a website, returns JSON data)</li>
<li>Webscraping (getting it yourself, this is considered “unstructured” data)</li>
</ol>
<p>Interactive tutorials here are the way to go. Just google around for some good ones.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://sqlbolt.com/">SQLBolt - Learn SQL - Introduction to SQL</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.dataquest.io/blog/python-api-tutorial/">Python API Tutorial: Getting Started with APIs – Dataquest</a></li>
<li><a href="https://realpython.com/python-web-scraping-practical-introduction/">A Practical Introduction to Web Scraping in Python – Real Python</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="week-6-intro-to-machine-learning" class="level1">
<h1>Week 6: Intro to Machine Learning</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>This book nails the foundations of machine learning. Doesn’t get too mathy, but teaches you the principles.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.statlearning.com/">An Introduction to Statistical Learning</a></li>
<li>For reference, a more mathy and dense book that supports the Intro book is <a href="https://hastie.su.domains/Papers/ESLII.pdf">Elements of Statistical Learninf</a></li>
</ul>
<p>For content on how to get insights from machine learning models: - <a href="https://christophm.github.io/interpretable-ml-book/">Interpretable Machine Learning</a></p>
<p>Additional - understand the bias in your models <a href="https://www.tobiasbaer.net/algorithmic-bias">Tobias Baer - Risk Management, Data Science, and Psychology</a> - <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/machine-learning-for/9781098102425/ch04.html">4. Managing Bias in Machine Learning - Machine Learning for High-Risk Applications</a></p>
</section>
<section id="week-7-regression-analysis" class="level1">
<h1>Week 7: Regression Analysis</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Regression Is key to getting insights out of data. It’s what sets you apart from a data analyst role.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://peopleanalytics-regression-book.org/">Welcome | Handbook of Regression Modeling in People Analytics: With Examples in R, Python and Julia</a></li>
<li><a href="https://avehtari.github.io/ROS-Examples/">Regression and Other Stories</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="week-8-choose-your-own-adventure" class="level1">
<h1>Week 8 Choose your own Adventure</h1>
<section id="ab-testing-and-kpi-optimization-for-online-companies-applies-to-offline-too" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ab-testing-and-kpi-optimization-for-online-companies-applies-to-offline-too">A/B Testing and KPI Optimization for Online Companies (applies to offline too)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>All big internet companies use A/B testing, or split testing, to make decisions about how to improve their product. If you’re interested in software, or understanding how all modern websites and software are improved, you need to understand A/B testing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If You’ve taken stat 101, this is where the “t.test” gets used to literally make Big Tech billions of dollars. I’m not kidding. It’s simple, but it’s powerful.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://netflixtechblog.com/its-all-a-bout-testing-the-netflix-experimentation-platform-4e1ca458c15">It’s All A/Bout Testing: The Netflix Experimentation Platform | by Netflix Technology Blog | Netflix TechBlog</a></li>
<li>A seven part series by Netflix: <a href="https://netflixtechblog.com/netflix-a-culture-of-learning-394bc7d0f94c">Netflix: A Culture of Learning. Martin Tingley with Wenjing Zheng… | by Netflix Technology Blog | Netflix TechBlog</a> I put here the seventh post because it likes to parts 1-6 in the intro. This part 7 is probably the best to start with because it explains the context behind A/B testing.</li>
<li><a href="https://experimentguide.com/">Experiment Guide – Accelerate innovation using trustworthy online controlled experiments</a> This book tells you how Microsoft, Amazon, and Google use online experimentation to make billions of dollars. It’s written by the people who invented online experimentation and who are top data scientists at those companies.</li>
<li><a href="https://netflixtechblog.com/sequential-a-b-testing-keeps-the-world-streaming-netflix-part-1-continuous-data-cba6c7ed49df">Sequential A/B Testing Keeps the World Streaming NetflixPart 1: Continuous Data | by Netflix Technology Blog | Feb, 2024 | Netflix TechBlog</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="time-series-data" class="level1">
<h1>Time Series Data</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>All modern data is time series data in some way (data collected over time). Even though you may not use forecasting in everything or what not, understanding the nature of that data will set you apart. Focus on principles, not techniques as you may not use these specific techniques.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://otexts.com/fpp3/">Forecasting: Principles&nbsp;and&nbsp;Practice (3rd&nbsp;ed)</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="week-9-intro-to-deep-learning" class="level1">
<h1>Week 9: Intro to Deep Learning</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Deep learning is all the rage, and will change the future for everyone. It’s vital you know how these systems work because this is the future of society.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.fast.ai/">fast.ai - fast.ai—Making neural nets uncool again</a>
<ul>
<li>Great courses that teaches you how to build ChatGPT and Image Generators and understand it.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>This YouTube videos and others by him are great:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zjkBMFhNj_g" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Also this:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jkrNMKz9pWU" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</section>
<section id="week-10-recommendation-systems" class="level1">
<h1>Week 10: Recommendation Systems</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>If you’re making automated decisions with data, you’re probably using a recommendation system at some level. Recommendation systems typically focus on “what video does Bryan want given all the data we have on him and people like him?”. But the principles also extend to: how do I recommend one course of action to my stakeholder?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don’t have great resources here, but getting the concepts down will help you understand how virtually every social media app or streaming service works. (Netflix, Spotify, Instagram, etc all use recommenders to figure out the content you’re interested in. )</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://eliassi.org/charu_recsys_intro.pdf">http://eliassi.org/charu_recsys_intro.pdf</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="week-11-do-projects" class="level1">
<h1>Week 11+: Do Projects</h1>
<p>Now that you’ve studied analytics, data viz, regression, machine learning, and deep learning, create two blog posts or personal projects.</p>
<ul>
<li>Build a dashboard using a Jupyter notebook that updates daily. You can host on GitHub using quarto to render the notebook and use GitHub actions to update it every day.</li>
<li>Create a model to predict who will win the next NBA game</li>
<li>Analyze any data from data.gov</li>
<li>Kaggle competitions!</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="prepare-your-resume" class="level1">
<h1>Prepare your Resume</h1>
<p>Now you’ve got 10 blog posts, which is 10 more bullet points on your resume than you had before you started. You’ve learned a ton if you only do 10% of all that’s above.</p>
<p>I’ve loved the advice I found written up here: <a href="../posts/2022-11-18-writing-a-tech-resume/index.html">Writing a Tech Resume</a>.</p>
<p>Once you have a good resume, find real people to give it to. Dont apply blindly online. Talk to everyone you know. Find people on LinkedIn and message them directly with a personal message. Use one of your blog posts in your message to tell them why you’re a good fit for their role. Perhaps even write a blog post specific to data from their company!</p>
<p>Good luck!</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>data science</category>
  <category>featured</category>
  <category>career</category>
  <category>recommendation systems</category>
  <category>A/B testing</category>
  <category>analytics</category>
  <category>beginners</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/a-10-week-self-guided-data-science-intro-course.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 21:59:18 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Only Mind that’s Clear Is the One That Sees No Alternative</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-only-mind-thats-clear-is-the-one-that-sees-no-alternative.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The easiest thing one can do is see the world through their own viewpoints. It takes no effort. Takes no work. It’s already done: your viewpoints are there. Either you care about climate change today or you don’t. Either you care about opossums or you don’t. You are who you are, right now.</p>
<p>The only gap between who you are today and who you are tomorrow is what you learn and experience and how you see the world because of what you learn and experience.</p>
<p>You learn from others. You learn from your experiences. You learn from other’s experiences.</p>
<p>The goal isn’t to be right. The goal is to understand.</p>
<p>And so, I believe in the value of learning from those around me, especially those I disagree with. It’s hard work to grind through walls of disbelief or misunderstanding. But it’s always worth it, even if at the other side you merely understand. That in and of itself is a destination worth pursuing because of the many benefits it yields.</p>
<p>But beware, with an assumption of understanding comes peril. Therefore, the goal is to constantly seek understanding, because no person is every the same one day to the next.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-seeing-through-a-glass-darkly-and-then-clearly.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Seeing through a glass darkly and then clearly</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Sources: - <a href="../book-review/how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people.html">How to Win Friends and Influence People</a> - the constant focus of the book is to put yourself in the other’s shoes. - <a href="../book-review/greenlights.html">Greenlights</a> African tribe: don’t seek to be right. Seek to understand. - <a href="../book-review/the-coddling-of-the-american-mind.html">The Coddling of the American Mind</a> - tribalism is when you don’t see another’s viewpoint and only feel you are right.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>my principles</category>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-only-mind-thats-clear-is-the-one-that-sees-no-alternative.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 20:31:52 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Writing Only Makes Sense to the Author</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/writing-only-makes-sense-to-the-author.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>If you’re a bad author</em>, your writing will only make sense to you.</p>
<p>Problem is, we’re all bad authors.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>My writing makes sense as I put it fown</li>
<li>It doesn’t always make sense to me 5 minutes later (my future self is practically another person)</li>
<li>The probability of it being perfectly interpreted by someone who isn’t even me, is likely near zero.</li>
</ol>
<p>So when we write, we send out an idea. It then becomes a painting on the wall, up for anyone to interpret how they may.<sup>1</sup> therefore, it’s best to put yourself as much in your audience’s shoes as possible (something discussed often in <a href="../book-review/how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people.html">How to Win Friends and Influence People</a>).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-image-people-in-an-art-museum-staring-at-a-painting-of-scribbles-on-the-wall.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">“Now what on earth was Bryan trying to say?!?” “I think he was inspired” “nah man, he just wrote scribbles on the wall. That’s not writing!” “Yea, maybe he should slap a banana with duct tape on there. Would have gotten the point across better”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


<section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Going to an extreme - ever write a kind word that was taken as an insult, or sent something sarcastic and it was interpreted as literal?↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>communication</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>art</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/writing-only-makes-sense-to-the-author.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 12:01:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Problem with Public Opinions</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-problem-with-public-opinions.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>If you become a public opinion person (author, speaker, podcaster), you’re inherently inviting publicity bias.</p>
<p>A message is like a product. If it’s not well received, either through attention, clicks, or books purchased, then most people may abandon the idea. Very few (those seeking truth), are staunch advocates of an opinion not popularly received.</p>
<p>Even unpopular opinion people try out their ideas. They may rise on social media as “they want to cancel me, so trust my opinion”. That sales pitch only lasts so long as you’re a minority.</p>
<p>Point is: if your opinion gets reception, you’re less likely to change your opinion. This is a problem in politics for people who espouse something for a long time.</p>
<p>Instead we should be like Galileo: show me the data.</p>
<p>So be cautious if people like your opinion because you may be at risk of not being able to change it, either through your own evolving greed or desire for social acceptance and popularity.</p>
<p>The reception of an idea doesn’t determine its truthfulness, but the ability of the idea to stand on its own.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-galileo-stars.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Look for the evidence, not the popularity</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I always try to think about this when listening to a popular author or podcaster: what about their idea has garnered popularity? Have they changed course in the face of evidence? I recall Amy Cuddy having one of the most popular Ted talks on Power Poses, only to have a Slate article come out that refused her research. She doubled down despite her research not being reproducible: the gold standard a scientist should seek.</p>
<p>Few people are like Amy Cuddy in that their ideas cannot be easily tested and so the world lazily believes them. This is the risk: when people stop thinking for themselves.</p>
<p>Things why Frank Herbert wrote <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>: to encourage people to think for themselves and not put too much trust in their leaders.</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="../goals/2024-01-17.html">2024-01-17</a> update:</p>
<p>Chapter 14 of <a href="../book-review/the-quest-for-cosmic-justice.html">The Quest for Cosmic Justice</a> discusses this way better than I do here.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <category>social media</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-problem-with-public-opinions.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 22:19:58 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
