<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/all.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/all.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 10:25:55 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Things I Don’t Understand</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/things-i-dont-understand.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I don’t know about or understand a lot of things. Here’s a random list:</p>
<ul>
<li>molecular biology</li>
<li>brain surgery</li>
<li>Shakespeare</li>
<li>Diplomacy between nations</li>
<li>Best teaching methods for four year olds</li>
<li>How the heater in my house works</li>
<li>How Apple Silicon works</li>
<li>A lot of data science stuff despite working as a data scientist for 10 years</li>
</ul>
<p>The thing with knowledge is that the more you get of it, the more questions you have about the world. It was kind of hard even making that list above because I know enough to know that I don’t know enough about it. What about all the things I know nothing about. Or scarier, what about the things I think I know something about but really don’t.</p>
<p>All these things mean there’s something to be learned on every day, every minute. The world is full. We are all multi-faceted individuals who can do a ton of different things. Perhaps often we compare ourselves to those who know most about a subject vs the value and opportunity we bring with the unique set of knowledge each of us has accumulated.</p>
<p>I’m grateful I’m usually wrong. It means there’s a better way. And if things turned out okay <em>and</em> I’m wrong, that’s even better: it means I can improve!</p>
<p>I’m grateful I’m able to learn from anyone on earth, who at least has a guaranteed different life experience and set of knowledge gained. I’m also grateful that everyone else is as imperfect as me, which means I can challenge them to figure out how they came to their knowledge and whether their knowledge is actually that or just a belief/opinion/etc.</p>
<p>All of this is fun, gives diversity to life, lets me know that there’s hope for a better world.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-library-of-brains.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Learning from brains that learn from books written by brains</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>epistemology</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/things-i-dont-understand.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 10:25:55 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 9.3</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-9.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>for the special purpose that there should be an account engraven of the ministry of my people.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>See <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/1-ne/9?id=p3&amp;lang=eng#p3">1 Nephi 9.3</a></p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I have received a commandment of the Lord that I should make these plates, for the special purpose that there should be an account engraven of the ministry of my people.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>See <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/1-ne/9?id=p3&amp;lang=eng#p3">1 Nephi 9.3</a></p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>favorite scriptures</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-9.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Music</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/music.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Music is a beautiful thing.</p>
<p>I’m not much of a musician, but I do love it. The first time I learned to play the guitar I felt a new form of communication.</p>
<p>I had known the piano before that, having played it in high school. But there was something about the guitar that taught me how to speak with music.</p>
<p>You speak with random noises from your mouth, surely you can speak with emotion from a musical instrument.</p>
<p>And people do. Great musicians communicate something in a way that words alone cannot express. And sometimes the music itself evokes an identity you didn’t know existed.</p>
<p>That’s the power of music. And I think it’s really cool that humans all over the world understand this power.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-guitar-on-the-beach.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">At some point you wanted to be this guy or girl, admit it.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<p>Reminds me as well of a close friend who wrote an album when a loved one passed away. Those were some of the most beautiful lyrics and music I had ever heard. Sometimes the best music comes from nobodies, including yourself.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>music</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/music.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 15:55:40 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Power of Habitual Prayer</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/the-power-of-habitual-prayer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I want to share my experience with how prayer has turned from not very meaningful to substantively helpful in a matter of a few short weeks.</p>
<p>Consider the scene:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote page-columns page-full">
<p>Children jumping on beds. Refusing to get dressed or brush their teeth or go to the bathroom. Screaming from the other room. Screaming from this room. Exhausted after a long day. I just want things to change and be different.<sup>1</sup></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;while writing this the insight came: I’m in the state of mind of wanting them to change. This is a mindset of control (<a href="../christianity/stop-trying-to-change-people.html">Stop trying to change people. Stop it.</a>). The fallacy a mind believes is “if only they’re better I’d be at more peace”. Consider the alternative: if they were peaceful but I’m still in a mindset of control. Would I be happier? Perhaps I would feel more comfortable (less noise in my ear). But I’m going to posit that a person in a mindset of control, regardless of whether they’re being listened to and their control is being obeyed, aren’t happy and aren’t mindful. They aren’t present with what is. A healthier mindset for me might be: “anything could happen, delightful that they’re food now, but it’s okay if they misbehave. They’re kids! How can I <a href="../christianity/find-the-fun.html">Find the Fun</a> in this moment?”</p></li></div></blockquote>
<p>Any parent comes across this more than once per day.</p>
<p>Most of last year I felt like I wasn’t getting a whole lot out of my prayers. A few comments:</p>
<ul>
<li>I try praying daily. But I found it hard to focus. Praying out loud helps with this, but I didn’t do it often.</li>
<li>even though I felt my prayers not well focused, I do believe God heard them regardless and by praying in an unfocused state I could still get <em>something</em> out of the experience. I believe God looks down on us when we’re trying, rather ineffectually, to do our best</li>
<li>I felt like my prayers were ineffective because I’d pray and mumble and think about work until I’d come back to me being in a prayer and then I’d say Amen. I’d always wondered what my experience would be like if I really felt a connection to God.</li>
</ul>
<p>Okay. So that’s last year. Lots of prayers. I know God loves me regardless of how effective they are. And I know they could be better.</p>
<p>Back to the scene. There were several times last year when the kids were nuts and I needed to calm myself down. It was hard. I tried a few times to go and pray but just felt like “it’s not working!” Im praying! Why can’t I get to a better state of mind?! This prayer thing isn’t working for me and I’m doing it wrong.</p>
<p>I never felt like prayer wasn’t good or useful. Just that I couldn’t get it to do what I wanted it to do for me: fix me. I figured: maybe I need to pray differently. Or try XYZ thing.</p>
<p>Okay, so throw up a prayer and hope it sticks. Change me! I’m here.</p>
<p>Nope. Didn’t work. I’d still be struggling with patience in those circumstances.</p>
<p>Last night I had a new experience. I <em>did</em> pray the same way I’ve prayed before when stressed. No, I didn’t get fixed - God doesn’t fix us like that. Instead, while praying I remembered a mindset <a href="../christianity/find-the-fun.html">Find the Fun</a> that I had discovered last week. That’s all that came to mind. I left the prayer still agitated because a kid was about to jump on another kid while I was praying and I had to leave the prayer.</p>
<p>What happened though? I was just like 20% less stressed as I tried focusing on <a href="../christianity/find-the-fun.html">Find the Fun</a>.</p>
<p>Okay, so the night went better than it did last week. I had something in my mind to hold on to.</p>
<p>What’s the difference between the me yesterday and the me of three weeks ago? I changed my relationship with prayer.</p>
<p>I’ve been trying to have just one good prayer per day. It’s a goal for this year. And a good prayer is one where I try to get some type of insight. Like meditation. Just pray until an insight. Setting a timer helps me. Doing it in my office or a place where I’m alone helps too. And when I’m done, I write down the insight.</p>
<p>Most of the time the insight isn’t like from God or anything. I don’t hear a voice. I don’t have any mental image. The insight for me usually comes from me hearing myself pray. “Oh, I didn’t realize that was on my mind” or “oh, how did I think of that?” I’ve come to learn that this is a spiritual prayer. This <em>is</em> praying by the spirit. When I desire to connect with God (get something out of my prayer), I’m elevated ever so slightly (<a href="../gratitude/small-things.html">I’m grateful for small things</a>).</p>
<p>And that’s it: I’ve been doing this for about two or weeks now and my relationship with prayer is changing. I no longer want it to fix me. I see it as a way to try to connect with heaven in a small way.</p>
<p>And that’s the realization: the power of prayer isn’t in the hail Mary’s. It’s in the consistent relationship with it.</p>
<p>I <em>do</em> believe a Hail Mary is better than no Hail. So hail away.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And now the Lord was slow to hear their cry because of their iniquities; <strong>nevertheless the Lord did hear their cries</strong> <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-21.15">Mosiah 21.15</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Lord hears your cries even if you’re wicked. Pray regardless. But there is a concept of Him being slow to hear at times: feeling the effect of prayer requires consistency. But he’s happy to help any time we come to Him. He’s not vindictive. He’s not “I told you so” or “you should be coming to me more often than this”. That’s how we treat each other, with pride. God isn’t like that. Heavenly Father wants us to come to him, and he’ll hear our cries.</p>
<p>Translating this to me: i wasn’t wicked or anything. I was just a stressed out dad. But I think the principle applies: if I have a lackluster relationship with prayer then he’ll be slow to hear. Or, said another way, <em>I’ll</em> be slow to hear. Slow to see. More reactive. More knee jerky and less patient. More thinking “why doesn’t this prayer thing work for me?”</p>
<p>So that’s my insight. Make prayer meaningful and it starts to pay dividends slowly. Very slowly. But I also believe in compounding interest.</p>
<p>if your investments gain 0.1% each day of the year, do you know what your returns would be over a year? 44% increase. So if you invest $100 today, by the end of the year you’ll have $144 if you keep reinvesting your returns. Thats insanely good! But that’s math. that’s compounding interest.<sup>2</sup></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;The math is this: 1.001^365=1.44. Or, your daily return is 1.001. Invest $10 and you’ll have $10.01 by the end of day one. Invest $10.01 on day two and gain 0.1% and you’ll have $10.02001 by end of day two. Do this 365 times and you’ll have $10*1.001^365=$14.40</p></li></div><p>So shoot for a 0.1% prayer. That’s all it’s gotta be to get massive returns.</p>
<p>So that’s the invitation: try to make prayer meaningful (whatever that means to <em>you</em>, not me). And try to do it consistently.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>But this is not all; ye must pour out your souls in your closets, and your secret places, and in your wilderness. <a href="../scriptures/alma-34.26">Alma 34.26</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-pray-in-your-wilderness.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Pray alone in your wilderness. Find somewhere.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>




<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>my testimony</category>
  <category>personal stories</category>
  <category>prayer</category>
  <category>scripture of the day</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>featured</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/the-power-of-habitual-prayer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 09:09:36 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 8 - Think for yourself</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-8-what-others-think.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This is an interesting scripture:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>and they were in the attitude of mocking and pointing their fingers towards those who had come at and were partaking of the fruit. And after they had tasted of the fruit they were ashamed, because of those that were scoffing at them; and they fell away into forbidden paths and were lost. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-8.27-28">1 Nephi 8.27–28</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Imagine you’re eating at a Michelin star restaurant and across the street there’s a food court at the mall with a bunch of people eating McDonalds and Burger King. And <em>they’re</em> mocking <em>you</em>.</p>
<p>Reasons this relationship is so fascinating:</p>
<ul>
<li>the people in the building don’t know what the tree tastes like.</li>
<li>The people in the building are far away.</li>
<li>The people eating the fruit are able to be numbed by the perceptions of others, and aren’t focusing on their own experience.</li>
</ul>
<p>If those who became ashamed had focused instead on their own experiences it would have been delicious.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-lehi-dream.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Lehi’s dream</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-8-what-others-think.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 00:23:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2024-01-21 Come Follow Me CTR 7 Jan 15-21 1 Nephi 6-10</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-21-jan-21.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Activity ideas</p>
<section id="studies" class="level1">
<h1>Studies</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-6-god-of-the-covenant.html">1 Nephi 6 - God of the Covenant</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-7-commitment.html">1 Nephi 7</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="activity-ideas" class="level1">
<h1>Activity Ideas</h1>
<ul>
<li>“let me see” (<a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-11.1.html">1 Nephi 11.1</a>) - show a video to one kid, have him share or try to draw it. Have others try to understand. They just have to see for themselves.</li>
</ul>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me lesson plan</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-21-jan-21.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 23:34:29 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 7 - Make a Choice, Don’t go Halvsies</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-7-commitment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="nephi-7" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>1 Nephi 7</h1>
<p>This exchange is fascinating:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Now behold, I say unto you that if ye will return unto Jerusalem ye shall also perish with them. <strong>And now, if ye have choice, go up to the land, and remember the words which I speak unto you, that if ye go ye will also perish;</strong> for thus the Spirit of the Lord constraineth me that I should speak.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Laman and Lemuel don’t want to be in the wilderness, but when Nephi tells them they have their agency, they’re not brave enough to go back to Jerusalem.</p>
<p>In other words, he catches them in their rouse. “Nobody’s forcing you”, go back if you want, but if you do you’ll remember that you’re going to die there.</p>
<p>How often do we like to complain about something but not actually do anything about it? Reminds me of the quote “So then because thou art lukewarm, and neither cold nor hot, I will spue thee out of my mouth.” (<a href="../scriptures/revelation-3.16">Revelation 3.16</a>)</p>
<p>If you don’t want to do anything about it, don’t complain. Vote with your feet, not your mouth. (They were voting with their feet to leave Jerusalem but voting with their mounts against it.)</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-walking-away.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">If you’re gonna walk, walk. If you’re gonna follow the prophet, follow.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>16 And it came to pass that when I, Nephi, had spoken these words unto my brethren, they were angry with me. And it came to pass that they did lay their hands upon me, for behold, they were exceedingly wroth, and they did bind me with cords, for they sought to take away my life, <strong>that they might leave me in the wilderness to be devoured by wild beasts.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-7.15-16">1 Nephi 7.15–16</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Also interesting is how they didn’t directly want to kill Nephi (didn’t have the courage here to try), but instead just decided to leave him to die (Joseph of Egypt style).</p>
<p>This is one of those “I’m not actually sinning because I didn’t do the sin” things. Tying someone up isn’t killing them. Should they die, that’s an unfortunate derivative consequence. But <em>we</em> didn’t kill him. <sup>1</sup></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;They were living the Old law. Perhaps this was legal. But the law of the heart says: this is attempted murder.</p></li></div><p>Backing up to a higher point: how often do we skirt the issue and not take full accountability? They can’t go back to Jerusalem and they can’t even properly attempt murder. They’re just lazy and without conviction all around.</p>
<p>But so are we. We all have these tendencies to disassociate from accountability for our life:</p>
<ul>
<li>well X person is annoying. “Are you going to talk to them?” No…</li>
<li>Etc…</li>
</ul>
<p>Own up. # Other Verses of Interest</p>
<p>Today I liked these verses:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wherefore, the things which are pleasing unto the world I do not write, but the things <strong>which are pleasing unto God and unto those who are not of the world.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-6.5">1 Nephi 6.5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Am I someone who is not of this world? Fascinating question because it makes me wonder what is “the world”. What was Nephibtrying to define here? Perhaps he was summarizing in his own way that those who have their head in the spiritual clouds will love these things, while those who live by “the world” won’t. It’s also reflective of his experience trying to share the gospel that some people don’t care. They just want to enjoy the pineapples and what not. Am I distracted by money, fame, greed, envy?</p>
<hr>
<p>I also got a little ahead and listened to this scripture:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For it came to pass after <strong>I had desired to know the things that my father had seen, and believing that the Lord was able to make them known unto me</strong>, as I sat pondering in mine heart I was caught away in the Spirit of the Lord, yea, into an exceedingly high mountain, which I never had before seen, and upon which I never had before set my foot. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-11.1">1 Nephi 11.1</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>My kids love to come up to my phone and say “let me see!!!” If they hear audio in another room they come sprinting.</p>
<p>Why do kids love seeing? They want to see. They’re sponges. They’re also without much experience in life so they want to see it all! Make up for lost time…</p>
<p>To become like a little child is to want to see for ourselves.</p>


</section>


<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>commitment</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <category>epistemology</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-7-commitment.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 23:34:11 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Problem with Public Opinions</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-problem-with-public-opinions.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>If you become a public opinion person (author, speaker, podcaster), you’re inherently inviting publicity bias.</p>
<p>A message is like a product. If it’s not well received, either through attention, clicks, or books purchased, then most people may abandon the idea. Very few (those seeking truth), are staunch advocates of an opinion not popularly received.</p>
<p>Even unpopular opinion people try out their ideas. They may rise on social media as “they want to cancel me, so trust my opinion”. That sales pitch only lasts so long as you’re a minority.</p>
<p>Point is: if your opinion gets reception, you’re less likely to change your opinion. This is a problem in politics for people who espouse something for a long time.</p>
<p>Instead we should be like Galileo: show me the data.</p>
<p>So be cautious if people like your opinion because you may be at risk of not being able to change it, either through your own evolving greed or desire for social acceptance and popularity.</p>
<p>The reception of an idea doesn’t determine its truthfulness, but the ability of the idea to stand on its own.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-galileo-stars.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Look for the evidence, not the popularity</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I always try to think about this when listening to a popular author or podcaster: what about their idea has garnered popularity? Have they changed course in the face of evidence? I recall Amy Cuddy having one of the most popular Ted talks on Power Poses, only to have a Slate article come out that refused her research. She doubled down despite her research not being reproducible: the gold standard a scientist should seek.</p>
<p>Few people are like Amy Cuddy in that their ideas cannot be easily tested and so the world lazily believes them. This is the risk: when people stop thinking for themselves.</p>
<p>Things why Frank Herbert wrote <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>: to encourage people to think for themselves and not put too much trust in their leaders.</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="../goals/2024-01-17.html">2024-01-17</a> update:</p>
<p>Chapter 14 of <a href="../book-review/the-quest-for-cosmic-justice.html">The Quest for Cosmic Justice</a> discusses this way better than I do here.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <category>social media</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-problem-with-public-opinions.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 22:19:58 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Paradise Lost and Paradise Regained</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/paradise-lost-and-paradise-regained.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="../goals/2024-01-16">2024-01-16</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Satan delights in giving war, regardless if he can’t win.</li>
<li>Satan delights in having raised war, feeling he is proud and strong for resisting good. Being courageous to walk out. But his courage only warranted misery.</li>
<li>“The mind is powerful. Can make heaven of hell or hell of heaven.”</li>
<li>Why would Satan want to walk away, knowing he was giving up godhood? What motivated him more than happiness?</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-paradise-lost-and-paradise-regained.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Paradise Lost and Paradise regained</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/paradise-lost-and-paradise-regained.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 20:51:13 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Open Source</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/open-source.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Open source software is incredible. I’m deeply grateful for the people who create it and share it.</p>
<p>So much of the world benefits from open source software. YouTube was built off Python. Samsung phones run on Android. Most modern websites are built off something Zuckerberg released. PyTorch and Tensorflow have ushered in the AI revolution.</p>
<p>We’d get along without open source. But we’d be using SAS or Stata, beholden to Oracle and Java everywhere and just enduring a slow pace of innovation.</p>
<p>AI is open sourced. The future is now.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-open-source-personified.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Open source as a person, according to ClosedAI</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/open-source.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 17:07:25 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 6 - God of the Covenant</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-6-god-of-the-covenant.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Nephi introduces the concept of the “God of Abraham” in the Book of Mormon:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For the fulness of mine intent is that I may persuade men to come unto the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, and be saved. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-6.4">1 Nephi 6.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Why? Well, repetition helps us remember. Calling out multiple names also tells us that there were several generations of believers. Also, many people are descendants of these folks so using their name invokes their ancestry. These are three reasons why Nephi (and others) may use this triple threat to identify the God we can worship.</p>
<p>But I think there’s one more reason: the God of the Old Testament is Jesus. He’s the god is the covenant. The covenant of Abraham in which all seeds of the earth shall be blessed. God of Isaac and Jacob - who also received more covenants.</p>
<p>When we worship a God of covenants, we become empowered by those covenants.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>scripture of the day</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-6-god-of-the-covenant.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 23:56:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Ice Skating</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/ice-skating.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today I went ice skating. It was great.</p>
<p>I remembered a video about this old guy that wakes up at 5am or something and goes out and waters the ice rink. He fills up a few tubs of his own hot water and just treks over to the public park to fill up the rink. He uses his own homemade zamboni and what not.</p>
<p>There are good people in this world.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-ice-rink-outdoors.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Ice rink</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>What’s cool about an ice rink is I don’t think about it for 364 days a year. But it’s there when I want to go. So that means enough people love it to keep it in business, and I can go only when I want to (once a year). Thats a cool thing too: collective community makes so many things possible, like downtown restaurants and museums - places that if they relied just on me they’d never last. But the community keeps them afloat (pun?).</p>
<p>I tried finding it, but this is the closest thing I could find. Just imagine this very old guy out there shlepping 55 gallon drums of water.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/MU37fBl-MR0?si=UcwfJ6-LM6KsgpNg" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<hr>
<p>I found it!</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>It’s just become a way of life. If I don’t do the rink I don’t feel right.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WJ-POcAxXyg?si=kFRU6jv20uW-gbPi" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>What a guy.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/ice-skating.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 20:49:56 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 5 - Will a promise be delivered?</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-5-trusting-a-promise.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Lehi and his wife Sariah are at base camp while their boys are trying to get the plates (ancient record/scriptures) from a ruthless Laban. Sariah gets very nervous (v1-3), perhaps thinking they’ve been killed.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-weary-wanderer-waiting.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Waiting in the wilderness</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Then once she sees them come back (mission accomplished) she rejoices:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And she spake, saying: Now I know of a surety that the Lord hath commanded my husband to flee into the wilderness; yea, and I also know of a surety that the Lord hath protected my sons, and delivered them out of the hands of Laban, and given them power whereby they could accomplish the thing which the Lord hath commanded them. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.8">1 Nephi 5.8</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But what if they hadn’t come back? Is this just confirmation bias?</p>
<p>No.&nbsp;</p>
<p>See, Sariah had been promised her sons safe return:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>and I know that the Lord will deliver my sons out of the hands of Laban, and bring them down again unto us in the wilderness. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.5">1 Nephi 5.5</a> (Lehi talking)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Because of this (a specific promise), we often fixate in contrary to the exact thing we should be expecting.</p>
<p>Consider Adam and Eve: don’t eat that one tree. Eat anything else. Everything else. Just not that one. → which one?<sup>1</sup> this one? Oh, we ate it.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;im being funny here, because there’s a lot more to the Adam and Eve story - they were supposed to eat it. Point is: we focus on what we’re told not to do.</p></li></div><p>Perhaps Sariah fixates on her sons not returning because that is what a prophet promised her.</p>
<p>Interestingly, there must be a space in time between when a promise is made and a promise is delivered (<a href="../scriptures/alma-40.6-9">see Alma 40.6–9</a> for similar logic). We are not told the length of that in between time. Could be today. Could be tomorrow. Who knows how long Sariah was waiting.</p>
<p>An interesting corollary: she wasn’t doubting something she <em>wasn’t</em> promised.</p>
<p>Consider all the promises in the scriptures. Abraham is promised the gospel will be in his seed. Nephi is promised his seed will be destroyed (he was the righteous one) and Laman and Lemuel were implicitly promised their seed would remain (even though they were wicked). Joseph of Egypt promised some things, Enos is promised other things, etc. We’re all unique.</p>
<p>Let’s consider Peter and John. The Lord offered them whatever they wanted. John wanted to tarry on earth and Peter wanted to be done with the earth and go to heaven. Peter seems to have gotten tiffed with John because John one-upped Peter on the righteous desires contest with Jesus as the Judge:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And for this cause the Lord said unto Peter: If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee? <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-7.4">Doctrine and Covenants 7.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>(The savior goes on to explain how both Peter and John’s desires were great.<sup>2</sup>)</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;side note: the Lord doesn’t compare Peter against John. He just says “John wanted to do more than what <em>he</em> has previously done.” “I say unto thee, Peter, this was a good desire; but my beloved has desired that he might do more, or a greater work yet among men than what he has before done. Yea, he has undertaken a greater work; therefore I will make him as flaming fire and a ministering angel; he shall minister for those who shall be heirs of salvation who dwell on the earth.” <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-7.5-6">Doctrine and Covenants 7.5–6</a></p></li></div><p>Back to Sariah - here are three ways we tend to worry:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>we can worry about things promised to us. We’re just rarely promised a timeline. Trust. Wait. And see.</li>
<li>Where we aren’t promised anything, we have nothing to think of or worry about.</li>
<li>We may individually be promised different things. The path of everyone is unique.</li>
</ol>
<p>But we’re all promised eternal life if we follow the Lord (eternal happiness):</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Verily I say unto you, ye shall both have according to your desires, for ye both joy in that which ye have desired. <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-7.8">Doctrine and Covenants 7.8</a></p>
</blockquote>




<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>faith</category>
  <category>covenant</category>
  <category>individual covenant</category>
  <category>promised blessings</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-5-trusting-a-promise.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 22:59:28 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Heaven</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/heaven.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m not sure what I would do if I didn’t have a concept of Heaven in my mind. It yields so very many benefits for me:</p>
<ul>
<li>Gives me hope for when family members pass</li>
<li>Reminds me why life matters: I can only take with me my relationships.</li>
<li>Heaven is about people, not money. Reminds me what matters <em>in</em> life and what will bring me happiness.</li>
<li>Gives me purpose as I raise my family.</li>
</ul>
<p>I have a sense that heaven is more like a peaceful home than a luxurious resort. Physical amenities don’t yield joy. True pleasure and enduring happiness in life come from inner peace.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-heavenly-home.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">My heavenly home would probably be more spruced up, but this is pretty peaceful.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As a concept alone, it guides you to make better decisions by living long term: death is only a door to the beyond. Even if I assume that heaven is a farce, still believing in it yields so much good for one’s life. But thankfully it’s not just some notion. It’s a real place. I’m grateful the Lord created the heavens.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Believe in God; believe that he is, and that he created all things, both in heaven and in earth; believe that he has all wisdom, and all power, both in heaven and in earth; believe that man doth not comprehend all the things which the Lord can comprehend. <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-4.9">Mosiah 4.9</a></p>
</blockquote>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/heaven.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 22:48:24 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Church Culture of Missionary work</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/sacrament-talk-on-missionary-work.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A friend gave a talk in church about missionary work, which is the Lord’s invitation to share His gospel and good news with the world. Having been a missionary for two years, it’s much less about “effective sales” strategies and much more about trying to live like a good person and invite others to enjoy the benefits of following Christ.</p>
<p>I bring up the point about sales because a lot of people outside of the church can see LDS missionaries as salespeople. To one degree, they are: they’re trying to change people’s belief system. Adopt Christianity. <sup>1</sup></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;From the ultra cynical: “they just want more tithing!” But, like, if you think about it this argument doesn’t work in so many ways. Mainly that the missionaries are paying to be there (don’t get any tithing) and most of tithing goes to maintaining the church (buildings, books, temples, missions, etc).</p></li></div><p>Yea, that’s certainly a reasonable way to look at it from one angle. But the reality is more like “I have something that’s great and I want other people to benefit from it the same way I benefit from it”. Or better said: there’s so much…misinformation about my church and Christianity in general, how do I have a productive conversation with you about it without knowing where you are? I’d love to talk to you about it, but are you deeply inwardly vehemently against it for some obtuse reason I’m not aware of? That’s what provoked some fear in sharing His good news.</p>
<p>But these fears aren’t warranted. Because that isn’t the right focus from my end. The best focus for “missionary work” is: if I have something that’s great in my life, I should share it like anything else great in my life.</p>
<p>Did I see a good movie over the weekend? Great, share it. Did i hear a great talk on Sunday at church? Great, share it. Did I have a good hike? Awesome, share it. Did I have a funny experience while teaching some kids on Sunday? Yea, dope. Share it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-orange-juice-rainforest.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Mind if I drink this? Oh, you’d like some? I didn’t want to offend you by offering but sure I’d love to share - Elder Uchtdorf analogy paraphrased</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<p>Things I liked from my friends talk:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Over the past several months, (my wife) and I have implemented a new fad into our lives in an attempt to improve our well-being, which is the practice of cold plunging. Some of you may have heard of this trend as many gurus talk about it on social media because of its benefits, such as reducing stress and mood enhancement. Cold plunging is submerging your body in very cold water (typically around 50 degrees) for a period of 3 to 6 minutes. Sounds absolutely terrible, right? Well, it is terrible! No matter how many times we do it, it is still very hard and very uncomfortable. Nonetheless, we continue to do it, almost every day, because of the way it makes us feel afterwards. Immediately after getting out of the water I feel alert, energized and confident I can tackle the tasks of the day. Sitting in that cold water is always uncomfortable, but the discomfort is always worth it. <strong>By having felt what’s on the other side, I can get comfortable with the uncomfortable.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This cold plunge analogy is interesting: because it’s always hard. Always intimidating. I think that’s true in my personal experience. But for me it’s more like… the opposite of hyperextending my knee.</p>
<p>When I was in high school I got a knee injury. I hyperextended it. The first time was incredibly painful. I was out a few days. But then I came back and was fine-ish. Then a few weeks later I did it again. Then a few days later: again. By the end of the season, I was hyperextending it every other day. It was bad news. A few weeks after the season ended I was playing in a bball tournament and again big hyperextending.</p>
<p>I stopped playing sports that summer and let myself heal up. Haven’t had problems since.</p>
<p>Same with sharing the gospel, but the opposite. At first it’s really intimidating. You do it once and you realize it’s not that bad. Then the more you do it the more it becomes part of your day.</p>
<p>Kinda like writing in this blog. At first I’m trying to find my voice. Now I don’t care and just want to write. I hope it’s beneficial for you.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>On the other hand, some may be thinking none of those sound any easier and maybe you sometimes feel that you aren’t contributing because missionary work is generally intimidating and uncomfortable to you. That is OKAY. <strong>All efforts, no matter how small, are important and impactful.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This reminded me of <a href="../concepts/president-russel-m-nelson.html">President Russel M. Nelson</a>’s invitation:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Anytime you do anything that helps anyone—on either side of the veil﻿—take a step toward making covenants with God and receiving their essential baptismal and temple ordinances, you are helping to gather Israel. It is as simple as that. <a href="../scriptures/hope-of-israel">Hope of Israel</a></p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>As a missionary in (Some Area) I had one mission president for my first year and another for my second year. Both presidents elevated the success of the mission with different approaches and leadership styles. In my first year under my first mission president, the mission accomplished a big goal of doubling the number of baptisms from the previous year. During this time our mission president wasn’t fond of us spending too much time with members and our success came from focusing on other areas of the work. By contrast, my second mission president changed the culture and encouraged us to spend as much time with the members as we could, even if we did not have someone to teach with the members. He taught us to focus on the number of lessons with a member participating as the most important key indicator. As a result, the mission’s baptisms started to skyrocket and the number more than doubled again. I know that our success can be attributed to us striving to have as many members as possible participating in our lessons and our emphasis on members and missionaries working together.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If your note a member of the church you may balk at “baptism skyrocketing”. It kinda gives a cultish vibe if that’s how you see it - our goal is to baptize everyone!! I get it. Not great language from the outsider’s perspective <em>if</em> that’s how you see it.</p>
<p>Having been a member of the church my whole life, I’ve heard this rhetoric a lot - get baptisms. But I think this is more of a sociological misrepresentation of a deeply inward desire to share what’s good in your life with others.</p>
<p>Do I want to baptize the world? Umm…do I want everyone to have world peace? Yea.</p>
<p>Will baptizing someone give them peace? No.&nbsp;Well, not <em>just</em> dunking yourself in a hot-tub sized mini pool.</p>
<p>Will someone who has a sincere desire to follow Christ the rest of their life benefit from being baptized because it gives them a chance to publicly commit to following Christ and thus be supported by a community of like-minded people also trying to self-improve constantly? Yea. Baptism would be great here.</p>
<p>Do I want to baptize everyone? No.&nbsp;I <em>would</em> love it if everyone desired to follow Jesus a little more in their life. Learn a little more about him. So, yea I want everyone to be baptized.</p>
<p>This is the spirit which my friend is describing.</p>
<p>So doubling baptisms is this notion of a very fascinating cultural experience: we have as a church more success in helping other people discover the joy of following Christ by <em>how</em> we package “the message”. Yea, it’s sales at some level. What’s a better strategy? Cold calling or referrals? Always referrals. There’s trust there. The product doesn’t seem as strange. Likewise, it takes a lot to change a set of religious beliefs. Having seen someone you know and enjoy associating with benefit from the religion helps make it more palatable at first to begin discussions.</p>
<p>Lastly, this strategy is fascinating: focus on teaching people who already believe in God about <em>why</em> they believe in God, or more about His story. These refreshers help enliven the mind, no different than perhaps me going back to some Stat 121 material and just really appreciating its elegance (even though I do more advanced math in my day to day). Teach people the basics and they’ll remember what they love about it.</p>
<hr>
<p>End/rant.</p>




<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>opinion</category>
  <category>lds culture</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/sacrament-talk-on-missionary-work.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 21:05:30 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Healing</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/healing.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A scraped knee. A broken leg. A cancerous tumor. A fractured mind. Wounded soul. Torn relationship.</p>
<p>Healing is possible. Thanks be to God for the gift of healing.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-healing-abstract.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Healing</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/healing.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2024 23:59:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 4 - Why not?</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-4-why-not.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Nephi asks a faith-opening question:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>for behold he is mightier than all the earth, <strong>then why not mightier than</strong> Laban and his fifty, yea, or even than his tens of thousands? <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-4.1">1 Nephi 4.1</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>As I wrote in <a href="../christianity/unknown-god.html">An Unknown God</a>, Nephi demonstrates the ability to find a way with his questioning. Instead of asking doubtfully, he asks faithfully.</p>
<p>It reminds me of Enoch:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>31 And when Enoch had heard these words, he bowed himself to the earth, before the Lord, and spake before the Lord, saying: <strong>Why is it that I have found favor in thy sight</strong>, and am but a lad, and all the people hate me; for I am slow of speech; wherefore am I thy servant? 32 And the Lord said unto Enoch: <strong>Go forth and do</strong> as I have commanded thee, and no man shall pierce thee. <a href="../scriptures/moses-6.31-32">Moses 6.31–32</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Lord didn’t tell him why he was chosen. He just said “go forth”.</p>
<p>The Lord’s thoughts are above our thoughts. Too often we put limiting beliefs on ourselves - I’m not good enough, why me? Or, why would God want to help me?</p>
<p>Why not instead ask, “why <em>wouldn’t</em> Heavenly Father want to help me? He loves me and has promised he <em>would</em> help me.”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-why-wouldn't-an-angel.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Angels want to help</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I love this quote by Jared after just going through something really hard:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass that Jared spake again unto his brother, saying: Go and inquire of the Lord whether he will drive us out of the land, and if he will drive us out of the land, cry unto him whither we shall go. <strong>And who knoweth but the Lord will carry us forth into a land which is choice above all the earth?</strong> And if it so be, let us be faithful unto the Lord, that we may receive it for our inheritance. <a href="../scriptures/ether-1.38">Ether 1.38</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just lost your job? Who knoweth but the Lord will provide a better one? Just lost your house? Who knoweth but the Lord will give you a promised land? (They had lost their jobs and house and were wandering at this point.) I love the optimism here.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-4-why-not.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2024 23:23:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 3 - Dreamed a Dream</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-3-dreamed-a-dream.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A great quote leading up to MLK Jr day:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Behold I have dreamed a dream <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-3.2">1 Nephi 3.2</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Lehi dreamed many dreams. It got him in trouble with his boys, as Laman and Lemuel “did murmur in many things against their father, <strong>because he was a visionary man</strong>” (<a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-2.11">1 Nephi 2.11</a>).</p>
<p>Lehi’s wife, Sariah, also murmured against him, “she also had complained against my father, <strong>telling him that he was a visionary man;</strong> saying: Behold thou hast led us forth from the land of our inheritance, and my sons are no more, and we perish in the wilderness.” (<a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.2">1 Nephi 5.2</a>)</p>
<p>Lehi’s response to this is great:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I <strong>know that I am a visionary man</strong>; for if I had not seen the things of God in a vision I should not have known the goodness of God, but had tarried at Jerusalem, and had perished with my brethren. But behold, I have obtained a land of promise, in the which things I do rejoice; yea, and I know that the Lord will deliver my sons out of the hands of Laban, and bring them down again unto us in the wilderness. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.4-5">1 Nephi 5.4–5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This response teaches me a few things:</p>
<ul>
<li>when people struggle, they can complain against a good thing and make it a bad thing. “Why do you always have to be such a goodie two shoes?”</li>
<li>The response is “if I weren’t such a goodie two shoes I’d be miserable”. Helps remind people of the value of their own biases.</li>
</ul>
<p>Complaining is a natural part of life. Just be careful what you complain about.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-3-dreamed-a-dream.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 22:52:51 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>You can plan your life in 5 minutes</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/you-can-plan-your-life-in-5-minutes.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It doesn’t take 30 years to plan a good life. It’s actually quite simple and if you sit down for 5 minutes you can figure out the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>do you like where you’re at? Heading? No? Where do you want to go? Why? What do you need to change to get there?</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it.</p>
<p>No fancy grand vision. No elaborate planning. Just maybe 15 minutes to plan ahead.</p>
<p>The speed of planning is 0.01% of the effort required to execute. “We’re going to the moon by the end of the decade”. Plan. Done. Execution is hard.</p>
<p>Ideas are fleeting. Plans are changeable. Plans and ideas aren’t the IP of your company. It’s the people and the execution. Thats the hard part.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-sunrise-on-hike.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">We’ve been to the moon. Now let’s go to the sun.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>purpose of life</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/you-can-plan-your-life-in-5-minutes.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 22:44:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for My Childhood</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/my-childhood.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I won the childhood lottery. I had good parents, good siblings, good friends, and luckily made a few good choices.</p>
<p>That’s all it takes: a few good choices. I credit my parents for giving me a good home to grow up in, a good religion to teach me good principles, and a lot of support.</p>
<p>As I grow older, time reveals itself. The dust under the childhood cushion is now identified. As I raise my own children I wonder: how did they do it?</p>
<p>Which perhaps is what my children will ask me someday.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-childhood-leaves.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Childhood is playing</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’m grateful I played a lot.</p>
<p>I’m grateful for parents who take up the challenge to raise the next generation. I’m grateful for siblings to live, love, and learn from. For friends who make the journey an adventure, and for a family that I can always come back to.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/my-childhood.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 20:36:34 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
