<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/all.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/all.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 15:10:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Write a thousand songs</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/write-a-thousand-songs.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I listened to an interview with Imagine Dragons. The lead singer talked about how he writes several songs per day.</p>
<p>No wonder he’s so successful. Repetitions breeds opportunity.</p>
<p>This has two affects on the brain. 1) lowers the pressure of individual songs. Don’t need to knock it of the park. 2) you get better at writing that much faster.</p>
<p>I heard once about a photography that let one half of the students only take 5 photos in a semester. The other half had to take 100. Which group had the better photos?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>You miss 100% of the shots you don’t take. <del>Wayne Gretzky</del> Michael Scott</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-hockey-shots-surreal-impressionist-water.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">More shots is more opportunities for a goal. Worry about good shots later.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>creativity</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/write-a-thousand-songs.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 15:10:01 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>When Leaders Lose their People</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/losing-to-yesmen.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In a scene in <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>, Paul notices that his warrior turns into his worshipper. He laments the loss, wondering if his non-religious warrior will be lost too.</p>
<p>Being a worshipped means you’re worshipped. Unchallenged. Can do no wrong. As such, you’re left with the intellect of one.</p>
<p>As a leader, you need to avoid worshippers. People who fail to challenge you out of fear or an abundance of praise. This all has to do in the decisions you make as a leader. The culture you decide to build. Is every voice heard, or does one voice rule them all?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-king-one-voice-to-rule.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">One voice to rule them all</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/losing-to-yesmen.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 14:31:39 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Multiverse of Careers</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-multiverse-of-careers.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Spoken about in <a href="../tech/dreaming-software.html">The Dream State of Software</a>, Paul of <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a> has a moment where he’s both past and present in his mind. He doesn’t know even whether he’s had his kid or not.</p>
<p>In a podcast I listened to lately on happiness, one suggestion was to write out all your goals and cross them off from day one. Pretend like it doesn’t even matter if you accomplish them. This helps free you.</p>
<p>Careers are like both of these things. We want everything. We can pretend like we have it. We can come to terms with it. And we can say “doesn’t matter if I don’t get that, because I’ve got a life outside my career.”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-multiverse-of-choice.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Which path you choose isn’t as important as who you choose as companions</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Consider your career from your deathbed (<a href="../posts/my-tombstone.html">My Tombstone</a>). What path did you take that mattered? What were all the alternate realities and multiverses you could have had.</p>
<p>Put them all together. In one multiverse you’ve been fired. In another you end up getting insanely wealthy. In another you start your own company. In another you become an online blogger.</p>
<p>All of them can’t be true when you do this exercise extensively enough. And choosing which one probably doesn’t matter as much (right vs wrong path thinking). If you’ve ever left a job you realize that nothing really comes over with you. Most relationships at work are short lived and contextual, like your relationships in high school. And that’s life.</p>
<p>Happiness is perhaps being okay with not having everything you desire, except for the few things that are truly attainable: peace with God, self, and cherished relationships.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <category>deathbed meditation</category>
  <category>career</category>
  <category>decisions</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-multiverse-of-careers.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 13:00:31 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>When a Person Changes their Perspective on Christ</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/a-change-in-witness.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The Book of Mormon had 12 witnesses of its divinity - the three spiritual testimonies by the Three Witnesses, the Eight Witnesses with a physical witness, and Joseph Smith, the one who translated it as prophet, seer, and revelator. Powerfully, all Three Witnesses left the church years later (1937/38) nearly 8-9 years after writing their testimony (1829), but never left their testimonies:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Despite differences with Joseph Smith that led each of the Three Witnesses to part ways individually with the Church (Cowdery and Harris later returned), they continued to affirm their testimony as witnesses throughout their lives. <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/history/topics/witnesses-of-the-book-of-mormon?lang=eng&amp;id=html">Witnesses of the Book of Mormon</a></p>
</blockquote>
<section id="when-a-loved-one-leaves-their-testimony" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>When a loved one leaves their testimony</h1>
<p>Let’s consider the world where these three denied their testimonies. (It’s easy to see that they “never doubted their own witness, therefore it must be true”.) But I think this is a sandy foundation because a thing should be true regardless of what three individuals say about it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-three-witnesses-one-missing.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">What if one had forsaken their testimony - would you still believe he saw it?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Those who believe in Christ hold strong beliefs in Him, and it must be a belief because they cannot see Him. They rely on the faith built on personal witness and also built by the testimony of others. But what do you do when a loved one abandons their testimony, or becomes an <a href="../book-review/unbelievable.html">unbeliever</a>? Do you doubt everything you learned from them? Perhaps.</p>
<p>Who do you trust - the “them” now that un-believes, or the “them” <em>then</em> that once believed?</p>
<p>Consider a hard-and-fast alternative: what if someone began doubting the existence of gravity? What if they were once your physics professor? Easy: you just go to the apple tree and demonstrate the principle by dropping an apple. “No, that’s magnetism”, the professor now claims.</p>
<p>You’re kind of stuck: well, if you think it’s magnetism, there’s not much I can do - this concept is called gravity. Similarly, people leave God’s path and believe the Hand of God that acts in their live is now, and always has been, just coincidence, luck, etc. what else could it be?</p>
<p>But what is coincidence? Luck? (I ponder these things often as a statistician. For another time…)</p>
</section>
<section id="putting-a-name-on-a-concept" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Putting a name on a Concept</h1>
<p>There’s precedence for this - when Ammon appeared to the Lamanites, they thought he acted by the Great Spirit. Instead of telling them they were wrong, he instead clarified, “that great spirit <em>is</em> God”.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>26 And then Ammon said: Believest thou that there is a Great Spirit? 27 And he said, Yea. 28 And Ammon said: This is God. And Ammon said unto him again: Believest thou that this Great Spirit, who is God, created all things which are in heaven and in the earth?<br>
<a href="../scriptures/alma-18.26-28">Alma 18.26–28</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Likewise, when unbelievers doubt the Hand of God, or re-cast their old ways according to a <em>new</em> belief framework, perhaps they’re just labeling a concept in a different way. (It’s also really hard to know what someone once considered “God” vs not in their life, so take this point with a grain of salt.)</p>
<p>After all, when people leave God some claim they were under <a href="https://robjhyndman.com/unbelievable/ch4.html">confirmation bias</a>, the concept that you favor the evidence that supports your belief. Hyndman argues confirmation bias can go both ways, for believers and unbelievers, but <em>does</em> claim that evidence favors the skeptics because there should be evidence. I’d argue he relies solely on <em>physical</em> evidence. There is <em>spiritual</em> evidence to be considered. <em>Spiritual</em> evidence is what we believe in. It’s what the Three Witnesses relied on. It’s unprovable to anyone else, and only receivable by the Holy Ghost. If God exists, let Him reveal himself. Let Him prevail:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>But whom say ye that I am? 16 And Simon Peter answered and said, Thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God. 17 And Jesus answered and said unto him, Blessed art thou, Simon Bar-jona: for <strong>flesh and blood hath not revealed it unto thee, but my Father which is in heaven.</strong><br>
<a href="../scriptures/matthew-16.15-17">Matthew 16.15–17</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The most powerful thing about being a Christian is that <em>it cannot be proven</em> Christ <em>didn’t</em> exist or walk the earth. Even if you falsify the entire bible, erase history, or discover that “Mary” was an invented concept by some creed or counsel bound to oppress us - there’s still a question: did the Man exist? We can debate it. Pharisees debated if He was That Messiah. Nobody now can know, except God reveals it to them.</p>
<p>Why? Because to claim God doesn’t exist, or the plates weren’t real, you’d also have to have evidence. Counter-evidence <em>isn’t</em> evidence. Lack of evidence likewise. Don’t we continually find new fossils? New animals in the wild? Lack of evidence doesn’t mean they don’t exist.<sup>1</sup></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;The other side may say (as Hyndman) does), I might as well believe in the Tooth Fairy, or Santa, because I don’t have evidence they don’t exist. Fair. Then belief is a choice, and must follow the principle of “by their fruits ye shall know them”. Did Baal call down Fire? No, only Elijah’s God. “Was that story of the Bible invented?” Perhaps. If so, explain why living Christ’s gospel brings me joy? “Because they’re good principles”, well, what is good, if not God? “Well then why not Zeus, or Baal to be your God?”, because I believe in the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob - not the God of Baal. I believe the scriptures because they teach good things. “What about the misogyny, racism, war and killing in the Bible etc etc etc”, well, perhaps some was commanded by God for reasons and context we don’t have. Perhaps some of the Bible isn’t truely written. “If some isn’t true it’s all not true because parts of it say it’s all true”. Well, what’s true is true, what’s not isn’t. “Who’s to say what God inspired?” Well, who’s to say what’s not inspired? Only God. “We’re not getting anywhere”. Ahh, but we are. Because I believe in God, and after believing Him I exercised faith in His son to pray on His name and open myself to trying to follow His ways. I’m far from perfect, but once I did this, I received spiritual knowledge, and having seen more of the Hand of God in my life, I can say there are miracles of events I can’t explain by chance or delusion alone. Miracles only a loving God could produce. This is my knowledge, which follows faith. <a href="../scriptures/alma-32.34-36">Alma 32.34–36</a> And we also have the Book of Mormon, which is a powerful second witness of Christ that brought reality to the truth in the Bible, and continually helps me feel the fruits of the Spirit, which is the Holy Ghost telling me it’s true.</p></li><li id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;my whole life until 21 I had no idea Joseph Smith had so many (up to 42) wives. “Some say he was a womanizer, pimp, etc”. Perhaps. But perhaps he was a prophet commanded to do so. Were we there? God at one point commanded Abraham to raise seed and have many wives. “Maybe Abraham was a philanderer too.” Okay, but does that definition of chastity and virtue not depend on the very construction of marriage as ordained by God who married Adam and Eve as husband and wife? If it’s from God, it’s His law, and He chose the rules. “But Joseph altered the rules and made stuff up so he could get with women and teenagers.” Perhaps. That assumes we know him, he told us that, and he believed it to be true. So we’ll leave it as an opinion. In my opinion he followed a commandment from an Angel, despite me not understanding it entirely or being comfortable with the idea. Let the man speak for himself.</p></li></div><p>To prove the Abrahamic God doesn’t exist people just say “well I found all this stuff about the bible, about church leaders, etc” was wrong or misconstrued. So? First, we have to make sure the “new stuff” learned is actually true (could be a lie), but if it is true (that something you once believed is a lie or misunderstanding) we must find out how this fits into Christ’s bigger picture.<sup>2</sup></p>
<p>You can’t claim that Joseph Smith <em>didn’t</em> see God and that the <em>Three Witnesses</em> <em>didn’t</em> see the plates at some point. Because you weren’t there in 1829. Even if they <em>had</em> later denied, from reading <a href="../book-review/killers-of-the-flower-moon.html">Killers of the Flower Moon: the Osage Murders and the Birth of the FBI</a>, it’s quite clear how people can be manipulated in the courts of law, influenced by money, influenced by their own delusions, etc. Since delusions go both ways, relying on people at all isn’t how we learn the existence of a Divine. Peter learned of Christ’s divinity the way we all must (quote above). Show me the evidence, says the scientist in me: the <em>spiritual</em> evidence. # Flip Floppers on Both Sides</p>
<p>Floppers flip both ways. The quote above said another way: who’s witness do you trust - the <em>you</em> of today, the <em>you</em> of yesterday, or the <em>you</em> of tomorrow? We can all come and go with our testimonies. This is life. We must have an unalterable way to learn truth, one independent of our path.</p>
<p>We’ve got the Paul’s of the world who were once Christian persecutors who flip to believers, and we’ve got those who claimed Joseph Smith was a fallen prophet after being in vision with him.</p>
<p>We’re all more like Laman and Lemuel than we realize. We see things that make us believe, we come to God, and then we forget and wonder if they never happened.</p>
<p>We’re all flip floppers. Let us not seek truth alone from others, or even rely solely on the Prophet. Our testimonies must be on Christ, and learning truth by the Holy Ghost, who will then guide us to understand the words of prophets and imperfect leaders. It’s good science.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In coming days, it will not be possible to survive spiritually without the guiding, directing, comforting, and constant influence of the Holy Ghost.<br>
<a href="../scriptures/russell-m-nelson-revelation-for-the-church-revelation-for-our-lives">“Revelation for the Church, Revelation for Our Lives”, Russell M. Nelson</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’m glad the Three Witnesses never denied their testimonies, but I’m glad there’s a way to know the Book of Mormon is true without them. After all, those dudes didn’t answer my prayer about the book’s truth. Heavenly Father did.</p>


</section>


<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/a-change-in-witness.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 09:11:17 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Zoom</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/zoom.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I first heard about zoom many years ago on a random podcast. Had no idea what it was or why it was useful. Now it’s enabled me to work remotely, chat with friends across the nation, and even attend church during lockdowns.</p>
<p>Behind this is a person with an idea that changed the world. Surely they weren’t the first video service, but they build off the earlier, crappier products.</p>
<p>I’m grateful for V1’s like Skype that paved the way for Zoom, which learned a ton, probably poached some talent, and gave me something with using.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-caravaggio-zoom.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Beethoven Zooming with friends, ala Caravaggio</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/zoom.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Your Mood is Contagious</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/your-mood-is-contagious.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-mood-sharing.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Moods flow. Keep the negative waves at bay</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There’s no question that moods are contagious. I once asked someone at the beach to leash their dog, and they slightly rebuked me, “this is a dog friendly beach.” <em>Well, so it is,</em> I thought, grumpily. I complained to a family member about this grumpy dog owner.</p>
<p>Moods escalate. And negative moods are even more pervasive and contagious than positive ones. They say a disgruntled customer tells more friends and family than happy ones. Why is this?</p>
<p>In the “Black Cat” (<a href="../book-review/the-best-of-edgar-allen-poe.html">The Best of Edgar Allen Poe</a>), Poe describes a gruesome tale man who wanted to do evil just for the sake of it. That it’s in his nature. Not because you want to do the thing, but because you want to do a forbidden thing. The same goes the other way, for sure. But I think we trend slightly pessimistic because being an optimist is more beneficial, more rewarding and therefore more difficult.</p>
<p>A leader once told me when I was managing a team, “They’ll pick up on <em>everything</em> you do or say.” Oddly, I was picking up on what he was saying.</p>
<p>So when you lead, lead carefully. Whether in home or work, lead with kindness, compassion, and restraint. Speak three kind words before a negative. Ask to understand before assuming. Lead as a servant. It takes all the effort to overcome negative vibes, and who better equipped than the leader to do it?</p>
<p>Don’t be Moriarty:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ncbEucjsNFU?si=rYhBqqavn4Nergap" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>“Why can’t you be more hopeful for a change?”</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <category>parenting</category>
  <category>emotional resilience</category>
  <category>grit</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/your-mood-is-contagious.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Writing Ethos</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/lists/writing-ethos.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>List of reasons why I write this blog and principles I aspire to. They evolve over time, and I like to keep track.</p>
<p>2023-12-31</p>
<ul>
<li>Write every day (Seth Godin style). Many posts will be bad. But higher repetitions means better writing.</li>
<li>Learn by writing. Synthesis only happens when sharing.</li>
<li>Write first, edit later.</li>
<li>Use writing to actively digest world news. Doomscrolling is futile and anxiety inducing. Writing and synthesizing helps me comparmentalize the world and where I fit into it.</li>
<li>Develop an opinion. Strong opinions, weakly held. A ship is better heading in any direction than none at all. An opinion is a direction.</li>
<li>Every post is a story. If it’s not a story, it’s not worth reading.</li>
<li>I am me. I write what’s on my mind. I hope it’s interesting to different people in different ways.</li>
<li>Write each post for one real person in my life, based on one real discussion.</li>
<li>Gratitude is healing, produces optimism, and reveals a new way. Give thanks daily. I give thanks, therefore I have.</li>
</ul>
<p>2022-12-05</p>
<ul>
<li>All blogs are wrong, but some are useful (riff on George Box’s quote that all models are wrong)</li>
</ul>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>lists</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/lists/writing-ethos.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Dream State of Software</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/dreaming-software.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-dreaming-software.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Dreaming code working is ever coders dream</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I returned from vacation yesterday and tried running my code. It didn’t work. I looked at code I had written, it had my imports correctly and all - why wasn’t it running?</p>
<p>The file it was importing didn’t exist.</p>
<p>I thought I created that. I swear I made it. My coworker remarked, “oh so you set up all the scafffolding but didn’t write the actual code?” I was in disbelief. maybe it was deleted by accident or stashed on another branch. But the <code>git log</code> shows all: the imported file never existed.</p>
<p>In <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>, Paul Atriedes has many visions and the author uses this feature to skip the book ahead three years. Paul wakes up one morning and doesn’t know what’s past or future. It’s all one in his mind.</p>
<p>So it is with software. It gets created in the mind near instantly. Coding is a burden, the journey of many failures and design choices to enable the simple vision of the mind.</p>
<p>Perhaps Gen AI can help us dream software faster. I look forward to when my dreams are realities, and not the rude awakening I still have coding to do.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>design</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>futurism</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/dreaming-software.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Steve Jobs (Biography)</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/steve-jobs-biography.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 








<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/steve-jobs-biography.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Share your testimony</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/share-your-testimony.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>At least a dozen people claimed to have seen the gold plates from which the Book of Mormon was translated by Joseph Smith.</p>
<p>There were the “Three Witnesses”, the “Eight Witnesses”, Emma Smith, Joseph Smith, and perhaps a few others.</p>
<p>What’s powerful to me is this testimony that the Eight shared:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And we give our names unto the world, to witness unto the world that which we have seen. And we lie not, God bearing witness of it. <a href="../scriptures/testimony-of-eight-witnesses">Testimony of Eight Witnesses</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I admire any who live with such conviction. It calls to mind the John Hancock’s of the world.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Be it known unto all nations, kindreds, tongues, and people, unto whom this work shall come: <a href="../scriptures/testimony-of-eight-witnesses">Testimony of Eight Witnesses</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>We’re invited to “stand as witnesses of God at all times and in all things, and in all places that ye may be in,” (<a href="../scriptures/mosiah-18.9">Mosiah 18.9</a>), to share what we’ve seen.</p>
<p>May we stand boldly, which doesn’t mean confrontational, contentiously, or loudly. It just means unequivocally. Sincerely.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-three-witnesses.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Stand by what you know to be true. Stand together</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>testimony</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/share-your-testimony.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My Tombstone</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/my-tombstone.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>They call it a death meditation, to look back from the end of your life and reflect as if you had just died (out of body style). Here’s my tombstone:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Here lies Bryan, son of Aragon, data scientist extraordinaire who knew how to use regular expressions and properly test linear regression assumptions</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Seem like a good tombstone?</p>
<p>Why do we measure our lives by something nobody cares about? Consider Steve Jobs, Isaac Newton, or whomever you idolize. What are they known for? Only a few things.</p>
<p>I read <a href="../book-review/steve-jobs-biography.html">Steve Jobs (Biography)</a> a while back. And I also read <a href="../book-review/leonardo-da-vinci.html">Leonardo da Vinci</a>. First was 25 hours, second was 17 hours. And guess what - that’s less than two days combined. Two “impressive” lives summed up in a few days.</p>
<p>My grandma’s obituary was brief. Yet her life was filled with millions of unwritten sentences - many written on my life. The in between moments. The laying around moments. The relationship moments. (Maybe it’s called a relation-“ship” because it sails the waters of life continuously, despite the infrequent dock postings.)</p>
<p>Nobody’s going to remember me, except those who call me dad, husband, brother, son, and friend. And I’m okay with that. I was never that good at data science anyway 😉.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-data-scientist-tombstone-on-beach.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">If I’m going out as a data scientist, at least my resting spot will be cool</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>mortality</category>
  <category>work</category>
  <category>work life balance</category>
  <category>perspective</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <category>priorities</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/my-tombstone.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Love Thy Neighbor, But Have Friends</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/love-thy-neighbor-but-have-friends.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Christ invited us to love our neighbors:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself: I am the Lord. <a href="../scriptures/leviticus-19.18">Leviticus 19.18</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But He himself had his friends: his disciples. He didn’t try hanging out with the Pharisees or the Romans. He spent time at dinner with his apostles and followers.</p>
<p>He had four brothers. Did he call them to apostleship? No.&nbsp;Did he <em>not</em> love them? No, he loved them.</p>
<p>He loved the Roman as much as he loved John the Beloved: enough to die for them and prepare the way for them to rejoin him in heaven.</p>
<p>But he also spent time with those he loved. What does this teach us about love?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-lunch-with-friends-impressionist.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Go get lunch with a friend</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>love</category>
  <category>family</category>
  <category>friendship</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/love-thy-neighbor-but-have-friends.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Leonardo da Vinci</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/leonardo-da-vinci.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Read this back in 2021. Great book.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/leonardo-da-vinci.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The miracles of Christ</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/the-miracles-of-christ.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m reading the Book of Mormon this year with the Come Follow Me (by <a href="../christianity/the-church-of-jesus-christ-of-latter-day-saints.html">The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints</a>) curriculum. I hope you enjoy as I write something I learn each day.</p>
<p>I’ll tag things “scripture of the day” for any one-scripture thoughts. If it’s related to the Come Follow Me theme, l’ll add a tag.</p>
<section id="miracles-of-christ" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Miracles of Christ</h1>
<p>This scripture caught me eye:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For behold, the time cometh, and is not far distant, that with power, the Lord Omnipotent who reigneth, who was, and is from all eternity to all eternity, shall come down from heaven among the children of men, and shall dwell in a tabernacle of clay, and shall go forth amongst men, <strong>working mighty miracles, such as healing the sick, raising the dead, causing the lame to walk, the blind to receive their sight, and the deaf to hear, and curing all manner of diseases.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-3.5">Mosiah 3.5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-christ-healing-clay.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Christ healing all who come unto him</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I have seen miracles in my life. I’ve also seen collateral-miracles, which is the miracle that happens when you’re expecting one thing but another thing happens instead.</p>
<p>I’ve seen someone healed from a Priesthood blessing. I’ve seen someone healed from depression. I’ve seen someone healed from doubt and disbelief. I’ve felt the power of the Holy Ghost in my life.</p>
<p>I’ve also seen people not healed, left to the struggles we all face, and yet miracles abound.</p>
<p>So what is a miracle? Is it an outcome? No.&nbsp;It’s the process of seeing how an event can be changed by God for the benefit of an individual. Occasionally, there are supernatural changes in the natural course of things.</p>
<p>If any of these things sounds fanciful to those not of my Church, it’s actually a lot more simple and plain than it sounds. Because “the Lord was not in the wind: and after the wind an earthquake; but the Lord was not in the earthquake: And after the earthquake a fire; but the Lord was not in the fire: and after the fire a <strong>still small voice</strong>.” (<a href="../scriptures/1-kings-19.11-12">1 Kings 19.11–12</a>) For me, seeing a miracle of Christ is perceiving the hand by how he operates.</p>
<p>Some have a hard time reading the Old Testament because how can a God who brought fire from heaven, parted the seas, gave manna from heaven also be a God who doesn’t do those things today?</p>
<p>I’d argue the miracles of Christ have risen to the point where he works according to our knowledge and insight. I believe in a Christ who is the source of all truth, and who teaches truth (even scientific) to everyone, regardless of their belief system. <a href="../scriptures/matthew-5.45">Matthew 5.45</a></p>
<p>And so, the miracles of God today are happening within science. Within tech. He doesn’t have to heal us by God’s power if he gave us medicine to do the same.</p>
<p>He also doesn’t show his miracles the same way. The people of the Old Testament were simple. They needed signs. But signs aren’t faith, and I believe these days before His second coming are days of greater faith. Days where we’ll have fewer signs.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Therefore, <strong>blessed are they who humble themselves without being compelled to be humble</strong>; or rather, in other words, blessed is he that believeth in the word of God, and is baptized without stubbornness of heart, yea, without being brought to know the word, or even compelled to know, before they will believe. Yea, there are many who do say: If thou wilt show unto us a sign from heaven, then we shall know of a surety; then we shall believe. 18 Now I ask, is this faith? Behold, I say unto you, Nay; for if a man knoweth a thing he hath no cause to believe, for he knoweth it. <a href="../scriptures/alma-32.16-18">Alma 32.16–18</a></p>
</blockquote>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>scripture of the day</category>
  <category>miracles</category>
  <category>faith</category>
  <category>signs</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/the-miracles-of-christ.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Psychology of New Software Releases and its Parallels with Fashion</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/why-we-want-new-software.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>What is it about a new release that gets people excited? Would you buy software that never changes? How about a hammer?</p>
<p>Why are we okay with buying a hammer, but not stagnant software? Our culture is addicted to new widgets. A/B testing.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-ship-fashion-software.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Shipping software like fashion, every season</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Software releases are free, but development is not. Therefore, research and development is constant, whereas the Hammer company hasn’t needed to update its product in a couple…millennia. That’s why they call it software. It’s not hard to make.</p>
<p>Is there a way to sell software like you sell a hammer?</p>
<p>No.&nbsp;Because per <a href="../book-review/innovators-dilemma.html">Innovator’s Dilemma</a>, those who can out-do you will. And software is easy to alter and improve. I’m not convinced all “updates” done in the software industry are actually improvements, but people like change. Ever see a fashion line repeat itself?</p>
<p>Software is like fashion.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>business strategy</category>
  <category>saas</category>
  <category>sales</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/why-we-want-new-software.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/the-church-of-jesus-christ-of-latter-day-saints.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’ve been a member of this church, also known as the Mormon church, my whole life. I’ve studied it, learned its history, and have come to believe that it provides a marvelous sense of purpose and guidance. I believe it teaches the most truth about Jesus Christ and His plan of happiness for us, and I believe it’s people (including my own) have a lot to learn from those teachings.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/the-church-of-jesus-christ-of-latter-day-saints.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Innovator’s Dilemma</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/innovators-dilemma.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 








<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/innovators-dilemma.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Good Books</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/good-books.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m grateful for good books. They take time. They take effort. They’re art (<a href="../gratitude/grateful-for-artists.html">I’m grateful for artists</a>). I’m finishing <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a> right now and I can’t imagine how long and how arduous the task must have been. They say it took Herbert six years, but many years in addition thinking about it. It’s powerfully creative, and has set the tone for science fiction for the next 60 years.</p>
<p>I’m grateful people can be so powerfully curious, intelligent, motivated, and capable to create such a book. Humans can do incredible things.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-open-book-on-table.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Books are only enjoyed if read</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/good-books.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>“Socrates A Life Worth Living” by Devra Lehman</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/socrates-a-life-worth-living.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-socrates.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Socrates, a Life Worth Living</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Notes: - socrates had a voice he felt was from Gods. Daimonion - Memorization. Lots of it. - Humanism - treated sacrifices to the gods as transactional. This meant they relied on themselves rather than gods to teach them. - Odd relationships (pedophelia) - function: intended purpose. Virtue: quality of function.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/socrates-a-life-worth-living.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m grateful for rest</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/rest.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m grateful for rest. Time away. I’m grateful that by taking time away, my brain resets. Now I’m more energized to tackle the day.</p>
<p>Why is rest necessary? I don’t know. But it is. Bodies need sleep. Minds need breaks.</p>
<p>I find that the mind is easier to overrule than a tired body. Why? Why can we push our brains more than is healthy for them? It’s hard to answer, but only rest tells us where our mind can be.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-resting-hammock-surreal.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Resting in an abstract and surrealistic way</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>observations</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/rest.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
