<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/all.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/all.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 22:55:24 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Becoming an expert is kind of a fallacy</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/becoming-an-expert.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Just watched this clip:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/I2ZK3ngNvvI?si=p4BCDVMWKBoc4KJQ" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Important discussion points: as a novice you’re worried about where to go or picking the wrong thing.</p>
<p>I remember not taking an opportunity to learn C++ because “that’s not what I want to do”. In another occasion I wanted to learn PySpark over SQL because Python…</p>
<p>While I don’t regret that choice per se, because I chose something else I was interested in, I’ve largely come to realize that I don’t care what programming language I’m using. I care about getting the job done.</p>
<p>Also, I’m probably over the 10,000 hours of <em>something</em>, I just don’t know what. Am I an ML expert? Data expert? SQL? Python? R?</p>
<p>Is it the application of the skill that makes you an expert? I’m not sure. Because I think novices can do some incredible things if they hone in.</p>
<p>If you read one book on a topic, you’re by no means an “expert”, but you probably know more about that topic than 99% of the nation. I learned this when I spent 6 months diving into the home security industry for my first job. Pretty sure I knew more about that than anyone I spoke to. Was I an expert? I really only had maybe 300 hours. Maybe I was inexperienced. Sure.</p>
<p>And who spends literally 10,000 hours on any one thing? Like 10,000 hours on XGBoost? Image classification? Deep learning? Machine learning? A/B testing? Spreadsheets? Generalist vs specialist, etc. if you’re an ML scientist at Google, you worry about very different things than an ML scientist at a startup. At a startup, you worry about your bigquery allocation and pipeline failures. At Google you worry about what your 5th skip VP is going to deprecate that month.</p>
<p>That’s just the nature of education. There are so many things in the world to know…that being an “expert” is a relative thing. But I agree that working hard and learning useful things helps you innovate faster.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-rocky-balboa-expert.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">I’d change my opinion on being an expert if I needed to beat Rocky.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Last thing, the crux is: don’t compare yourself to others. Compare yourself to yourself. That’s how you assess your progress.</p>
<p>But I’d argue: why even compare yourself to yourself? Compare your solution to the problem. Does it matter if you have 10,000 hours? No.&nbsp;What matters is if the solution fits. This is why innovations and disruptions come from unexpected places: because novices can nail solutions.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>personal development</category>
  <category>growth</category>
  <category>grit</category>
  <category>life lessons</category>
  <category>data science</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/becoming-an-expert.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 22:55:24 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My testimony: Moving across the Country</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/my-testimony-2024-01-07.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>Today is fast Sunday, a day when testimonies are shared in church. Here’s my testimony I shared today. Someone had just spoken about moving to a new place and seeing God in their lives, even if it was far away from where they had thought they needed to be. They had moved away from family.</em></p>
<p>I was reminded today of why I live where I do. Without going into personal details, as a family we decided it was time to leave the east coast and move west. As I wondered how it might be possible, I was encouraged by my wife to reach out to an old contact on a random spreadsheet I had kept seven years prior when I was first looking for jobs. The guy had since changed jobs from when he had interviewed me, but he referred me to his new company.</p>
<p>Well, this company was otherwise impossible to get noticed at, even with referrals. Turns out this guy was a lot higher than I had known. It was enough to get me the first interview. Four years later we’re still on the west coast. It’s definitely a better situation for our family in many ways.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-u-haul-moving.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Moving because when we had a desire, the Lord opened the door for us</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And in terms of family, I grew up living far away from cousins. My church congregation became my family. My parents friends became my Sunday school teachers and mentors. My friends at church became my closest confidants and kept me company in living the principles I believed in.</p>
<p>Recently, this church family helped us with meals, gifts, and emotional warmth. I don’t know what I’d do without belonging to a group of people who care for one another (I know many communities are like this, but I think it’s extra special in a Christian context where everyone wants to help and strengthen each other in kindness. We all try their best.)</p>
<p>Christ’s design that we have a church is inspired:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>There is <strong>one body, and one Spirit</strong>, even as ye are called in one hope of your calling; One Lord, one faith, one baptism, One God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all. <a href="../scriptures/ephesians-4.4-6">Ephesians 4.4–6</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>And are we not all family? The spiritual children of Christ and sons and daughters of Heavenly Father.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And now, because of the covenant which ye have made <strong>ye shall be called the children of Christ, his sons, and his daughters;</strong> for behold, this day he hath spiritually begotten you; for ye say that your hearts are changed through faith on his name; therefore, ye are born of him and have become his sons and his daughters. … therefore, I would that ye should take upon you the name of Christ… <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-5.7-8">Mosiah 5.7–8</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I testify the <a href="../concepts/hand-of-god.html">Hand of God</a> is real. He leads and guides people to where they need to be gathered. And when we gather together as one body, miracles happen.</p>
<hr>
<p>I also love this scripture, how Lehi was guided to a “land of promise”.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>behold, I <strong>have obtained</strong> a land of promise <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.5">1 Nephi 5.5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>He wrote “have obtained” while he was struggling for food and water in the desert. He saw ahead to when he’d eventually live in a near rain forest paradise.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>fast sunday</category>
  <category>my testimony</category>
  <category>memories</category>
  <category>let god prevail</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/my-testimony-2024-01-07.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 14:52:13 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What does it mean to preside?</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/what-does-it-mean-to-preside.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The responsibility of a Father is to preside:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>By divine design, <strong>fathers are to preside over their families in love and righteousness</strong> and are responsible to provide the necessities of life and protection for their families. <a href="../scriptures/the-family-proclamation">The Family Proclamation</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve long wondered what this meant. Earlier in my marriage I wondered: does this mean a father leads all family gatherings, has the first or last word, or delegates who says the prayer? That’s probably because the word “preside” is used synonymously with lead with respect to church callings and such:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Verily, I say unto you, saith the Lord of Hosts, there must needs be presiding elders to <strong>preside</strong> over those who are of the office of an elder; And also priests to <strong>preside</strong> over those who are of the office of a priest; 62 And also teachers to preside <strong>over</strong> those who are of the office of a teacher, in like manner, and also the deacons <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-107.60-62">Doctrine and Covenants 107.60–62</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I never really wondered if this was “who calls the shots”, or “who runs the show” - that never felt like a thing because my father is a gentle, servant leader. But I know some wonder what the details of this phrase mean. And what does it mean for single moms?</p>
<p>Well, I recently learned what <em>I</em> think it means. I started getting slightly more-than-average stressed with being sleep deprived after having a newborn.</p>
<p>I noticed, by consequence, my kids appeared more agitated. I remembered my <a href="../posts/your-mood-is-contagious.html">Mood is Contagious</a>.</p>
<p>Once I got more sleep, I realized the kids model my behavior as a father than follow my words. The way I talk to them is how they talk to each other - for better or worse.</p>
<p>Every parent knows this.</p>
<p>So while “preside” technically means to lead a meeting, it also means to lead a gathering. Is a family not a gathering?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>…how oft have I gathered you as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings, and have nourished you. And again, how oft would I have gathered you as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings, <a href="../scriptures/3-nephi-10.4-5">3 Nephi 10.4–5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-water-color-a-mother-hen-with-a-chicken-under-her-wing-as-its-raining.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Shouldn’t we preside more like this?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Maybe we can preside more like Christ: with kindness, gentleness, and love unfeigned.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>doctrine and covenants</category>
  <category>priesthood</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <category>the family a proclamation to the world</category>
  <category>parenting</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/what-does-it-mean-to-preside.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 13:37:28 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2024-01-07 Come Follow Me CTR 7 Jan 1-7</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-07-jan-7.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>5 min intro.</p>
<section id="book-of-mormon-overview-10m" class="level1">
<h1>Book of Mormon overview (10m)</h1>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3dNYpXZIN_c?si=dFOPuGvklJ1XOK2k" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</section>
<section id="keystone-activity-10m" class="level1">
<h1>Keystone Activity (10m)</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“I told the brethren that the Book of Mormon was the most correct of any book on earth, and the keystone of our religion, and a man would get nearer to God by abiding by its precepts, than by any other book.” <a href="../scriptures/introduction">Introduction</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-tip no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Activity
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Bring magnitiles. Have them try to build a triangle without any supporting pieces.</p>
<p>Test the strength of their creations. Pull out one piece and see if it falls.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="read-the-book-of-mormon-daily" class="level1">
<h1>Read the Book of Mormon Daily</h1>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-tip no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Activity
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Have the kids write down some things they do every day.</li>
<li>Is the Book of Mormon one of them?</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<p>Goal: spiritual closeness with the Savior every day.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The voices and pressures of the world are engaging and numerous. But too many voices are deceptive, seductive, and can pull us off the covenant path. To avoid the inevitable heartbreak that follows, I plead with you today to counter the lure of the world by <strong>making time for the Lord in your life—each and every day.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/russell-m-nelson-make-time-for-the-lord">“Make Time for the Lord”, Russell M. Nelson</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Read the Book of Mormon every day</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>My dear brothers and sisters, <strong>I promise that as you prayerfully study the Book of Mormon every day, you will make better decisions—every day</strong>. I promise that as you ponder what you study, the windows of heaven will open, and you will receive answers to your own questions and direction for your own life. I promise that as you daily immerse yourself in the Book of Mormon, you can be immunized against the evils of the day, even the gripping plague of pornography and other mind-numbing addictions. <a href="../scriptures/russell-m-nelson-the-book-of-mormon-what-would-your-life-be-like-without-it">“The Book of Mormon: What Would Your Life Be Like without It?”, Russell M. Nelson</a></p>
</blockquote>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>come follow me lesson plan</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-07-jan-7.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 08:58:34 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cars</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/cars.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>When’s the last time I walked 40 miles? 30? 20? 10?</p>
<p>It’s been a minute. Only 150 years ago or 200 years ago I may have done one of those maybe once a month or year.</p>
<p>While I’m not entirely sure it’s beneficial for my health <em>not</em> to walk a ton every day, I’m grateful for cars.</p>
<ul>
<li>I can live far from my workplace.</li>
<li>I can visit my parents in a day, today if I wanted</li>
<li>I can go to the hills, take a hike, and be back to take my kids to school</li>
<li>I can go get groceries.</li>
</ul>
<p>Maybe life was simpler back in the days without cars, I’m not sure. But I’m grateful for the variety of life I can live <em>with</em> a car. I also remember not having easy access to a car while living in the city and I just felt so trapped all the time. Cars are great.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-subaru-hill.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">I like my Subaru, even if it’s salvaged and 14 years old</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/cars.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 08:37:32 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Haircuts</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/haircuts.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Growing up my mom would cut my hair. I would sit in the bathroom on a wooden stool, looking into the mirror.</p>
<p>Today I cut my son’s hair for the first time. I couldn’t help but think of those many years of one-on-one conversations with my mom.</p>
<p>Spending time just sitting and talking can be the best time we have to share. It can be something as simple as a boring haircut.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-mom-cutting-boys-hair.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Time together is time not apart</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/haircuts.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2024 20:32:59 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AI won’t replace us. We’ll always create.</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/ai-will-not-replace-human-creativity.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I recently got back into writing some poems. <a href="../creative/poem-the-dove-forevermore.html">The Dove (Forevermore)</a> was fun to write. After the fact, I tried getting ChatGPT to create something similar. I only tried once before declaring victory.</p>
<p>Why is this poem meaningful to me? Because it has my soul in it. It’s the summation of my experience as a parent. Should you find it interesting, perhaps that’s why.</p>
<p>Reading <a href="../book-review/the-best-of-edgar-allen-poe.html">The Best of Edgar Allen Poe</a> recently I’m amazed (besides how depressing he is) at how excellent a writer he is. He peers into the mind and soul and extricates anything interesting. It’s interesting because a human wrote it.</p>
<p>Do we still paint, even if a camera can take a picture? Do we still ride bikes and horses even with cars and things? Do we still read even though we have TV and movies?</p>
<p>Words. Creative expression. They will always be interesting to us. Humans are interesting to us. Stories. Social acceptance is a fundamental human need. We desire connection. We’ll like reading something because a human wrote it.</p>
<p>But what about that guy I heard about who makes a ton of money using ChatGPT to create fake digital books on Amazon. People don’t <em>know</em> it’s AI-written. Digital GenAI images now are insanely accurate - it’s only 2024. It’s very possible great AI art will inspire us more than non-AI art (whatever that means because everyone uses photoshop anyway).</p>
<p>I’m not saying we won’t find value in AI art (creative writing, digital, video, etc.). We will. It’s clear we’ll have a really hard time knowing what’s human vs not.</p>
<p>But I am saying that creativity will never disappear. We’re always going to be interested in creating - even if machines can do it better. Machines can beat us at Go and StarCraft (<a href="../posts/2023-12-25-ai-robots-are-mastering-tasks-faster-than-humans-/index.html">AI Robots are mastering tasks faster than humans</a>), but we’ll still play. Because what else will there be to do?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-leonardo-painting-the-mona-lisa.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">I guess I’ll pick up painting now…</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>futurism</category>
  <category>humanity</category>
  <category>creativity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/ai-will-not-replace-human-creativity.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 23:21:29 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Time</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/time.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m grateful for time.</p>
<p>Time to live. Time to breathe. Time to eat. Time to walk. Time to sit at my computer and hope I’m making a difference in the world. Time to be with my family and realize I am.</p>
<p>Children are more affected by time than others. Time robs them of their youth, forcing them minute by minute into the world. But time is generous, equitable, and just. It’s fair to everyone. We all have time.</p>
<p>But we don’t all have the same time. Someone I know had cancer. Their time was marked. Another with cancer had their marking erased. Another on a bike passed out mid ride; time ran out. Another on a hill whose time was almost out recovered quickly. Time.</p>
<p>And I’m grateful for that time is temporary. (<a href="../creative/poem-the-dove-forevermore.html">The Dove (Forevermore)</a>)</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-hourglass-on-the-beach.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Time is measured by the sands of the beach, but the sands don’t measure time</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/time.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 19:57:52 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How I use the Book of Mormon</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/how-to-use-the-book-of-mormon.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The Book of Mormon is the most powerful book I’ve read.</p>
<p>This is how I get the most out of the book:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I say unto you that ye must pray always, and not faint; that ye <strong>must not perform any thing unto the Lord save in the first place ye shall pray unto the Father</strong> in the name of Christ, that <strong>he will consecrate thy performance unto thee</strong>, that thy performance may be for the welfare of thy soul. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-32.9">2 Nephi 32.9</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve read a lot of self help books. It’s not like that. This is a book that inspires personal revelation and a relationship with Christ and Heavenly Father. I get the most out of it when I have a true desire in my heart:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And when ye shall receive these things, I would exhort you that ye would ask God, the Eternal Father, in the name of Christ, if these things are not true; and if ye shall ask with a <strong>sincere heart, with real intent,</strong> having faith in Christ, he will manifest the truth of it unto you, by the power of the Holy Ghost. <a href="../scriptures/moroni-10.4">Moroni 10.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>When I read it in a rush, I don’t get much out of it. When I don’t pray before hand, or if I’m not sincere, I don’t really get anything substantive.</p>
<p>It’s like texting vs calling a friend. If you’re in a rush, you give a half thought text. But if you’re on a long drive and want to build a relationship, you give the friend a call.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-plant-a-seed-and-grow.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">If you plant a seed, you need to nourish it</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The best insight doesn’t come from the Book of Mormon. It comes from the Holy Ghost. So I can read the book as a literary critique and not see its divinity. But as I read it trying to build a relationship with Heavenly Father, then I feel that relationship grow.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Now, we will compare the word unto a seed. Now, if ye give place, that a seed may be <strong>planted in your heart</strong>, behold, if it be a true seed, or a good seed, if ye do not cast it out by your unbelief, that ye will resist the Spirit of the Lord, behold, it will begin to swell within your breasts; and when you feel these swelling motions, ye will begin to say within yourselves—It must needs be that this is a good seed, or that the word is good, for it beginneth to enlarge my soul; yea, it beginneth to enlighten my understanding, yea, it <strong>beginneth to be delicious to me.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/alma-32.28">Alma 32.28</a></p>
</blockquote>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>testimony</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/how-to-use-the-book-of-mormon.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 08:40:59 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hard Work and its Reward</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/hard-work.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>My dad grew up on a sheep farm. And his dad grew up farming too. Same with his dad, all the way back to when dads were a thing.</p>
<p>One of my grand/great grands worked on a beet farm. I read a story once about the beet farmers by Jay Jensen. It was called “Hoe to the end of the row” (apparently there’s a poem with that same title).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-beat-farming.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Beet it, just beet it…</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The principle the author shared was of planting to the end of the row. Some people got lazy and gave up 80% of the way through. But the hard workers went to the end. They took pride in it. And when the harvest came the boss knew who was coming back next summer: those with finished rows.</p>
<p>I’m grateful for hard work. My grandpa told my dad to work with his mind, not his back.<br>
So my dad got a desk job. And so did I.</p>
<p>Perhaps if my grandpa had seen today maybe he would instead say “get off those screens and go plant a beet”. But hard work is hard regardless of it being mental or physical. “Hard work” is the reward itself.</p>
<p>In another quote my father shared with me: “the gift of a good life is having lived it”. Same applies to hard work. The reward of hard work is having done it.</p>
<p>Most of what we do on a daily basis goes unnoticed. The rewards are for ourselves. This is a joy of life.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>perspective</category>
  <category>effort</category>
  <category>life lessons</category>
  <category>memories</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/hard-work.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 21:33:03 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What startups and musicians have in common</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/what-startups-and-musicians-have-in-common.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I was reminded of a video I watched a while back on YouTube. It was a great documentary about these new artists and their debate about whether to sign a record label (there’s a recent trend to selling music as an independent artist).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-musician-signing-record-label-watercolors.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Putting pen to ink</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I forget all the details, but there are some roughly insane trends that are generally interesting as I recall:</p>
<ul>
<li>new record labels are for $500k give or take. This is so the artist can invest a year into their music and get an album out, pay for production, etc.</li>
<li>many artists at that early stage aren’t financially literate and end up wasting the (they’re musicians, not bankers)</li>
<li>Some have to pay back the money</li>
<li>Up to 85% of the streaming royalties are owed to the label (started when streaming became a thing)</li>
<li>Labels also take a large portion of touring revenues now (something that wasn’t common 10 years ago)</li>
</ul>
<p>Why is this similar to tech startups? Lots.</p>
<p>Musicians have to find product market fit. They need to find their customers. Their monthly listeners.</p>
<p>They need to keep them coming back.</p>
<p>They need to differentiate.</p>
<p>Those who are customer focused and build a following are those who succeed. (Money in the bank and relying too much on the label can cripple you)</p>
<section id="the-musicians-in-town" class="level1">
<h1>The Musicians in Town</h1>
<p>I remember hanging out with some new artists while I was running my startup (we both used the same videographer). I couldn’t help but notice how similar the dynamics were. The founders. The first hires (replacements). The convos about who gets what. It’s all very fascinating.</p>
<p>Not much else to say.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>startups</category>
  <category>music</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/what-startups-and-musicians-have-in-common.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 20:53:53 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The future wave of AI hype</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/the-future-wave-of-ai-hype.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Reading about Airplane’s failure per OnlyCFO. A few notable quotes:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Airplane’s shutdown and future shutdowns like this will have negative consequences for many early stage companies. For many years buyers of these tools haven’t had to deal with a tool being abruptly killed. It only takes this happening once for you to really second guess purchasing a startup tool that is mission critical, deeply integrated, or would take a long time to replace.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/the-future-wave-of-ai-hype.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 20:32:46 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Write a thousand songs</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/write-a-thousand-songs.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I listened to an interview with Imagine Dragons. The lead singer talked about how he writes several songs per day.</p>
<p>No wonder he’s so successful. Repetitions breeds opportunity.</p>
<p>This has two affects on the brain. 1) lowers the pressure of individual songs. Don’t need to knock it of the park. 2) you get better at writing that much faster.</p>
<p>I heard once about a photography that let one half of the students only take 5 photos in a semester. The other half had to take 100. Which group had the better photos?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>You miss 100% of the shots you don’t take. <del>Wayne Gretzky</del> Michael Scott</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-hockey-shots-surreal-impressionist-water.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">More shots is more opportunities for a goal. Worry about good shots later.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>creativity</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/write-a-thousand-songs.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 15:10:01 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>When Leaders Lose their People</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/losing-to-yesmen.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In a scene in <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>, Paul notices that his warrior turns into his worshipper. He laments the loss, wondering if his non-religious warrior will be lost too.</p>
<p>Being a worshipped means you’re worshipped. Unchallenged. Can do no wrong. As such, you’re left with the intellect of one.</p>
<p>As a leader, you need to avoid worshippers. People who fail to challenge you out of fear or an abundance of praise. This all has to do in the decisions you make as a leader. The culture you decide to build. Is every voice heard, or does one voice rule them all?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-king-one-voice-to-rule.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">One voice to rule them all</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/losing-to-yesmen.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 14:31:39 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Multiverse of Careers</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-multiverse-of-careers.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Spoken about in <a href="../tech/dreaming-software.html">The Dream State of Software</a>, Paul of <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a> has a moment where he’s both past and present in his mind. He doesn’t know even whether he’s had his kid or not.</p>
<p>In a podcast I listened to lately on happiness, one suggestion was to write out all your goals and cross them off from day one. Pretend like it doesn’t even matter if you accomplish them. This helps free you.</p>
<p>Careers are like both of these things. We want everything. We can pretend like we have it. We can come to terms with it. And we can say “doesn’t matter if I don’t get that, because I’ve got a life outside my career.”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-multiverse-of-choice.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Which path you choose isn’t as important as who you choose as companions</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Consider your career from your deathbed (<a href="../posts/my-tombstone.html">My Tombstone</a>). What path did you take that mattered? What were all the alternate realities and multiverses you could have had.</p>
<p>Put them all together. In one multiverse you’ve been fired. In another you end up getting insanely wealthy. In another you start your own company. In another you become an online blogger.</p>
<p>All of them can’t be true when you do this exercise extensively enough. And choosing which one probably doesn’t matter as much (right vs wrong path thinking). If you’ve ever left a job you realize that nothing really comes over with you. Most relationships at work are short lived and contextual, like your relationships in high school. And that’s life.</p>
<p>Happiness is perhaps being okay with not having everything you desire, except for the few things that are truly attainable: peace with God, self, and cherished relationships.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <category>deathbed meditation</category>
  <category>career</category>
  <category>decisions</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-multiverse-of-careers.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 13:00:31 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>When a Person Changes their Perspective on Christ</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/a-change-in-witness.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The Book of Mormon had 12 witnesses of its divinity - the three spiritual testimonies by the Three Witnesses, the Eight Witnesses with a physical witness, and Joseph Smith, the one who translated it as prophet, seer, and revelator. Powerfully, all Three Witnesses left the church years later (1937/38) nearly 8-9 years after writing their testimony (1829), but never left their testimonies:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Despite differences with Joseph Smith that led each of the Three Witnesses to part ways individually with the Church (Cowdery and Harris later returned), they continued to affirm their testimony as witnesses throughout their lives. <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/history/topics/witnesses-of-the-book-of-mormon?lang=eng&amp;id=html">Witnesses of the Book of Mormon</a></p>
</blockquote>
<section id="when-a-loved-one-leaves-their-testimony" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>When a loved one leaves their testimony</h1>
<p>Let’s consider the world where these three denied their testimonies. (It’s easy to see that they “never doubted their own witness, therefore it must be true”.) But I think this is a sandy foundation because a thing should be true regardless of what three individuals say about it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-three-witnesses-one-missing.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">What if one had forsaken their testimony - would you still believe he saw it?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Those who believe in Christ hold strong beliefs in Him, and it must be a belief because they cannot see Him. They rely on the faith built on personal witness and also built by the testimony of others. But what do you do when a loved one abandons their testimony, or becomes an <a href="../book-review/unbelievable.html">unbeliever</a>? Do you doubt everything you learned from them? Perhaps.</p>
<p>Who do you trust - the “them” now that un-believes, or the “them” <em>then</em> that once believed?</p>
<p>Consider a hard-and-fast alternative: what if someone began doubting the existence of gravity? What if they were once your physics professor? Easy: you just go to the apple tree and demonstrate the principle by dropping an apple. “No, that’s magnetism”, the professor now claims.</p>
<p>You’re kind of stuck: well, if you think it’s magnetism, there’s not much I can do - this concept is called gravity. Similarly, people leave God’s path and believe the Hand of God that acts in their live is now, and always has been, just coincidence, luck, etc. what else could it be?</p>
<p>But what is coincidence? Luck? (I ponder these things often as a statistician. For another time…)</p>
</section>
<section id="putting-a-name-on-a-concept" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Putting a name on a Concept</h1>
<p>There’s precedence for this - when Ammon appeared to the Lamanites, they thought he acted by the Great Spirit. Instead of telling them they were wrong, he instead clarified, “that great spirit <em>is</em> God”.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>26 And then Ammon said: Believest thou that there is a Great Spirit? 27 And he said, Yea. 28 And Ammon said: This is God. And Ammon said unto him again: Believest thou that this Great Spirit, who is God, created all things which are in heaven and in the earth?<br>
<a href="../scriptures/alma-18.26-28">Alma 18.26–28</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Likewise, when unbelievers doubt the Hand of God, or re-cast their old ways according to a <em>new</em> belief framework, perhaps they’re just labeling a concept in a different way. (It’s also really hard to know what someone once considered “God” vs not in their life, so take this point with a grain of salt.)</p>
<p>After all, when people leave God some claim they were under <a href="https://robjhyndman.com/unbelievable/ch4.html">confirmation bias</a>, the concept that you favor the evidence that supports your belief. Hyndman argues confirmation bias can go both ways, for believers and unbelievers, but <em>does</em> claim that evidence favors the skeptics because there should be evidence. I’d argue he relies solely on <em>physical</em> evidence. There is <em>spiritual</em> evidence to be considered. <em>Spiritual</em> evidence is what we believe in. It’s what the Three Witnesses relied on. It’s unprovable to anyone else, and only receivable by the Holy Ghost. If God exists, let Him reveal himself. Let Him prevail:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>But whom say ye that I am? 16 And Simon Peter answered and said, Thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God. 17 And Jesus answered and said unto him, Blessed art thou, Simon Bar-jona: for <strong>flesh and blood hath not revealed it unto thee, but my Father which is in heaven.</strong><br>
<a href="../scriptures/matthew-16.15-17">Matthew 16.15–17</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The most powerful thing about being a Christian is that <em>it cannot be proven</em> Christ <em>didn’t</em> exist or walk the earth. Even if you falsify the entire bible, erase history, or discover that “Mary” was an invented concept by some creed or counsel bound to oppress us - there’s still a question: did the Man exist? We can debate it. Pharisees debated if He was That Messiah. Nobody now can know, except God reveals it to them.</p>
<p>Why? Because to claim God doesn’t exist, or the plates weren’t real, you’d also have to have evidence. Counter-evidence <em>isn’t</em> evidence. Lack of evidence likewise. Don’t we continually find new fossils? New animals in the wild? Lack of evidence doesn’t mean they don’t exist.<sup>1</sup></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;The other side may say (as Hyndman) does), I might as well believe in the Tooth Fairy, or Santa, because I don’t have evidence they don’t exist. Fair. Then belief is a choice, and must follow the principle of “by their fruits ye shall know them”. Did Baal call down Fire? No, only Elijah’s God. “Was that story of the Bible invented?” Perhaps. If so, explain why living Christ’s gospel brings me joy? “Because they’re good principles”, well, what is good, if not God? “Well then why not Zeus, or Baal to be your God?”, because I believe in the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob - not the God of Baal. I believe the scriptures because they teach good things. “What about the misogyny, racism, war and killing in the Bible etc etc etc”, well, perhaps some was commanded by God for reasons and context we don’t have. Perhaps some of the Bible isn’t truely written. “If some isn’t true it’s all not true because parts of it say it’s all true”. Well, what’s true is true, what’s not isn’t. “Who’s to say what God inspired?” Well, who’s to say what’s not inspired? Only God. “We’re not getting anywhere”. Ahh, but we are. Because I believe in God, and after believing Him I exercised faith in His son to pray on His name and open myself to trying to follow His ways. I’m far from perfect, but once I did this, I received spiritual knowledge, and having seen more of the Hand of God in my life, I can say there are miracles of events I can’t explain by chance or delusion alone. Miracles only a loving God could produce. This is my knowledge, which follows faith. <a href="../scriptures/alma-32.34-36">Alma 32.34–36</a> And we also have the Book of Mormon, which is a powerful second witness of Christ that brought reality to the truth in the Bible, and continually helps me feel the fruits of the Spirit, which is the Holy Ghost telling me it’s true.</p></li><li id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;my whole life until 21 I had no idea Joseph Smith had so many (up to 42) wives. “Some say he was a womanizer, pimp, etc”. Perhaps. But perhaps he was a prophet commanded to do so. Were we there? God at one point commanded Abraham to raise seed and have many wives. “Maybe Abraham was a philanderer too.” Okay, but does that definition of chastity and virtue not depend on the very construction of marriage as ordained by God who married Adam and Eve as husband and wife? If it’s from God, it’s His law, and He chose the rules. “But Joseph altered the rules and made stuff up so he could get with women and teenagers.” Perhaps. That assumes we know him, he told us that, and he believed it to be true. So we’ll leave it as an opinion. In my opinion he followed a commandment from an Angel, despite me not understanding it entirely or being comfortable with the idea. Let the man speak for himself.</p></li></div><p>To prove the Abrahamic God doesn’t exist people just say “well I found all this stuff about the bible, about church leaders, etc” was wrong or misconstrued. So? First, we have to make sure the “new stuff” learned is actually true (could be a lie), but if it is true (that something you once believed is a lie or misunderstanding) we must find out how this fits into Christ’s bigger picture.<sup>2</sup></p>
<p>You can’t claim that Joseph Smith <em>didn’t</em> see God and that the <em>Three Witnesses</em> <em>didn’t</em> see the plates at some point. Because you weren’t there in 1829. Even if they <em>had</em> later denied, from reading <a href="../book-review/killers-of-the-flower-moon.html">Killers of the Flower Moon: the Osage Murders and the Birth of the FBI</a>, it’s quite clear how people can be manipulated in the courts of law, influenced by money, influenced by their own delusions, etc. Since delusions go both ways, relying on people at all isn’t how we learn the existence of a Divine. Peter learned of Christ’s divinity the way we all must (quote above). Show me the evidence, says the scientist in me: the <em>spiritual</em> evidence. # Flip Floppers on Both Sides</p>
<p>Floppers flip both ways. The quote above said another way: who’s witness do you trust - the <em>you</em> of today, the <em>you</em> of yesterday, or the <em>you</em> of tomorrow? We can all come and go with our testimonies. This is life. We must have an unalterable way to learn truth, one independent of our path.</p>
<p>We’ve got the Paul’s of the world who were once Christian persecutors who flip to believers, and we’ve got those who claimed Joseph Smith was a fallen prophet after being in vision with him.</p>
<p>We’re all more like Laman and Lemuel than we realize. We see things that make us believe, we come to God, and then we forget and wonder if they never happened.</p>
<p>We’re all flip floppers. Let us not seek truth alone from others, or even rely solely on the Prophet. Our testimonies must be on Christ, and learning truth by the Holy Ghost, who will then guide us to understand the words of prophets and imperfect leaders. It’s good science.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In coming days, it will not be possible to survive spiritually without the guiding, directing, comforting, and constant influence of the Holy Ghost.<br>
<a href="../scriptures/russell-m-nelson-revelation-for-the-church-revelation-for-our-lives">“Revelation for the Church, Revelation for Our Lives”, Russell M. Nelson</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’m glad the Three Witnesses never denied their testimonies, but I’m glad there’s a way to know the Book of Mormon is true without them. After all, those dudes didn’t answer my prayer about the book’s truth. Heavenly Father did.</p>


</section>


<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>epistemology</category>
  <category>theology</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/a-change-in-witness.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 09:11:17 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>30 Seconds is All You Get</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/30-seconds-for-payment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Apple iTunes changed the music industry forever with one simple decision: the preview of a song should be 30 seconds long.</p>
<p>This little change dramatically altered how music sounds today. I’ve recently listened to some bangers that were only 90 seconds long. They left me hanging.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-listening-to-music-colorful.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Enjoy the music while it lasts</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Why was my song so short? Because nobody gets paid after 30 seconds.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Apple’s decision made artists want to have more interesting 30 seconds in the iTunes Store</li>
<li>That evolved into: an artist doesn’t get paid if you don’t listen at least 30 seconds. And they don’t get paid any more if you listen 31 or 900 seconds. In fact, they get paid more if you listen to two songs, 30s a piece.</li>
</ol>
<p>Spotify, Amazon, YouTube, Apple, etc all pay based on views. They each define views their own way, but they need to negotiate with the labels who already decided to agree to Apple’s 30s schemes in the early 2000’s. They may have different payment schemes, but some have a scheme of “take all revenue, distribute it according to the artist’s share of views.” So if I pay $10/mo for Spotify and don’t use it, my money goes to someone I didn’t listen to.</p>
<p>So how do small artists compete? They’ve got to build their following. Proportionally, the major artists (rather, their labels) soak up all the streaming royalties.</p>
<p>What would be more fair is if my $10 went to the artists I actually listened to, as if I bought their music.</p>
<p>Why does any of this matter? Algorithms. Optimization. Monetization.</p>
<p>Incentives drive outcomes. How we designed our music payment incentives altered music forever (try to be super catchy for 30s). Now, with AI, music can be created much faster which will dilute the pool.</p>
<p>In the end, one simple decision changed billions of lives. 30s? That’s all you need to get paid.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>music</category>
  <category>economics</category>
  <category>incentives</category>
  <category>posts</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/30-seconds-for-payment.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Zoom</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/zoom.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I first heard about zoom many years ago on a random podcast. Had no idea what it was or why it was useful. Now it’s enabled me to work remotely, chat with friends across the nation, and even attend church during lockdowns.</p>
<p>Behind this is a person with an idea that changed the world. Surely they weren’t the first video service, but they build off the earlier, crappier products.</p>
<p>I’m grateful for V1’s like Skype that paved the way for Zoom, which learned a ton, probably poached some talent, and gave me something with using.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-caravaggio-zoom.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Beethoven Zooming with friends, ala Caravaggio</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/zoom.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Your Mood is Contagious</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/your-mood-is-contagious.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-mood-sharing.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Moods flow. Keep the negative waves at bay</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There’s no question that moods are contagious. I once asked someone at the beach to leash their dog, and they slightly rebuked me, “this is a dog friendly beach.” <em>Well, so it is,</em> I thought, grumpily. I complained to a family member about this grumpy dog owner.</p>
<p>Moods escalate. And negative moods are even more pervasive and contagious than positive ones. They say a disgruntled customer tells more friends and family than happy ones. Why is this?</p>
<p>In the “Black Cat” (<a href="../book-review/the-best-of-edgar-allen-poe.html">The Best of Edgar Allen Poe</a>), Poe describes a gruesome tale man who wanted to do evil just for the sake of it. That it’s in his nature. Not because you want to do the thing, but because you want to do a forbidden thing. The same goes the other way, for sure. But I think we trend slightly pessimistic because being an optimist is more beneficial, more rewarding and therefore more difficult.</p>
<p>A leader once told me when I was managing a team, “They’ll pick up on <em>everything</em> you do or say.” Oddly, I was picking up on what he was saying.</p>
<p>So when you lead, lead carefully. Whether in home or work, lead with kindness, compassion, and restraint. Speak three kind words before a negative. Ask to understand before assuming. Lead as a servant. It takes all the effort to overcome negative vibes, and who better equipped than the leader to do it?</p>
<p>Don’t be Moriarty:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ncbEucjsNFU?si=rYhBqqavn4Nergap" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>“Why can’t you be more hopeful for a change?”</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <category>parenting</category>
  <category>emotional resilience</category>
  <category>grit</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/your-mood-is-contagious.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Writing Ethos</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/lists/writing-ethos.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>List of reasons why I write this blog and principles I aspire to. They evolve over time, and I like to keep track.</p>
<p>2023-12-31</p>
<ul>
<li>Write every day (Seth Godin style). Many posts will be bad. But higher repetitions means better writing.</li>
<li>Learn by writing. Synthesis only happens when sharing.</li>
<li>Write first, edit later.</li>
<li>Use writing to actively digest world news. Doomscrolling is futile and anxiety inducing. Writing and synthesizing helps me comparmentalize the world and where I fit into it.</li>
<li>Develop an opinion. Strong opinions, weakly held. A ship is better heading in any direction than none at all. An opinion is a direction.</li>
<li>Every post is a story. If it’s not a story, it’s not worth reading.</li>
<li>I am me. I write what’s on my mind. I hope it’s interesting to different people in different ways.</li>
<li>Write each post for one real person in my life, based on one real discussion.</li>
<li>Gratitude is healing, produces optimism, and reveals a new way. Give thanks daily. I give thanks, therefore I have.</li>
</ul>
<p>2022-12-05</p>
<ul>
<li>All blogs are wrong, but some are useful (riff on George Box’s quote that all models are wrong)</li>
</ul>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>lists</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/lists/writing-ethos.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
