<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/all.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/all.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 23:33:40 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Scriptures within Scriptures</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/scriptures-within-scriptures.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-white-fruit-delicious-zoom-in.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The Scriptures are precious and worth our time</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Nephi recounts how they had obtained some scriptures:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And <strong>we had obtained the records which the Lord had commanded us</strong>, and searched them and found that they were desirable; yea, even of great worth unto us, insomuch that we could preserve the commandments of the Lord unto our children. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.21">1 Nephi 5.21</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>A few things that stand out to me:</p>
<ul>
<li>He thought about his children. In <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-25.26">2 Nephi 25.26</a> it’s mentioned “that our children may know to what source they may look for a remission of their sins.”</li>
<li>They had the scriptures because they accomplished the task laid before them, “I know that the Lord giveth no commandments unto the children of men, save he shall prepare a way for them that they may accomplish the thing which he commandeth them.” <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-3.7.html">1 Nephi 3.7</a></li>
<li>These scriptures were “desirable”. Know what else is desirable? The fruit of the tree of life:</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass that I beheld a tree, whose fruit was desirable to make one happy. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-8.10">1 Nephi 8.10</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The scriptures, especially the Book of Mormon, are precious to help our families know of Christ, have been obtained and written by those obedient to Christ, and are desirable and great to consume.</p>
<p>In <a href="../tech/a-knife-to-a-gun-fight.html">A Knife to a Gun Fight: Why I’m off Social Media</a>, I talk about how tech workers talk of social media as “snackable content”. Frequently the word “consumption” is used to describe how app “users” “consume” content.</p>
<p>It’s mostly not the stuff worth consuming in great quantities. Don’t settle for snacks. Enjoy a feast:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wherefore, do not spend <strong>money</strong> for that which is of no worth, nor your labor for that which cannot satisfy. Hearken diligently unto me, and remember the words which I have spoken; and come unto the Holy One of Israel, and <strong>feast upon that which perisheth not</strong>, neither can be corrupted, and <strong>let your soul delight in fatness.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-9.51">2 Nephi 9.51</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>Replace “money” with “time”.</em></p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>scripture of the day</category>
  <category>scriptures</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/scriptures-within-scriptures.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 23:33:40 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Dune: Messiah</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/dune-messiah.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Sequel to <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>.</p>
<p>Notes: - sometimes lies are easier to believe than the truth</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/dune-messiah.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 22:07:10 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Legal AI</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/lists/legal-ai.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.maginative.com/article/legal-ai-startup-harvey-ai-raises-80m-at-715m-valuation/">Harvey</a>: valued at $715M, partners with OpenAI. Contract review and document drafting. (2024-01-08)
<ul>
<li>Competitors: EvenUp, Darrow, Casetext</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/lists/legal-ai.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 21:44:17 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Power of Habit</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/the-power-of-habit.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-the-power-of-habit.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Power of Habit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/the-power-of-habit.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 19:34:02 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for the Toothbrush</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/toothbrush.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Is there anything more refreshing than brushing your teeth? Anything less satisfying than going to bed without brushing your teeth (camping, airplane ride?)?</p>
<p>Brushing my teeth is a gift. And I know it prevents problems (cavities, disease, etc). It also enables me to have more sugar, which is probably bad for me but I enjoy regardless.</p>
<p>In <a href="../book-review/the-power-of-habit.html">The Power of Habit</a> and learned about this great fact about tooth brushing (summarized by ChatGPT):</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Yes, “The Power of Habit” by Charles Duhigg does mention toothpaste. The book discusses how toothpaste companies, particularly Pepsodent, leveraged the power of habit to increase their product’s usage. Duhigg explains how Pepsodent created a daily habit for people by associating the use of toothpaste with the tingling sensation it produces, which wasn’t common in toothpastes before Pepsodent. This case study is used to illustrate how cues and rewards can create lasting habits.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Pepsodent and their marketing team in the 1920’s changed life for us all. Same goes for body wash, hand soap, and other soaps - they put the bubbles in them to make us think it’s “working”.</p>
<p>But I also like bubbles. Who doesn’t like bubbles? Toothpaste has bubbles. What a gift.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-toothbrush-family-1920.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Family bonding through bubbling refreshment since the 1920s</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/toothbrush.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 19:31:43 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Knife to a Gun Fight: Why I’m off Social Media</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/a-knife-to-a-gun-fight.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Tim Ferris describes why he doesn’t have social media on his phone:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_Fn-giKevmo?si=f1Lz9H2U08BQhKwv" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>I recently deleted social media from my phone 14 days ago. I had been using Instagram until April when I quit and Twitter all year. I realized within days how much better I felt without social media. Happier. Legitimately happier.</p>
<p>And why? What do I get out of it? I’m not growing closer to friends. That’s what texting and calling and spending time in person does. But I’d argue even texting doesn’t really strengthen a relationship because it’s so hard to properly interpret emotions and cues via text: you interpret them how you read those texts. You interpret it according to your emotional state, not the sender’s.</p>
<p>Phone provides vocal emotional cues. Body language another set of emotional cues. I can get probably 70% of this out from FaceTime or <a href="../gratitude/zoom.html">Zoom</a>. But being in person is what we’re meant for.</p>
<p>This is why we strengthen relationships locally, and fail to continue ones from high school or our previous job.</p>
<p>So what was I doing on social media? Watching clips of either strangers I don’t care about or college associates I friended (once lived locally with) that I no longer talk to.</p>
<p>So what’s the knife you’re bringing to the gun fight? When at YouTube I heard the CEO praise a team for increasing “seconds watched” by 15% by reducing the lag of the swipes between YouTube shorts (TikTok clone). The lag reduction was in the milliseconds. Your attention is being bought and manipulated by the shareholders of these companies.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-knife-gun-fight.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Yes, they’re targeting specifically you. You don’t stand a chance. And you have a pocket knife, and you’re 50 feet away. Who’s gonna win?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>They A/B test everything. This isn’t morally wrong. It’s actually quite human: we all A/B test everything every day. A joke here. A smile there. We put out feelers and see if we get a reaction. Don’t believe me? Ask my kid why he keeps throwing things in the toilet!</p>
<p>Billions of dollars and the brightest minds on earth are working at FAANG. Why? They need to provide for their families and academics doesn’t pay. Non-profits don’t pay. This isn’t immoral, it just is. There are very good people working there: honest, moral people. Some of the best I’ve seen in the industry. But when you get paid to maximize swipes, you maximize swipes. It’s just human nature. And some of them buy into the odd notions of “snackable content”, as if swiping for 30 minutes while on the toilet is what anyone wakes up excited to do. Keep on snacking…</p>
<p>Social media and Netflix provide a ton of value to the world in my opinion. I can use them to call anyone I want, raise money for a cause, or get likes on a cute pic of my cat (I don’t have a cat). I <em>do</em> see the value.</p>
<p>But the costs for me have outweighed the value.</p>
<p>I <em>do</em> miss laughing about some random Reel. There’s nothing that can get you laughing faster than a 10 second clip paired with the right cuts and music and everything. The right meme just nails it in a way nothing else can. I miss seeing memes from my friends. But when all I do is send memes to these friends, is that a friendship?</p>
<p>Since being off social media I feel like my senses have grown. I now find my kids a lot funnier, my wife funnier, and I’m able to make heavy situations lighter much easier.</p>
<p>There’s a quote in <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a> that’s something like “If you rely only on your eyes, your other senses weaken”. I’d argue my other relationships weakened too. Time to leave the fight. I was losing.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>personal experiments</category>
  <category>A/B testing</category>
  <category>social media</category>
  <category>big tech</category>
  <category>incentives</category>
  <category>decisions</category>
  <category>relationships</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>emotional intelligence</category>
  <category>purpose of life</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/a-knife-to-a-gun-fight.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 11:24:09 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Becoming an expert is kind of a fallacy</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/becoming-an-expert.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Just watched this clip:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/I2ZK3ngNvvI?si=p4BCDVMWKBoc4KJQ" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Important discussion points: as a novice you’re worried about where to go or picking the wrong thing.</p>
<p>I remember not taking an opportunity to learn C++ because “that’s not what I want to do”. In another occasion I wanted to learn PySpark over SQL because Python…</p>
<p>While I don’t regret that choice per se, because I chose something else I was interested in, I’ve largely come to realize that I don’t care what programming language I’m using. I care about getting the job done.</p>
<p>Also, I’m probably over the 10,000 hours of <em>something</em>, I just don’t know what. Am I an ML expert? Data expert? SQL? Python? R?</p>
<p>Is it the application of the skill that makes you an expert? I’m not sure. Because I think novices can do some incredible things if they hone in.</p>
<p>If you read one book on a topic, you’re by no means an “expert”, but you probably know more about that topic than 99% of the nation. I learned this when I spent 6 months diving into the home security industry for my first job. Pretty sure I knew more about that than anyone I spoke to. Was I an expert? I really only had maybe 300 hours. Maybe I was inexperienced. Sure.</p>
<p>And who spends literally 10,000 hours on any one thing? Like 10,000 hours on XGBoost? Image classification? Deep learning? Machine learning? A/B testing? Spreadsheets? Generalist vs specialist, etc. if you’re an ML scientist at Google, you worry about very different things than an ML scientist at a startup. At a startup, you worry about your bigquery allocation and pipeline failures. At Google you worry about what your 5th skip VP is going to deprecate that month.</p>
<p>That’s just the nature of education. There are so many things in the world to know…that being an “expert” is a relative thing. But I agree that working hard and learning useful things helps you innovate faster.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-rocky-balboa-expert.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">I’d change my opinion on being an expert if I needed to beat Rocky.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Last thing, the crux is: don’t compare yourself to others. Compare yourself to yourself. That’s how you assess your progress.</p>
<p>But I’d argue: why even compare yourself to yourself? Compare your solution to the problem. Does it matter if you have 10,000 hours? No.&nbsp;What matters is if the solution fits. This is why innovations and disruptions come from unexpected places: because novices can nail solutions.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>personal development</category>
  <category>growth</category>
  <category>grit</category>
  <category>life lessons</category>
  <category>data science</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/becoming-an-expert.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 22:55:24 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My testimony: Moving across the Country</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/my-testimony-2024-01-07.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>Today is fast Sunday, a day when testimonies are shared in church. Here’s my testimony I shared today. Someone had just spoken about moving to a new place and seeing God in their lives, even if it was far away from where they had thought they needed to be. They had moved away from family.</em></p>
<p>I was reminded today of why I live where I do. Without going into personal details, as a family we decided it was time to leave the east coast and move west. As I wondered how it might be possible, I was encouraged by my wife to reach out to an old contact on a random spreadsheet I had kept seven years prior when I was first looking for jobs. The guy had since changed jobs from when he had interviewed me, but he referred me to his new company.</p>
<p>Well, this company was otherwise impossible to get noticed at, even with referrals. Turns out this guy was a lot higher than I had known. It was enough to get me the first interview. Four years later we’re still on the west coast. It’s definitely a better situation for our family in many ways.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-u-haul-moving.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Moving because when we had a desire, the Lord opened the door for us</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And in terms of family, I grew up living far away from cousins. My church congregation became my family. My parents friends became my Sunday school teachers and mentors. My friends at church became my closest confidants and kept me company in living the principles I believed in.</p>
<p>Recently, this church family helped us with meals, gifts, and emotional warmth. I don’t know what I’d do without belonging to a group of people who care for one another (I know many communities are like this, but I think it’s extra special in a Christian context where everyone wants to help and strengthen each other in kindness. We all try their best.)</p>
<p>Christ’s design that we have a church is inspired:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>There is <strong>one body, and one Spirit</strong>, even as ye are called in one hope of your calling; One Lord, one faith, one baptism, One God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all. <a href="../scriptures/ephesians-4.4-6">Ephesians 4.4–6</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>And are we not all family? The spiritual children of Christ and sons and daughters of Heavenly Father.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And now, because of the covenant which ye have made <strong>ye shall be called the children of Christ, his sons, and his daughters;</strong> for behold, this day he hath spiritually begotten you; for ye say that your hearts are changed through faith on his name; therefore, ye are born of him and have become his sons and his daughters. … therefore, I would that ye should take upon you the name of Christ… <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-5.7-8">Mosiah 5.7–8</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I testify the <a href="../concepts/hand-of-god.html">Hand of God</a> is real. He leads and guides people to where they need to be gathered. And when we gather together as one body, miracles happen.</p>
<hr>
<p>I also love this scripture, how Lehi was guided to a “land of promise”.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>behold, I <strong>have obtained</strong> a land of promise <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.5">1 Nephi 5.5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>He wrote “have obtained” while he was struggling for food and water in the desert. He saw ahead to when he’d eventually live in a near rain forest paradise.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>fast sunday</category>
  <category>my testimony</category>
  <category>memories</category>
  <category>let god prevail</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/my-testimony-2024-01-07.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 14:52:13 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What does it mean to preside?</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/what-does-it-mean-to-preside.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The responsibility of a Father is to preside:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>By divine design, <strong>fathers are to preside over their families in love and righteousness</strong> and are responsible to provide the necessities of life and protection for their families. <a href="../scriptures/the-family-proclamation">The Family Proclamation</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve long wondered what this meant. Earlier in my marriage I wondered: does this mean a father leads all family gatherings, has the first or last word, or delegates who says the prayer? That’s probably because the word “preside” is used synonymously with lead with respect to church callings and such:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Verily, I say unto you, saith the Lord of Hosts, there must needs be presiding elders to <strong>preside</strong> over those who are of the office of an elder; And also priests to <strong>preside</strong> over those who are of the office of a priest; 62 And also teachers to preside <strong>over</strong> those who are of the office of a teacher, in like manner, and also the deacons <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-107.60-62">Doctrine and Covenants 107.60–62</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I never really wondered if this was “who calls the shots”, or “who runs the show” - that never felt like a thing because my father is a gentle, servant leader. But I know some wonder what the details of this phrase mean. And what does it mean for single moms?</p>
<p>Well, I recently learned what <em>I</em> think it means. I started getting slightly more-than-average stressed with being sleep deprived after having a newborn.</p>
<p>I noticed, by consequence, my kids appeared more agitated. I remembered my <a href="../posts/your-mood-is-contagious.html">Mood is Contagious</a>.</p>
<p>Once I got more sleep, I realized the kids model my behavior as a father than follow my words. The way I talk to them is how they talk to each other - for better or worse.</p>
<p>Every parent knows this.</p>
<p>So while “preside” technically means to lead a meeting, it also means to lead a gathering. Is a family not a gathering?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>…how oft have I gathered you as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings, and have nourished you. And again, how oft would I have gathered you as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings, <a href="../scriptures/3-nephi-10.4-5">3 Nephi 10.4–5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-water-color-a-mother-hen-with-a-chicken-under-her-wing-as-its-raining.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Shouldn’t we preside more like this?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Maybe we can preside more like Christ: with kindness, gentleness, and love unfeigned.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>doctrine and covenants</category>
  <category>priesthood</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <category>the family a proclamation to the world</category>
  <category>parenting</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/what-does-it-mean-to-preside.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 13:37:28 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2024-01-07 Come Follow Me CTR 7 Jan 1-7</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-07-jan-7.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>5 min intro.</p>
<section id="book-of-mormon-overview-10m" class="level1">
<h1>Book of Mormon overview (10m)</h1>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3dNYpXZIN_c?si=dFOPuGvklJ1XOK2k" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</section>
<section id="keystone-activity-10m" class="level1">
<h1>Keystone Activity (10m)</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“I told the brethren that the Book of Mormon was the most correct of any book on earth, and the keystone of our religion, and a man would get nearer to God by abiding by its precepts, than by any other book.” <a href="../scriptures/introduction">Introduction</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-tip no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Activity
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Bring magnitiles. Have them try to build a triangle without any supporting pieces.</p>
<p>Test the strength of their creations. Pull out one piece and see if it falls.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="read-the-book-of-mormon-daily" class="level1">
<h1>Read the Book of Mormon Daily</h1>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-tip no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Activity
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Have the kids write down some things they do every day.</li>
<li>Is the Book of Mormon one of them?</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<p>Goal: spiritual closeness with the Savior every day.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The voices and pressures of the world are engaging and numerous. But too many voices are deceptive, seductive, and can pull us off the covenant path. To avoid the inevitable heartbreak that follows, I plead with you today to counter the lure of the world by <strong>making time for the Lord in your life—each and every day.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/russell-m-nelson-make-time-for-the-lord">“Make Time for the Lord”, Russell M. Nelson</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Read the Book of Mormon every day</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>My dear brothers and sisters, <strong>I promise that as you prayerfully study the Book of Mormon every day, you will make better decisions—every day</strong>. I promise that as you ponder what you study, the windows of heaven will open, and you will receive answers to your own questions and direction for your own life. I promise that as you daily immerse yourself in the Book of Mormon, you can be immunized against the evils of the day, even the gripping plague of pornography and other mind-numbing addictions. <a href="../scriptures/russell-m-nelson-the-book-of-mormon-what-would-your-life-be-like-without-it">“The Book of Mormon: What Would Your Life Be Like without It?”, Russell M. Nelson</a></p>
</blockquote>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>come follow me lesson plan</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-07-jan-7.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 08:58:34 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cars</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/cars.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>When’s the last time I walked 40 miles? 30? 20? 10?</p>
<p>It’s been a minute. Only 150 years ago or 200 years ago I may have done one of those maybe once a month or year.</p>
<p>While I’m not entirely sure it’s beneficial for my health <em>not</em> to walk a ton every day, I’m grateful for cars.</p>
<ul>
<li>I can live far from my workplace.</li>
<li>I can visit my parents in a day, today if I wanted</li>
<li>I can go to the hills, take a hike, and be back to take my kids to school</li>
<li>I can go get groceries.</li>
</ul>
<p>Maybe life was simpler back in the days without cars, I’m not sure. But I’m grateful for the variety of life I can live <em>with</em> a car. I also remember not having easy access to a car while living in the city and I just felt so trapped all the time. Cars are great.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-subaru-hill.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">I like my Subaru, even if it’s salvaged and 14 years old</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/cars.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 08:37:32 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I’m Grateful for Haircuts</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/haircuts.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Growing up my mom would cut my hair. I would sit in the bathroom on a wooden stool, looking into the mirror.</p>
<p>Today I cut my son’s hair for the first time. I couldn’t help but think of those many years of one-on-one conversations with my mom.</p>
<p>Spending time just sitting and talking can be the best time we have to share. It can be something as simple as a boring haircut.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-mom-cutting-boys-hair.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Time together is time not apart</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/haircuts.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2024 20:32:59 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AI won’t replace us. We’ll always create.</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/ai-will-not-replace-human-creativity.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I recently got back into writing some poems. <a href="../creative/poem-the-dove-forevermore.html">The Dove (Forevermore)</a> was fun to write. After the fact, I tried getting ChatGPT to create something similar. I only tried once before declaring victory.</p>
<p>Why is this poem meaningful to me? Because it has my soul in it. It’s the summation of my experience as a parent. Should you find it interesting, perhaps that’s why.</p>
<p>Reading <a href="../book-review/the-best-of-edgar-allen-poe.html">The Best of Edgar Allen Poe</a> recently I’m amazed (besides how depressing he is) at how excellent a writer he is. He peers into the mind and soul and extricates anything interesting. It’s interesting because a human wrote it.</p>
<p>Do we still paint, even if a camera can take a picture? Do we still ride bikes and horses even with cars and things? Do we still read even though we have TV and movies?</p>
<p>Words. Creative expression. They will always be interesting to us. Humans are interesting to us. Stories. Social acceptance is a fundamental human need. We desire connection. We’ll like reading something because a human wrote it.</p>
<p>But what about that guy I heard about who makes a ton of money using ChatGPT to create fake digital books on Amazon. People don’t <em>know</em> it’s AI-written. Digital GenAI images now are insanely accurate - it’s only 2024. It’s very possible great AI art will inspire us more than non-AI art (whatever that means because everyone uses photoshop anyway).</p>
<p>I’m not saying we won’t find value in AI art (creative writing, digital, video, etc.). We will. It’s clear we’ll have a really hard time knowing what’s human vs not.</p>
<p>But I am saying that creativity will never disappear. We’re always going to be interested in creating - even if machines can do it better. Machines can beat us at Go and StarCraft (<a href="../posts/2023-12-25-ai-robots-are-mastering-tasks-faster-than-humans-/index.html">AI Robots are mastering tasks faster than humans</a>), but we’ll still play. Because what else will there be to do?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-leonardo-painting-the-mona-lisa.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">I guess I’ll pick up painting now…</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>futurism</category>
  <category>humanity</category>
  <category>creativity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/ai-will-not-replace-human-creativity.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 23:21:29 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Time</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/time.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m grateful for time.</p>
<p>Time to live. Time to breathe. Time to eat. Time to walk. Time to sit at my computer and hope I’m making a difference in the world. Time to be with my family and realize I am.</p>
<p>Children are more affected by time than others. Time robs them of their youth, forcing them minute by minute into the world. But time is generous, equitable, and just. It’s fair to everyone. We all have time.</p>
<p>But we don’t all have the same time. Someone I know had cancer. Their time was marked. Another with cancer had their marking erased. Another on a bike passed out mid ride; time ran out. Another on a hill whose time was almost out recovered quickly. Time.</p>
<p>And I’m grateful for that time is temporary. (<a href="../creative/poem-the-dove-forevermore.html">The Dove (Forevermore)</a>)</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-hourglass-on-the-beach.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Time is measured by the sands of the beach, but the sands don’t measure time</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/time.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 19:57:52 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How I use the Book of Mormon</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/how-to-use-the-book-of-mormon.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The Book of Mormon is the most powerful book I’ve read.</p>
<p>This is how I get the most out of the book:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I say unto you that ye must pray always, and not faint; that ye <strong>must not perform any thing unto the Lord save in the first place ye shall pray unto the Father</strong> in the name of Christ, that <strong>he will consecrate thy performance unto thee</strong>, that thy performance may be for the welfare of thy soul. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-32.9">2 Nephi 32.9</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve read a lot of self help books. It’s not like that. This is a book that inspires personal revelation and a relationship with Christ and Heavenly Father. I get the most out of it when I have a true desire in my heart:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And when ye shall receive these things, I would exhort you that ye would ask God, the Eternal Father, in the name of Christ, if these things are not true; and if ye shall ask with a <strong>sincere heart, with real intent,</strong> having faith in Christ, he will manifest the truth of it unto you, by the power of the Holy Ghost. <a href="../scriptures/moroni-10.4">Moroni 10.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>When I read it in a rush, I don’t get much out of it. When I don’t pray before hand, or if I’m not sincere, I don’t really get anything substantive.</p>
<p>It’s like texting vs calling a friend. If you’re in a rush, you give a half thought text. But if you’re on a long drive and want to build a relationship, you give the friend a call.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-plant-a-seed-and-grow.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">If you plant a seed, you need to nourish it</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The best insight doesn’t come from the Book of Mormon. It comes from the Holy Ghost. So I can read the book as a literary critique and not see its divinity. But as I read it trying to build a relationship with Heavenly Father, then I feel that relationship grow.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Now, we will compare the word unto a seed. Now, if ye give place, that a seed may be <strong>planted in your heart</strong>, behold, if it be a true seed, or a good seed, if ye do not cast it out by your unbelief, that ye will resist the Spirit of the Lord, behold, it will begin to swell within your breasts; and when you feel these swelling motions, ye will begin to say within yourselves—It must needs be that this is a good seed, or that the word is good, for it beginneth to enlarge my soul; yea, it beginneth to enlighten my understanding, yea, it <strong>beginneth to be delicious to me.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/alma-32.28">Alma 32.28</a></p>
</blockquote>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>testimony</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/how-to-use-the-book-of-mormon.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 08:40:59 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hard Work and its Reward</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/hard-work.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>My dad grew up on a sheep farm. And his dad grew up farming too. Same with his dad, all the way back to when dads were a thing.</p>
<p>One of my grand/great grands worked on a beet farm. I read a story once about the beet farmers by Jay Jensen. It was called “Hoe to the end of the row” (apparently there’s a poem with that same title).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-beat-farming.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Beet it, just beet it…</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The principle the author shared was of planting to the end of the row. Some people got lazy and gave up 80% of the way through. But the hard workers went to the end. They took pride in it. And when the harvest came the boss knew who was coming back next summer: those with finished rows.</p>
<p>I’m grateful for hard work. My grandpa told my dad to work with his mind, not his back.<br>
So my dad got a desk job. And so did I.</p>
<p>Perhaps if my grandpa had seen today maybe he would instead say “get off those screens and go plant a beet”. But hard work is hard regardless of it being mental or physical. “Hard work” is the reward itself.</p>
<p>In another quote my father shared with me: “the gift of a good life is having lived it”. Same applies to hard work. The reward of hard work is having done it.</p>
<p>Most of what we do on a daily basis goes unnoticed. The rewards are for ourselves. This is a joy of life.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>gratitude</category>
  <category>perspective</category>
  <category>effort</category>
  <category>life lessons</category>
  <category>memories</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude/hard-work.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 21:33:03 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What startups and musicians have in common</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/what-startups-and-musicians-have-in-common.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I was reminded of a video I watched a while back on YouTube. It was a great documentary about these new artists and their debate about whether to sign a record label (there’s a recent trend to selling music as an independent artist).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-musician-signing-record-label-watercolors.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Putting pen to ink</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I forget all the details, but there are some roughly insane trends that are generally interesting as I recall:</p>
<ul>
<li>new record labels are for $500k give or take. This is so the artist can invest a year into their music and get an album out, pay for production, etc.</li>
<li>many artists at that early stage aren’t financially literate and end up wasting the (they’re musicians, not bankers)</li>
<li>Some have to pay back the money</li>
<li>Up to 85% of the streaming royalties are owed to the label (started when streaming became a thing)</li>
<li>Labels also take a large portion of touring revenues now (something that wasn’t common 10 years ago)</li>
</ul>
<p>Why is this similar to tech startups? Lots.</p>
<p>Musicians have to find product market fit. They need to find their customers. Their monthly listeners.</p>
<p>They need to keep them coming back.</p>
<p>They need to differentiate.</p>
<p>Those who are customer focused and build a following are those who succeed. (Money in the bank and relying too much on the label can cripple you)</p>
<section id="the-musicians-in-town" class="level1">
<h1>The Musicians in Town</h1>
<p>I remember hanging out with some new artists while I was running my startup (we both used the same videographer). I couldn’t help but notice how similar the dynamics were. The founders. The first hires (replacements). The convos about who gets what. It’s all very fascinating.</p>
<p>Not much else to say.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>startups</category>
  <category>music</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/what-startups-and-musicians-have-in-common.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 20:53:53 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The future wave of AI hype</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/the-future-wave-of-ai-hype.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Reading about Airplane’s failure per OnlyCFO. A few notable quotes:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Airplane’s shutdown and future shutdowns like this will have negative consequences for many early stage companies. For many years buyers of these tools haven’t had to deal with a tool being abruptly killed. It only takes this happening once for you to really second guess purchasing a startup tool that is mission critical, deeply integrated, or would take a long time to replace.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/the-future-wave-of-ai-hype.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 20:32:46 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Write a thousand songs</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/write-a-thousand-songs.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I listened to an interview with Imagine Dragons. The lead singer talked about how he writes several songs per day.</p>
<p>No wonder he’s so successful. Repetitions breeds opportunity.</p>
<p>This has two affects on the brain. 1) lowers the pressure of individual songs. Don’t need to knock it of the park. 2) you get better at writing that much faster.</p>
<p>I heard once about a photography that let one half of the students only take 5 photos in a semester. The other half had to take 100. Which group had the better photos?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>You miss 100% of the shots you don’t take. <del>Wayne Gretzky</del> Michael Scott</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-hockey-shots-surreal-impressionist-water.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">More shots is more opportunities for a goal. Worry about good shots later.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>creativity</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/write-a-thousand-songs.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 15:10:01 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>When Leaders Lose their People</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/losing-to-yesmen.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In a scene in <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>, Paul notices that his warrior turns into his worshipper. He laments the loss, wondering if his non-religious warrior will be lost too.</p>
<p>Being a worshipped means you’re worshipped. Unchallenged. Can do no wrong. As such, you’re left with the intellect of one.</p>
<p>As a leader, you need to avoid worshippers. People who fail to challenge you out of fear or an abundance of praise. This all has to do in the decisions you make as a leader. The culture you decide to build. Is every voice heard, or does one voice rule them all?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-king-one-voice-to-rule.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">One voice to rule them all</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/losing-to-yesmen.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 14:31:39 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
