<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 21:43:10 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Turn to God, not your idols</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/turn-to-god-not-your-idols.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I wrote <a href="../christianity/the-power-of-habitual-prayer.html">The Power of Habitual Prayer</a> in the mindset of having intentional prayers. Today, I experienced another one.</p>
<p>I felt overwhelmed by a few things (just day to day life, parenting, working, making sure I get that insurance policy and that bill figured out, etc, etc, etc.)</p>
<p>I decided to see if prayer could help me get out of my funk.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-angels-in-the-crop-fields.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Pray for help in all things, and watch the Hand of the Lord reveal itself</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>During my prayer, I felt something happen. I decided I would pray until I felt a change. And I did. I felt a change. More hope entered in. (“It’s all gonna be fine!”) I felt more grateful for the help I failed to fully appreciate just moments ago.</p>
<p>We get into moods. And bad moods are hard to get out of. But this is life. Life is full of bad moods.</p>
<p>What do you do to fix your bad mood?</p>
<p>This quote came to mind while I was praying:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>As you think celestial, you will find yourself avoiding anything that robs you of your agency. Any addiction—be it gaming, gambling, debt, drugs, alcohol, anger, pornography, sex, or even food﻿—offends God. Why? <strong>Because your obsession becomes your god. You look to it rather than to Him for solace.</strong><br>
<a href="../scriptures/russell-m-nelson-think-celestial">“Think Celestial!”, Russell M. Nelson</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>You don’t need an addiction to appreciate the sentiment here: where do you turn when you’re struggling?</p>
<p>Do you turn to social media? Phone calls? News? The internet? TV? Anger? Food?</p>
<p>I’ve tried all those things. They’re all wonderful (except anger lol), especially calling a friend. But am I doing that before taking the issue to the Lord?</p>
<p>He has invited us to take all things to Him. Every thought even:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Look unto me in <strong><em>every</em></strong> thought; doubt not, fear not.<br>
<a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-6.36">Doctrine and Covenants 6.36</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>And we take all things to Him so He can consecrate them to us:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>ye must <strong>not perform any thing</strong> unto the Lord <strong>save in the first place ye shall pray</strong> unto the Father in the name of Christ, that he will consecrate thy performance unto thee, that thy performance may be for the welfare of thy soul.<br>
<a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-32.9">2 Nephi 32.9</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes, the Lord blesses us even when we don’t pray. But the promise is in the prayer: pray in all things. Pray in every thought. Do all things for Good reasons.</p>
<p>And he didn’t qualify what “labor” means here:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Come unto me, <strong>all ye that labour and are heavy laden, and I will give you rest</strong> Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me; for I am meek and lowly in heart: and ye shall find rest unto your souls. For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light.<br>
<a href="../scriptures/matthew-11.28-30">Matthew 11.28–30</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Perhaps He wants us to decide what our labor is, bring it to Him, and consecrate it and ask His help. This seems aligned with Him wanting us to be agents:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For the power is in them, wherein they are agents unto themselves. And inasmuch as men do good they shall in nowise lose their reward.<br>
<a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-58.28">Doctrine and Covenants 58.28</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>(This comes after “Verily I say, men should be anxiously engaged in a good cause, and do many things of their own free will, and bring to pass much righteousness;” <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-58.27">Doctrine and Covenants 58.27</a>)</p>
<p>So: get an idea of some good cause to be engaged in (parenting, providing for family, etc), pray for support in it, ask Him to consecrate it, watch for miracles.</p>
<p>I think we find reasons for why we <em>shouldn’t</em> pray.<sup>1</sup> Because we think we need to do it on our own. There’s a constant balance between “how much do I rely on God and how much should I just get up and do it myself”. I think the balance is rather not a balance at all. Just pick a plan, ask for help, then go and do what’s in your power. The scriptures are full of examples of people who did this.<sup>2</sup></p>
<p>He loves us. He wants us to succeed. He cares about our daily labor, whether that’s in a field or in the barn that a home turns into. If you’re still wondering, <a href="https://knowhy.bookofmormoncentral.org/knowhy/the-simple-miracle-that-helped-the-whitmers-further-the-book-of-mormon">Read this cool story on David Whitmer and how the Lord helped him with his crops</a> and how the Lord is aware of all our needs, temporal and spiritual.</p>
<p>I got up from my prayer feeling “I can do this!” And the impression came “<em>we</em> can do this”.</p>


<aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>“And now, my beloved brethren, I perceive that ye ponder still in your hearts; and it grieveth me that I must speak concerning this thing. For if ye would hearken unto the Spirit which teacheth a man to pray, ye would know that ye must pray; for the evil spirit teacheth not a man to pray, but teacheth him that he must not pray.” (<a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-32.8">2 Nephi 32.8</a>)↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Nephi and the broken bow, Nephi and the material for the ship, brother of Jared and the stones, etc.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</aside>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>scripture of the day</category>
  <category>prayer</category>
  <category>faith</category>
  <category>consecration</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/turn-to-god-not-your-idols.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 21:43:10 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 11 - Angel shows signs to Nephi</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-11-seeing-signs-of-christ.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Nephi saw a vision because he desired knowledge. Consider the Angel’s instruction:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>7 And behold this thing <strong>shall be given unto thee for a sign</strong>, that after thou hast beheld the tree which bore the fruit which thy father tasted, thou shalt also behold a man descending out of heaven, and him shall ye witness; and after ye have witnessed him ye shall bear record that it is the Son of God. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-11.7">1 Nephi 11.7</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Now, we know that the Lord rebuked the Pharisees for seeking signs:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The Pharisees also with the Sadducees came, and tempting desired him that he would shew them a sign from heaven. He answered and said unto them, When it is evening, ye say, It will be fair weather: for the sky is red. And in the morning, It will be foul weather to day: for the sky is red and lowring. O ye hypocrites, ye can discern the face of the sky; but <strong>can ye not discern the signs of the times?</strong> A <strong>wicked and adulterous generation seeketh after a sign</strong>; and there shall no sign be given unto it, but the sign of the prophet Jonas. And he left them, and departed. <a href="../scriptures/matthew-16.1-4">Matthew 16.1–4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But signs themselves are good. Moses lead by signs: the seven miracles. Baal was trumped by a sign: fire from heaven. Manna in the wilderness. Water from the rock. The fall of the city from trumpets. Oil in the vial.</p>
<p>Any miracle is a sign. A sign that God exists. That He has all power. That Christ is His son.</p>
<p>But today we don’t need to seek for <em>new</em> signs but instead do as the Lord said and “discern the signs of the times”.</p>
<p>By seeking to see His hand, we find the signs.</p>
<p>It’s wicked to seek for a sign, because wicked means “unrepentant”. An unrepentant soul, one who is not going to Heavenly Father and seeking His love, doesn’t see the Hand of God in their life. As a result, they are without his signs (<a href="../concepts/gratus-sum-ergo-habeo.html">Gratus sum, ergo habeo</a>).</p>
<p>So to see signs:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Repent (desire a connection with Heavenly Father and His son)</li>
<li>Look for them (discern)</li>
</ol>
<p>Presto poof.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-moses-raising-a-brass-serpent-watercolor-expressionist.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Why would I believe a new sign if I don’t believe the old signs?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>faith</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-11-seeing-signs-of-christ.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 09:14:07 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2024-01-21 Come Follow Me CTR 7 Jan 15-21 1 Nephi 6-10</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-21-jan-21.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="summary" class="level1">
<h1>Summary</h1>
<p>These chapters teach me:</p>
<ul>
<li>how to overcome adversity (prayer)</li>
<li>Some people never change (Laman and Lemuel)</li>
<li>People who don’t like the message usually reject it and denounce it (Laman and Lemuel)</li>
<li>The love of God is accessible to all</li>
<li>The Lord invites all, even if He knows they won’t listen</li>
<li>Those who come can fully appreciate the beauty of the Lord’s love</li>
<li>If you take your eyes off the Savior, and care what people think instead, you can feel shame which can drive you to leave Him</li>
<li>The scriptures are written with a specific purpose: they don’t know. They’re doing what the Lord wants them to do.</li>
<li>The Lord will teach those about the Tree of Life who want to know about it. Nephi wasn’t any more special than anyone else. He just wanted to know.</li>
<li>The Lord works through prophets. Through the priesthood.</li>
<li>Perhaps Lehi could have been more gentle with Laman and Lemuel. But Nephi <em>did</em> mention the “tender feelings” that Lehi had for them, so maybe Laman and Lemuel just didn’t get it</li>
<li>There’s a little bit of Laman and Lemuel and Nephi and Sam and Lehi and Sariah in all of us.</li>
<li>Over time, the prophecies are revealed and fulfilled.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-1-nephi-610-summary.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="The image generated by GPT from the above bullets"> # Studies</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-6-god-of-the-covenant.html">1 Nephi 6 - God of the Covenant</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-7-commitment.html">1 Nephi 7 - Make a Choice, Don’t go Halvsies</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-8-what-others-think.html">1 Nephi 8 - Think for yourself</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-9-write-with-a-purpose.html">1 Nephi 9 - Write with a Purpose</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-10-rely-on-the-redeemer.html">1 Nephi 10 - Rely on the Redeemer</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="activity-ideas" class="level1">
<h1>Activity Ideas</h1>
<ul>
<li>“let me see” (<a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-11.1.html">1 Nephi 11.1</a>) - show a video to one kid, have him share or try to draw it. Have others try to understand. They just have to see for themselves.</li>
<li>Iron rod activity: blindfold.</li>
</ul>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me lesson plan</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-21-jan-21.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 23:34:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Receive the Holy Ghost</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/receive-the-holy-ghost.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today at church someone was confirmed a member of the Church after having been baptized yesterday. This taught me something new about the sacrament and the covenant we make with Him every week.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-receive-the-holy-ghostXimage-the-resurrected-christ-in-white-laying-both-of-his-hands-on-the-heads-of-one-person-water-colors-peaceful--inside-focus-on-the-savior-phase-out-other-things-impressionist.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Receive the Holy Ghost</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="entry-into-his-church-by-baptism" class="level1">
<h1>Entry into His Church by Baptism</h1>
<p>After baptism, we receive the gift of the Holy Ghost:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>But now I give unto thee a commandment, that thou shalt baptize by water, and they shall receive the Holy Ghost by the laying on of the hands, even as the apostles of old. <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-35.6">Doctrine and Covenants 35.6</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>There is precedence for this, as the Savior gave the gift of the Holy Ghost to his apostles after he was no longer tarrying with them:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And when he had said this, he breathed on them, and saith unto them, Receive ye the Holy Ghost: <a href="../scriptures/john-20.22">John 20.22</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Pausing on that thought for a moment, let’s consider the last sentence in the sacrament prayer on the bread:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>that they may <strong>always</strong> have his Spirit to be with them. <a href="../scriptures/moroni-4.3">Moroni 4.3</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Also consider that the last of the water prayer omits that word “always”:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>that they may have his Spirit to be with them. <a href="../scriptures/moroni-5.2">Moroni 5.2</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Are they contradictory? No.&nbsp;Because the full last sentence of the water prayer says:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>that they do <strong>always</strong> remember him, that they may have his Spirit to be with them. <a href="../scriptures/moroni-5.2">Moroni 5.2</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This tells us that if we always remember him (the Savior), we’ll have His spirit to be with us.</p>
<p>Back to the New Teatament. The Lord taught His disciples that the comforter would come to them <em>once He left</em>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Nevertheless I tell you the truth; It is expedient for you that I go away: for if I go not away, the Comforter will not come unto you; but if I depart, I will send him unto you. <a href="../scriptures/john-16.7">John 16.7</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>And in a prior chapter, Jesus had instructed that this was the plan - that he would give them the gift of the Comforter when He was gone. Notice the word “another”:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And I will pray the Father, and he shall give you <em>another</em> Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever; Even the Spirit of truth; whom the world cannot receive, because it seeth him not, neither knoweth him: but ye know him; for he dwelleth with you, and shall be in you. I will not leave you comfortless: I will come to you. <a href="../scriptures/john-14.16-18">John 14.16–18</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Perhaps He said “another” Comforter because He is the first?</p>
<p>He further promised the role of the Holy Ghost is to teach of truth and testify of the Savior:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>But when the Comforter is come, whom I will send unto you from the Father, even the Spirit of truth, which proceedeth from the Father, he shall testify of me: <a href="../scriptures/john-15.26">John 15.26</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Lord also explained how He works with the Holy Ghost. It appears that, because the Savior was with them, He was their source of truth. But as He was planning to leave them He needed to leave them with a source of truth. As such, they were being prepared to receive the gift of the Holy Ghost:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>These things have I spoken unto you, <strong>being yet present with you.</strong> But the Comforter, which is the Holy Ghost, whom the Father will send in my name, he shall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, whatsoever I have said unto you. <a href="../scriptures/john-14.25-26">John 14.25–26</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This doesn’t mean they didn’t have the spirit - how else could Peter have received His spiritual witness of the Savior? <a href="../scriptures/matthew-16.15-17.html">matthew-16.15-17</a></p>
<p>What do these scriptures all teach me?</p>
<ul>
<li>If we always remember the Savior, we’ll have His spirit to be with us</li>
<li>His spirit teaches us what is truth: it testifies of Christ</li>
<li>He gave this gift because we can’t always be in His presence.</li>
<li>Even if we were in His presence, we’d need the spirit to let us know that He is the Christ</li>
<li>When we receive the Holy Ghost after baptism, we are commanded to “receive the Holy Ghost” by confirmation into the church.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="what-is-the-gift-of-the-holy-ghost" class="level1">
<h1>What is the “gift” of the Holy Ghost?</h1>
<p>This last one is powerful, because of a clarifying point in the handbook of the church:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>States “receive the Holy Ghost” (not “receive the gift of the Holy Ghost”).<br>
<a href="../scriptures/18.-performing-priesthood-ordinances-and-blessings">18. Performing Priesthood Ordinances and Blessings</a></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Or, the “gift” of the Holy Ghost perhaps isn’t a thing like the priesthood - something bestowed upon us. (This is something I’ve thought it was my whole life - a gift I receive.) why aren’t we told to receive the gift of the Holy Ghost?</p>
<p>What, then, is legally binding about the Lord’s covenant? And what is the “gift of the Holy Ghost” as mentioned in the scriptures? (<a href="../scriptures/articles-of-faith-1.4">Articles of Faith 1.4</a>, <a href="../scriptures/moses-5.58">Moses 5.58</a>, <a href="../scriptures/jacob-6.8">Jacob 6.8</a>, <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-39.23">Doctrine and Covenants 39.23</a>, <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-49.14">Doctrine and Covenants 49.14</a>, <a href="../scriptures/acts-10.45">Acts 10.45</a>, and like 4 other references…it’s referenced in every standard work!)</p>
<p>Even the Lord says he’ll bestow the gift of the Holy Ghost:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And whoso having faith you shall confirm in my church, by the laying on of the hands, and <strong>I will bestow the gift of the Holy Ghost upon them</strong>. <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-33.15">Doctrine and Covenants 33.15</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Because we don’t “receive the gift of the Holy Ghost”, perhaps the <em>gift</em> of the Holy Ghost is instead the <em>promised blessing of the constant companionship</em> as a <em>result</em> of keeping our covenant. Things consistent with the definitions in the Guide to the Scriptures:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>It is the right of every worthy baptized member of the Church to have the constant influence of the Holy Ghost</strong>. Following a person’s baptism into the true Church of Jesus Christ, he receives the gift of the Holy Ghost by the laying on of hands from one who has the proper authority <a href="../scriptures/gift-of-the-holy-ghost">Gift of the Holy Ghost</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Anyone on earth can enjoy the Holy Ghost. It teaches those of truth. But only those of the covenant of baptism, who keep that covenant and the <a href="../concepts/sacrament-covenant.html">Sacrament Covenant</a> (To always remember Him, keep His commandments, and take His name upon us), are blessed <em>always</em> with His spirit. Things the gift of the Holy Ghost: its constant companionship.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>While someone is being confirmed a member of the Church, he or she is told to “receive the Holy Ghost.” The gift of the Holy Ghost is not forced on anyone. <strong>It becomes the responsibility of members to invite the Holy Ghost to be with them</strong> <a href="../scriptures/gift-of-the-holy-ghost">Gift of the Holy Ghost</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>And perhaps the ordinance of the confirmation is to start that covenant: “receive the Holy Ghost now, and always as you remember Me.”</p>
<p>And why do we always want His spirit to be with us? Because the spirit is a proxy for Him: the Comforter, the Source of Truth, the Light and Life of the World. When we have that spirit, we are of the Kingdom of Heaven (on earth).</p>
<p>So when I take the sacrament every week, I’m making the covenant to always remember Him so that I can enjoy the <em>gift</em> of <em>receiving</em> the Holy Ghost always.</p>
<hr>
<p>Why is this relevant to me personally?</p>
<ul>
<li>the <em>gift</em> isn’t some separate power that I can offend or please. It’s not some separate God. Instead, the gift is a covenant. This changes my focus away from a relationship with the Holy Ghost and instead a relationship with the Savior. The purpose of the holy ghost is to point me to the Savior. And if I’m not feeling the spirit, it’s not about trying to please the Holy Ghost - I just need to begin remembering the savior in that moment.</li>
</ul>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>sacrament-symbols</category>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/receive-the-holy-ghost.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 10:41:50 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 8 - Press Forward Continually</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/choosing-to-press-forward.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Obtaining the love of Christ is not easy:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I beheld others pressing forward, and they came forth and caught hold of the end of the rod of iron; and they did press forward through the mist of darkness, clinging to the rod of iron, even until they did come forth and partake of the fruit of the tree. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-8.24">1 Nephi 8.24</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Now, He loves us unconditionally. But it is up to us to come to Him.</p>
<p>He constantly invites us to come to Him, and because He gives us agency (<a href="../christianity/stop-trying-to-change-people.html">Stop trying to change people. Stop it.</a>), we have to choose to follow Him.</p>
<p>This choice isn’t an easy one. It’s a difficult one. Some of us get tired and let go. Or we get distracted by all there is around us. Whatever the case - God’s love for us is constant. It’s there. It’s available. It’s at the tree. It’s felt through meaningful prayer (<a href="../christianity/the-power-of-habitual-prayer.html">The Power of Habitual Prayer</a>). It’s felt through studying His words. It’s by building a relationship that we come to Him. It’s hard work, but it’s the way we experience the delicious fruit.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-the-tree-of-light.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The tree of life is also the tree of light. Always there</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>love</category>
  <category>love of God</category>
  <category>agency</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/choosing-to-press-forward.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2024 23:41:36 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 10 - Rely on the Redeemer</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-10-rely-on-the-redeemer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As people, we are consistently imperfect:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wherefore, all mankind were in a lost and in a fallen state, and ever would be save they should rely on this Redeemer. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-10.6">1 Nephi 10.6</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The blessing of this imperfection is a constant reminder that to become who we need to, we need to rely on the Savior.</p>
<p>This isn’t a one-time thing. Perhaps it’s like walking up a slippery hill. There are grips on our knee pads, but not on our shoes.</p>
<p>Kneel in prayer to rely on the Redeemer.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-ascend-the-hill-by-kneeling-in-prayer.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The only way up is down on your knees</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-10-rely-on-the-redeemer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2024 00:07:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 9 - Write with a Purpose</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-9-write-with-a-purpose.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The Book of Mormon has a purpose:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I have received a commandment of the Lord that I should make these plates, for the special purpose that there should be an account engraven of the ministry of my people. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-9.3">1 Nephi 9.3</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/img/dalle-writing-on-gold-plates.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Write with a purpose. Journal with a purpose.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Then the other plates had a different purpose:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>the other plates are for the more part of the reign of the kings and the wars and contentions of my people. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-9.4">1 Nephi 9.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>What purpose does my writing have? What is the purpose of this blog?</p>
<p>When we write, it helps to have a purpose. It guides the writing. How does writing for entertainment differ from writing to try to change someone’s life by inviting them to Christ? The Book of Mormon is written for the later.</p>
<p>Let us write. Write with a purpose.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-9-write-with-a-purpose.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 23:59:57 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Power of Habitual Prayer</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/the-power-of-habitual-prayer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I want to share my experience with how prayer has turned from not very meaningful to substantively helpful in a matter of a few short weeks.</p>
<p>Consider the scene:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Children jumping on beds. Refusing to get dressed or brush their teeth or go to the bathroom. Screaming from the other room. Screaming from this room. Exhausted after a long day. I just want things to change and be different.<sup>1</sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Any parent comes across this more than once per day.</p>
<p>Most of last year I felt like I wasn’t getting a whole lot out of my prayers. A few comments:</p>
<ul>
<li>I try praying daily. But I found it hard to focus. Praying out loud helps with this, but I didn’t do it often.</li>
<li>even though I felt my prayers not well focused, I do believe God heard them regardless and by praying in an unfocused state I could still get <em>something</em> out of the experience. I believe God looks down on us when we’re trying, rather ineffectually, to do our best</li>
<li>I felt like my prayers were ineffective because I’d pray and mumble and think about work until I’d come back to me being in a prayer and then I’d say Amen. I’d always wondered what my experience would be like if I really felt a connection to God.</li>
</ul>
<p>Okay. So that’s last year. Lots of prayers. I know God loves me regardless of how effective they are. And I know they could be better.</p>
<p>Back to the scene. There were several times last year when the kids were nuts and I needed to calm myself down. It was hard. I tried a few times to go and pray but just felt like “it’s not working!” Im praying! Why can’t I get to a better state of mind?! This prayer thing isn’t working for me and I’m doing it wrong.</p>
<p>I never felt like prayer wasn’t good or useful. Just that I couldn’t get it to do what I wanted it to do for me: fix me. I figured: maybe I need to pray differently. Or try XYZ thing.</p>
<p>Okay, so throw up a prayer and hope it sticks. Change me! I’m here.</p>
<p>Nope. Didn’t work. I’d still be struggling with patience in those circumstances.</p>
<p>Last night I had a new experience. I <em>did</em> pray the same way I’ve prayed before when stressed. No, I didn’t get fixed - God doesn’t fix us like that. Instead, while praying I remembered a mindset <a href="../christianity/find-the-fun.html">Find the Fun</a> that I had discovered last week. That’s all that came to mind. I left the prayer still agitated because a kid was about to jump on another kid while I was praying and I had to leave the prayer.</p>
<p>What happened though? I was just like 20% less stressed as I tried focusing on <a href="../christianity/find-the-fun.html">Find the Fun</a>.</p>
<p>Okay, so the night went better than it did last week. I had something in my mind to hold on to.</p>
<p>What’s the difference between the me yesterday and the me of three weeks ago? I changed my relationship with prayer.</p>
<p>I’ve been trying to have just one good prayer per day. It’s a goal for this year. And a good prayer is one where I try to get some type of insight. Like meditation. Just pray until an insight. Setting a timer helps me. Doing it in my office or a place where I’m alone helps too. And when I’m done, I write down the insight.</p>
<p>Most of the time the insight isn’t like from God or anything. I don’t hear a voice. I don’t have any mental image. The insight for me usually comes from me hearing myself pray. “Oh, I didn’t realize that was on my mind” or “oh, how did I think of that?” I’ve come to learn that this is a spiritual prayer. This <em>is</em> praying by the spirit. When I desire to connect with God (get something out of my prayer), I’m elevated ever so slightly (<a href="../gratitude/small-things.html">I’m grateful for small things</a>).</p>
<p>And that’s it: I’ve been doing this for about two or weeks now and my relationship with prayer is changing. I no longer want it to fix me. I see it as a way to try to connect with heaven in a small way.</p>
<p>And that’s the realization: the power of prayer isn’t in the hail Mary’s. It’s in the consistent relationship with it.</p>
<p>I <em>do</em> believe a Hail Mary is better than no Hail. So hail away.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And now the Lord was slow to hear their cry because of their iniquities; <strong>nevertheless the Lord did hear their cries</strong> <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-21.15">Mosiah 21.15</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Lord hears your cries even if you’re wicked. Pray regardless. But there is a concept of Him being slow to hear at times: feeling the effect of prayer requires consistency. But he’s happy to help any time we come to Him. He’s not vindictive. He’s not “I told you so” or “you should be coming to me more often than this”. That’s how we treat each other, with pride. God isn’t like that. Heavenly Father wants us to come to him, and he’ll hear our cries.</p>
<p>Translating this to me: i wasn’t wicked or anything. I was just a stressed out dad. But I think the principle applies: if I have a lackluster relationship with prayer then he’ll be slow to hear. Or, said another way, <em>I’ll</em> be slow to hear. Slow to see. More reactive. More knee jerky and less patient. More thinking “why doesn’t this prayer thing work for me?”</p>
<p>So that’s my insight. Make prayer meaningful and it starts to pay dividends slowly. Very slowly. But I also believe in compounding interest.</p>
<p>if your investments gain 0.1% each day of the year, do you know what your returns would be over a year? 44% increase. So if you invest $100 today, by the end of the year you’ll have $144 if you keep reinvesting your returns. Thats insanely good! But that’s math. that’s compounding interest.<sup>2</sup></p>
<p>So shoot for a 0.1% prayer. That’s all it’s gotta be to get massive returns.</p>
<p>So that’s the invitation: try to make prayer meaningful (whatever that means to <em>you</em>, not me). And try to do it consistently.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>But this is not all; ye must pour out your souls in your closets, and your secret places, and in your wilderness. <a href="../scriptures/alma-34.26">Alma 34.26</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-pray-in-your-wilderness.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Pray alone in your wilderness. Find somewhere.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


<aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>while writing this the insight came: I’m in the state of mind of wanting them to change. This is a mindset of control (<a href="../christianity/stop-trying-to-change-people.html">Stop trying to change people. Stop it.</a>). The fallacy a mind believes is “if only they’re better I’d be at more peace”. Consider the alternative: if they were peaceful but I’m still in a mindset of control. Would I be happier? Perhaps I would feel more comfortable (less noise in my ear). But I’m going to posit that a person in a mindset of control, regardless of whether they’re being listened to and their control is being obeyed, aren’t happy and aren’t mindful. They aren’t present with what is. A healthier mindset for me might be: “anything could happen, delightful that they’re food now, but it’s okay if they misbehave. They’re kids! How can I <a href="../christianity/find-the-fun.html">Find the Fun</a> in this moment?”↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>The math is this: 1.001^365=1.44. Or, your daily return is 1.001. Invest $10 and you’ll have $10.01 by the end of day one. Invest $10.01 on day two and gain 0.1% and you’ll have $10.02001 by end of day two. Do this 365 times and you’ll have $10*1.001^365=$14.40↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</aside>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>my testimony</category>
  <category>personal stories</category>
  <category>prayer</category>
  <category>scripture of the day</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>featured</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/the-power-of-habitual-prayer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 09:09:36 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 8 - Think for yourself</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-8-what-others-think.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This is an interesting scripture:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>and they were in the attitude of mocking and pointing their fingers towards those who had come at and were partaking of the fruit. And after they had tasted of the fruit they were ashamed, because of those that were scoffing at them; and they fell away into forbidden paths and were lost. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-8.27-28">1 Nephi 8.27–28</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Imagine you’re eating at a Michelin star restaurant and across the street there’s a food court at the mall with a bunch of people eating McDonalds and Burger King. And <em>they’re</em> mocking <em>you</em>.</p>
<p>Reasons this relationship is so fascinating:</p>
<ul>
<li>the people in the building don’t know what the tree tastes like.</li>
<li>The people in the building are far away.</li>
<li>The people eating the fruit are able to be numbed by the perceptions of others, and aren’t focusing on their own experience.</li>
</ul>
<p>If those who became ashamed had focused instead on their own experiences it would have been delicious.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-lehi-dream.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Lehi’s dream</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-8-what-others-think.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 00:23:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 7 - Make a Choice, Don’t go Halvsies</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-7-commitment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="nephi-7" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>1 Nephi 7</h1>
<p>This exchange is fascinating:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Now behold, I say unto you that if ye will return unto Jerusalem ye shall also perish with them. <strong>And now, if ye have choice, go up to the land, and remember the words which I speak unto you, that if ye go ye will also perish;</strong> for thus the Spirit of the Lord constraineth me that I should speak.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Laman and Lemuel don’t want to be in the wilderness, but when Nephi tells them they have their agency, they’re not brave enough to go back to Jerusalem.</p>
<p>In other words, he catches them in their rouse. “Nobody’s forcing you”, go back if you want, but if you do you’ll remember that you’re going to die there.</p>
<p>How often do we like to complain about something but not actually do anything about it? Reminds me of the quote “So then because thou art lukewarm, and neither cold nor hot, I will spue thee out of my mouth.” (<a href="../scriptures/revelation-3.16">Revelation 3.16</a>)</p>
<p>If you don’t want to do anything about it, don’t complain. Vote with your feet, not your mouth. (They were voting with their feet to leave Jerusalem but voting with their mounts against it.)</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-walking-away.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">If you’re gonna walk, walk. If you’re gonna follow the prophet, follow.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>16 And it came to pass that when I, Nephi, had spoken these words unto my brethren, they were angry with me. And it came to pass that they did lay their hands upon me, for behold, they were exceedingly wroth, and they did bind me with cords, for they sought to take away my life, <strong>that they might leave me in the wilderness to be devoured by wild beasts.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-7.15-16">1 Nephi 7.15–16</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Also interesting is how they didn’t directly want to kill Nephi (didn’t have the courage here to try), but instead just decided to leave him to die (Joseph of Egypt style).</p>
<p>This is one of those “I’m not actually sinning because I didn’t do the sin” things. Tying someone up isn’t killing them. Should they die, that’s an unfortunate derivative consequence. But <em>we</em> didn’t kill him. <sup>1</sup></p>
<p>Backing up to a higher point: how often do we skirt the issue and not take full accountability? They can’t go back to Jerusalem and they can’t even properly attempt murder. They’re just lazy and without conviction all around.</p>
<p>But so are we. We all have these tendencies to disassociate from accountability for our life:</p>
<ul>
<li>well X person is annoying. “Are you going to talk to them?” No…</li>
<li>Etc…</li>
</ul>
<p>Own up. # Other Verses of Interest</p>
<p>Today I liked these verses:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wherefore, the things which are pleasing unto the world I do not write, but the things <strong>which are pleasing unto God and unto those who are not of the world.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-6.5">1 Nephi 6.5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Am I someone who is not of this world? Fascinating question because it makes me wonder what is “the world”. What was Nephibtrying to define here? Perhaps he was summarizing in his own way that those who have their head in the spiritual clouds will love these things, while those who live by “the world” won’t. It’s also reflective of his experience trying to share the gospel that some people don’t care. They just want to enjoy the pineapples and what not. Am I distracted by money, fame, greed, envy?</p>
<hr>
<p>I also got a little ahead and listened to this scripture:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For it came to pass after <strong>I had desired to know the things that my father had seen, and believing that the Lord was able to make them known unto me</strong>, as I sat pondering in mine heart I was caught away in the Spirit of the Lord, yea, into an exceedingly high mountain, which I never had before seen, and upon which I never had before set my foot. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-11.1">1 Nephi 11.1</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>My kids love to come up to my phone and say “let me see!!!” If they hear audio in another room they come sprinting.</p>
<p>Why do kids love seeing? They want to see. They’re sponges. They’re also without much experience in life so they want to see it all! Make up for lost time…</p>
<p>To become like a little child is to want to see for ourselves.</p>


</section>
<aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>They were living the Old law. Perhaps this was legal. But the law of the heart says: this is attempted murder.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</aside>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>commitment</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <category>epistemology</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-7-commitment.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 23:34:11 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 6 - God of the Covenant</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-6-god-of-the-covenant.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Nephi introduces the concept of the “God of Abraham” in the Book of Mormon:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For the fulness of mine intent is that I may persuade men to come unto the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, and be saved. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-6.4">1 Nephi 6.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Why? Well, repetition helps us remember. Calling out multiple names also tells us that there were several generations of believers. Also, many people are descendants of these folks so using their name invokes their ancestry. These are three reasons why Nephi (and others) may use this triple threat to identify the God we can worship.</p>
<p>But I think there’s one more reason: the God of the Old Testament is Jesus. He’s the god is the covenant. The covenant of Abraham in which all seeds of the earth shall be blessed. God of Isaac and Jacob - who also received more covenants.</p>
<p>When we worship a God of covenants, we become empowered by those covenants.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>scripture of the day</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-6-god-of-the-covenant.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 23:56:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 5 - Will a promise be delivered?</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-5-trusting-a-promise.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Lehi and his wife Sariah are at base camp while their boys are trying to get the plates (ancient record/scriptures) from a ruthless Laban. Sariah gets very nervous (v1-3), perhaps thinking they’ve been killed.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-weary-wanderer-waiting.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Waiting in the wilderness</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Then once she sees them come back (mission accomplished) she rejoices:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And she spake, saying: Now I know of a surety that the Lord hath commanded my husband to flee into the wilderness; yea, and I also know of a surety that the Lord hath protected my sons, and delivered them out of the hands of Laban, and given them power whereby they could accomplish the thing which the Lord hath commanded them. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.8">1 Nephi 5.8</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But what if they hadn’t come back? Is this just confirmation bias?</p>
<p>No.&nbsp;</p>
<p>See, Sariah had been promised her sons safe return:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>and I know that the Lord will deliver my sons out of the hands of Laban, and bring them down again unto us in the wilderness. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.5">1 Nephi 5.5</a> (Lehi talking)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Because of this (a specific promise), we often fixate in contrary to the exact thing we should be expecting.</p>
<p>Consider Adam and Eve: don’t eat that one tree. Eat anything else. Everything else. Just not that one. → which one?<sup>1</sup> this one? Oh, we ate it.</p>
<p>Perhaps Sariah fixates on her sons not returning because that is what a prophet promised her.</p>
<p>Interestingly, there must be a space in time between when a promise is made and a promise is delivered (<a href="../scriptures/alma-40.6-9">see Alma 40.6–9</a> for similar logic). We are not told the length of that in between time. Could be today. Could be tomorrow. Who knows how long Sariah was waiting.</p>
<p>An interesting corollary: she wasn’t doubting something she <em>wasn’t</em> promised.</p>
<p>Consider all the promises in the scriptures. Abraham is promised the gospel will be in his seed. Nephi is promised his seed will be destroyed (he was the righteous one) and Laman and Lemuel were implicitly promised their seed would remain (even though they were wicked). Joseph of Egypt promised some things, Enos is promised other things, etc. We’re all unique.</p>
<p>Let’s consider Peter and John. The Lord offered them whatever they wanted. John wanted to tarry on earth and Peter wanted to be done with the earth and go to heaven. Peter seems to have gotten tiffed with John because John one-upped Peter on the righteous desires contest with Jesus as the Judge:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And for this cause the Lord said unto Peter: If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee? <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-7.4">Doctrine and Covenants 7.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>(The savior goes on to explain how both Peter and John’s desires were great.<sup>2</sup>)</p>
<p>Back to Sariah - here are three ways we tend to worry:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>we can worry about things promised to us. We’re just rarely promised a timeline. Trust. Wait. And see.</li>
<li>Where we aren’t promised anything, we have nothing to think of or worry about.</li>
<li>We may individually be promised different things. The path of everyone is unique.</li>
</ol>
<p>But we’re all promised eternal life if we follow the Lord (eternal happiness):</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Verily I say unto you, ye shall both have according to your desires, for ye both joy in that which ye have desired. <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-7.8">Doctrine and Covenants 7.8</a></p>
</blockquote>


<aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>im being funny here, because there’s a lot more to the Adam and Eve story - they were supposed to eat it. Point is: we focus on what we’re told not to do.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>side note: the Lord doesn’t compare Peter against John. He just says “John wanted to do more than what <em>he</em> has previously done.” “I say unto thee, Peter, this was a good desire; but my beloved has desired that he might do more, or a greater work yet among men than what he has before done. Yea, he has undertaken a greater work; therefore I will make him as flaming fire and a ministering angel; he shall minister for those who shall be heirs of salvation who dwell on the earth.” <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-7.5-6">Doctrine and Covenants 7.5–6</a>↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</aside>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>faith</category>
  <category>covenant</category>
  <category>individual covenant</category>
  <category>promised blessings</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-5-trusting-a-promise.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 22:59:28 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Church Culture of Missionary work</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/sacrament-talk-on-missionary-work.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A friend gave a talk in church about missionary work, which is the Lord’s invitation to share His gospel and good news with the world. Having been a missionary for two years, it’s much less about “effective sales” strategies and much more about trying to live like a good person and invite others to enjoy the benefits of following Christ.</p>
<p>I bring up the point about sales because a lot of people outside of the church can see LDS missionaries as salespeople. To one degree, they are: they’re trying to change people’s belief system. Adopt Christianity. <sup>1</sup></p>
<p>Yea, that’s certainly a reasonable way to look at it from one angle. But the reality is more like “I have something that’s great and I want other people to benefit from it the same way I benefit from it”. Or better said: there’s so much…misinformation about my church and Christianity in general, how do I have a productive conversation with you about it without knowing where you are? I’d love to talk to you about it, but are you deeply inwardly vehemently against it for some obtuse reason I’m not aware of? That’s what provoked some fear in sharing His good news.</p>
<p>But these fears aren’t warranted. Because that isn’t the right focus from my end. The best focus for “missionary work” is: if I have something that’s great in my life, I should share it like anything else great in my life.</p>
<p>Did I see a good movie over the weekend? Great, share it. Did i hear a great talk on Sunday at church? Great, share it. Did I have a good hike? Awesome, share it. Did I have a funny experience while teaching some kids on Sunday? Yea, dope. Share it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-orange-juice-rainforest.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Mind if I drink this? Oh, you’d like some? I didn’t want to offend you by offering but sure I’d love to share - Elder Uchtdorf analogy paraphrased</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<p>Things I liked from my friends talk:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Over the past several months, (my wife) and I have implemented a new fad into our lives in an attempt to improve our well-being, which is the practice of cold plunging. Some of you may have heard of this trend as many gurus talk about it on social media because of its benefits, such as reducing stress and mood enhancement. Cold plunging is submerging your body in very cold water (typically around 50 degrees) for a period of 3 to 6 minutes. Sounds absolutely terrible, right? Well, it is terrible! No matter how many times we do it, it is still very hard and very uncomfortable. Nonetheless, we continue to do it, almost every day, because of the way it makes us feel afterwards. Immediately after getting out of the water I feel alert, energized and confident I can tackle the tasks of the day. Sitting in that cold water is always uncomfortable, but the discomfort is always worth it. <strong>By having felt what’s on the other side, I can get comfortable with the uncomfortable.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This cold plunge analogy is interesting: because it’s always hard. Always intimidating. I think that’s true in my personal experience. But for me it’s more like… the opposite of hyperextending my knee.</p>
<p>When I was in high school I got a knee injury. I hyperextended it. The first time was incredibly painful. I was out a few days. But then I came back and was fine-ish. Then a few weeks later I did it again. Then a few days later: again. By the end of the season, I was hyperextending it every other day. It was bad news. A few weeks after the season ended I was playing in a bball tournament and again big hyperextending.</p>
<p>I stopped playing sports that summer and let myself heal up. Haven’t had problems since.</p>
<p>Same with sharing the gospel, but the opposite. At first it’s really intimidating. You do it once and you realize it’s not that bad. Then the more you do it the more it becomes part of your day.</p>
<p>Kinda like writing in this blog. At first I’m trying to find my voice. Now I don’t care and just want to write. I hope it’s beneficial for you.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>On the other hand, some may be thinking none of those sound any easier and maybe you sometimes feel that you aren’t contributing because missionary work is generally intimidating and uncomfortable to you. That is OKAY. <strong>All efforts, no matter how small, are important and impactful.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This reminded me of <a href="../concepts/president-russel-m-nelson.html">President Russel M. Nelson</a>’s invitation:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Anytime you do anything that helps anyone—on either side of the veil﻿—take a step toward making covenants with God and receiving their essential baptismal and temple ordinances, you are helping to gather Israel. It is as simple as that. <a href="../scriptures/hope-of-israel">Hope of Israel</a></p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>As a missionary in (Some Area) I had one mission president for my first year and another for my second year. Both presidents elevated the success of the mission with different approaches and leadership styles. In my first year under my first mission president, the mission accomplished a big goal of doubling the number of baptisms from the previous year. During this time our mission president wasn’t fond of us spending too much time with members and our success came from focusing on other areas of the work. By contrast, my second mission president changed the culture and encouraged us to spend as much time with the members as we could, even if we did not have someone to teach with the members. He taught us to focus on the number of lessons with a member participating as the most important key indicator. As a result, the mission’s baptisms started to skyrocket and the number more than doubled again. I know that our success can be attributed to us striving to have as many members as possible participating in our lessons and our emphasis on members and missionaries working together.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If your note a member of the church you may balk at “baptism skyrocketing”. It kinda gives a cultish vibe if that’s how you see it - our goal is to baptize everyone!! I get it. Not great language from the outsider’s perspective <em>if</em> that’s how you see it.</p>
<p>Having been a member of the church my whole life, I’ve heard this rhetoric a lot - get baptisms. But I think this is more of a sociological misrepresentation of a deeply inward desire to share what’s good in your life with others.</p>
<p>Do I want to baptize the world? Umm…do I want everyone to have world peace? Yea.</p>
<p>Will baptizing someone give them peace? No.&nbsp;Well, not <em>just</em> dunking yourself in a hot-tub sized mini pool.</p>
<p>Will someone who has a sincere desire to follow Christ the rest of their life benefit from being baptized because it gives them a chance to publicly commit to following Christ and thus be supported by a community of like-minded people also trying to self-improve constantly? Yea. Baptism would be great here.</p>
<p>Do I want to baptize everyone? No.&nbsp;I <em>would</em> love it if everyone desired to follow Jesus a little more in their life. Learn a little more about him. So, yea I want everyone to be baptized.</p>
<p>This is the spirit which my friend is describing.</p>
<p>So doubling baptisms is this notion of a very fascinating cultural experience: we have as a church more success in helping other people discover the joy of following Christ by <em>how</em> we package “the message”. Yea, it’s sales at some level. What’s a better strategy? Cold calling or referrals? Always referrals. There’s trust there. The product doesn’t seem as strange. Likewise, it takes a lot to change a set of religious beliefs. Having seen someone you know and enjoy associating with benefit from the religion helps make it more palatable at first to begin discussions.</p>
<p>Lastly, this strategy is fascinating: focus on teaching people who already believe in God about <em>why</em> they believe in God, or more about His story. These refreshers help enliven the mind, no different than perhaps me going back to some Stat 121 material and just really appreciating its elegance (even though I do more advanced math in my day to day). Teach people the basics and they’ll remember what they love about it.</p>
<hr>
<p>End/rant.</p>


<aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>From the ultra cynical: “they just want more tithing!” But, like, if you think about it this argument doesn’t work in so many ways. Mainly that the missionaries are paying to be there (don’t get any tithing) and most of tithing goes to maintaining the church (buildings, books, temples, missions, etc).↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</aside>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>opinion</category>
  <category>lds culture</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/sacrament-talk-on-missionary-work.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 21:05:30 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Architecture Reminds Me of His Cross</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/support-beams-represent-the-cross.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today I noticed the wooden beams supporting the roof of my chapel building.</p>
<p>Christ is our foundation. He’s our rock. But he also carried the cross up the hill. People looked up to him in His last moments.</p>
<p>Likewise this beam above me can represent His ascension above the cross. It can also remind me to take up His cross.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-wooden-beam-church.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Wooden beams</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>24 Then said Jesus unto his disciples, If any man will come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me. 25 For whosoever will save his life shall lose it: and whosoever will lose his life for my sake shall find it. 26 For what is a man profited, if he shall gain the whole world, and lose his own soul? or what shall a man give in exchange for his soul? <a href="../scriptures/matthew-16.24-26">Matthew 16.24–26</a></p>
</blockquote>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>sacrament symbol</category>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>scripture of the day</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/support-beams-represent-the-cross.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 15:51:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 4 - Why not?</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-4-why-not.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Nephi asks a faith-opening question:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>for behold he is mightier than all the earth, <strong>then why not mightier than</strong> Laban and his fifty, yea, or even than his tens of thousands? <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-4.1">1 Nephi 4.1</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>As I wrote in <a href="../christianity/unknown-god.html">An Unknown God</a>, Nephi demonstrates the ability to find a way with his questioning. Instead of asking doubtfully, he asks faithfully.</p>
<p>It reminds me of Enoch:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>31 And when Enoch had heard these words, he bowed himself to the earth, before the Lord, and spake before the Lord, saying: <strong>Why is it that I have found favor in thy sight</strong>, and am but a lad, and all the people hate me; for I am slow of speech; wherefore am I thy servant? 32 And the Lord said unto Enoch: <strong>Go forth and do</strong> as I have commanded thee, and no man shall pierce thee. <a href="../scriptures/moses-6.31-32">Moses 6.31–32</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Lord didn’t tell him why he was chosen. He just said “go forth”.</p>
<p>The Lord’s thoughts are above our thoughts. Too often we put limiting beliefs on ourselves - I’m not good enough, why me? Or, why would God want to help me?</p>
<p>Why not instead ask, “why <em>wouldn’t</em> Heavenly Father want to help me? He loves me and has promised he <em>would</em> help me.”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-why-wouldn't-an-angel.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Angels want to help</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I love this quote by Jared after just going through something really hard:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass that Jared spake again unto his brother, saying: Go and inquire of the Lord whether he will drive us out of the land, and if he will drive us out of the land, cry unto him whither we shall go. <strong>And who knoweth but the Lord will carry us forth into a land which is choice above all the earth?</strong> And if it so be, let us be faithful unto the Lord, that we may receive it for our inheritance. <a href="../scriptures/ether-1.38">Ether 1.38</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just lost your job? Who knoweth but the Lord will provide a better one? Just lost your house? Who knoweth but the Lord will give you a promised land? (They had lost their jobs and house and were wandering at this point.) I love the optimism here.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-4-why-not.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2024 23:23:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 3 - Dreamed a Dream</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-3-dreamed-a-dream.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A great quote leading up to MLK Jr day:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Behold I have dreamed a dream <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-3.2">1 Nephi 3.2</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Lehi dreamed many dreams. It got him in trouble with his boys, as Laman and Lemuel “did murmur in many things against their father, <strong>because he was a visionary man</strong>” (<a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-2.11">1 Nephi 2.11</a>).</p>
<p>Lehi’s wife, Sariah, also murmured against him, “she also had complained against my father, <strong>telling him that he was a visionary man;</strong> saying: Behold thou hast led us forth from the land of our inheritance, and my sons are no more, and we perish in the wilderness.” (<a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.2">1 Nephi 5.2</a>)</p>
<p>Lehi’s response to this is great:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I <strong>know that I am a visionary man</strong>; for if I had not seen the things of God in a vision I should not have known the goodness of God, but had tarried at Jerusalem, and had perished with my brethren. But behold, I have obtained a land of promise, in the which things I do rejoice; yea, and I know that the Lord will deliver my sons out of the hands of Laban, and bring them down again unto us in the wilderness. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.4-5">1 Nephi 5.4–5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This response teaches me a few things:</p>
<ul>
<li>when people struggle, they can complain against a good thing and make it a bad thing. “Why do you always have to be such a goodie two shoes?”</li>
<li>The response is “if I weren’t such a goodie two shoes I’d be miserable”. Helps remind people of the value of their own biases.</li>
</ul>
<p>Complaining is a natural part of life. Just be careful what you complain about.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-3-dreamed-a-dream.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 22:52:51 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 2 - Receiving a promised land</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-2-receiving-a-promised-land.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>While Lehi wandered in the wilderness, Nephi recounted he left the “land of his inheritance”:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass that he departed into the wilderness. And he left his house, and the land of his inheritance, and his gold, and his silver, and his precious things, and took nothing with him, <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-2.4">1 Nephi 2.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-leaving-the-promised-land.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Leaving the promised land</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Yet by the end of the Chapter, Nephi is promised a land of inheritance:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And inasmuch as ye shall keep my commandments, ye shall prosper, and shall be led to a land of promise; yea, even a land which I have prepared for you; yea, a land which is choice above all other lands. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-2.20">1 Nephi 2.20</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Amazing how they lose one thing but gain another. Also amazing is how they had prophets warning them of Jerusalem’s destruction - why didn’t the Lord make <em>those</em> prophets leave?</p>
<p>He has a plan for us individually.</p>
<p>CS Lewis remarked something along the lines of “We don’t chase God, God chases us”.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Both Malcolm Muggeridge and C.S. Lewis attest to this. Muggeridge wrote, “I had a notion that somehow, besides questing, I was being pursued.” Lewis said that, “…night after night…I sensed the steady, unrelenting approach of Him whom I so earnestly desired not to meet. Finally, I gave in, and admitted that God was God, and knelt and prayed…” (<a href="https://www.stettlerindependent.com/community/man-can-not-sidestep-thinking-about-god-faith-and-reflection-6606319">link</a>, also discussed in <a href="../book-review/the-oxford-inklings-lewis-tolkien-and-their-circle.html">The Oxford Inklings: Lewis, Tolkien and Their Circle</a>) (<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/681434-you-must-picture-me-alone-in-that-room-in-magdalen">good reads link</a>)</p>
</blockquote>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>covenant</category>
  <category>individual covenant</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-2-receiving-a-promised-land.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2024 10:52:34 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Find the Fun</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/find-the-fun.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-find-the-fun.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Find the fun</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Kid screaming? why?</p>
<p>Milk on the floor? why is that a funny thing?</p>
<p>Poop on the ground? (<a href="../creative/poem-the-dove-forevermore.html">The Dove (Forevermore)</a>) It won’t last. it’s endearing.</p>
<p>No, this isn’t just fanciful thinking - this is a choice. You’ve chosen to be angry at that spilled milk, lost your cool when bro slapped sis, and walked out of the room when you heard that last cry for “more breakfast!!”.</p>
<p>But <em>why</em> did you get overwhelmed? Stressed about all there is to do, and now there’s one more thing? Stressed about “am i a good parent”? Stressed about raising your kids right and you have to instruct them on everything they do wrong in order to do that?</p>
<p>My new philosophy: Kids are kids. They’re optimizers. Anyone in tech knows that an optimizer is a thing trying to find the optimal point of another thing. It’s like battleships - you keep guessing until you find. Then you guess around until you get all the points, until you know where to look.</p>
<p>Kids do this all day. They say something crazy trying to get a reaction. They say a not-funny joke 100 times until it’s funny again. Humans do that too.</p>
<p>So they’re optimizing. Exploring. Exploiting. That’s all their doing - exploring the space, exploiting the emotional signal.</p>
<p>Knowing that, find the fun in the moment. They won’t always be like this. And when it’s gone, you’ll wish it wasn’t. <a href="../creative/poem-the-dove-forevermore.html">The Dove (Forevermore)</a></p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>parenting</category>
  <category>mental health</category>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>A/B testing</category>
  <category>mindset</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/find-the-fun.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2024 10:26:44 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Stop trying to change people. Stop it.</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/stop-trying-to-change-people.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>One thing I’ve seen a lot of people, including myself, do is try to change other people.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-chameleon-and-iguana.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Come on! Why won’t you change colors?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’m not sure why this is or why we do this. Perhaps we want others to be happier and we feel in our own egos that we know the better way. Perhaps we want our own problems to go away. Etc. etc.</p>
<p>The gospel isn’t about healing others. The gospel of Jesus is about individuals coming to Him for personal healing.</p>
<p>We can pray for others, sure. But what’s the point of that prayer?</p>
<ul>
<li>To ask Heaven to send good vibes to someone else or,</li>
<li>to have the <em>process</em> of praying change <em>our</em> own hearts. (<a href="../christianity/the-power-of-habitual-prayer.html">The Power of Habitual Prayer</a>)</li>
</ul>
<p>When we pray, it changes us. <em>What</em> changes us? <em>He</em> does. Heavenly Father changes us through the power of the Savior’s atonement. Prayer is never about changing other people’s hearts, even if you pray their heart might be softened. But by praying for their heart to be softened, it actually softens your own heart.</p>
<p>When Alma and their people prayed for deliverance from captivity, they prayed for softened hearts:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Therefore they hushed their fears, and began to cry unto the Lord that he would soften the hearts of the Lamanites… <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-23.28">Mosiah 23.28</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The hearts softened, but the more important thing that happened is that they developed enough faith in the Lord in order to be able to sneak out and not be afraid of being hunted down or what not. Like the Israelites in Egypt it can be dangerous to just go into the desert. Takes a lot of faith. But the prayers and Miracles of Moses softened the Israelite’s hearts and prepared them to follow Moses.</p>
<p>But what about Alma praying for his kids?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Behold, the Lord hath heard the prayers of his people, and also the prayers of his servant, Alma, who is thy father; for he has prayed with much faith concerning thee that thou mightest be brought to the knowledge of the truth; <strong>therefore, for this purpose have I come to convince thee of the power and authority of God, that the prayers of his servants might be answered according to their faith.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-27.14">Mosiah 27.14</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Surely this is about God sending an angel to change someone. Pray hard and miracles happen, even if they don’t see an angel.</p>
<p>But the reality is more nuanced.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And now I say unto thee, Alma, go thy way, and seek to destroy the church no more, that their prayers may be answered, <strong>and this even if thou wilt of thyself be cast off</strong>. <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-27.16">Mosiah 27.16</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The angel didn’t come to change Alma.</p>
<p>But you’d think there would be a strong correlation between seeing an angel and changing your ways though, right? A piece of counter evidence is found with Laman and Lemuel who were visited by an angel while bearing up Nephi:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And after the angel had departed, Laman and Lemuel <strong>again began to murmur</strong>, saying: How is it possible that the Lord will deliver Laban into our hands? Behold, he is a mighty man, and he can command fifty, yea, even he can slay fifty; then why not us? <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-3.31">1 Nephi 3.31</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Or what about the people who saw Jesus heal and then condemn him for doing so on a Sunday? Evidence abounds that spiritual encounters don’t forcibly change us. Angelic visitations don’t change us. Jesus appearing to people didn’t change them.</p>
<p>This is agency. This is Heavenly Father’s plan.</p>
<p>When Alma saw the angel, the angel said “I’m visiting you to answer the prayers of your dad.” So yes, absolutely, the Lord does things on our behalf <em>because</em> we pray. But he doesn’t change us.</p>
<p>This very same angel gave Alma an out: “even if thou wilt of thyself be cast off”…The angel gave agency. But Alma could easily have acted like Laman and Lemuel or the Pharisees and hardened his heart. It’s also why the Lord was able to do many miracles in the Americas that he couldn’t do in Jerusalem (3 Nephi): they had faith. They chose to follow Him. They had agency.</p>
<p>The gospel isn’t about us changing others through prayer. It’s about us allowing the Savior to change our hearts. This same scripture could be applied when trying to change another person:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>why beholdest thou the mote that is in thy brother’s eye, but considerest not the beam that is in thine own eye? <a href="../scriptures/matthew-7.3">Matthew 7.3</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Or this:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>When we feel hurt, angry, or envious, it is quite easy to judge people. This topic could actually be taught in a two-word sermon. When it comes to hating, gossiping, ignoring, ridiculing, holding grudges, or wanting to cause harm, please apply the following:</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Stop it! <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/friend/2013/06/stop-it?lang=eng">Uchtdorf</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Instead, find the good in others. Focus on changing and improving yourself to be more understanding, more accepting, more go with the flow.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>prayer</category>
  <category>agency</category>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <category>perspective</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/stop-trying-to-change-people.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 13:16:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 1 - He prepares us to teach us</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-Nephi-1-he-prepares-us-to-teach-us.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Consider this:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass that he returned to his own house at Jerusalem; and he cast himself upon his bed, being overcome with the Spirit and the things which he had seen. And being <strong>thus</strong> overcome with the Spirit, he was carried away in a vision, even that he saw the heavens open, <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-1.7-8">1 Nephi 1.7–8</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Cause and effect. First: he was overcome by the spirit. Second, he had a vision.</p>
<p>But that’s not how the vision came. First, it began with prayer.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wherefore it came to pass that my father, Lehi, as he went forth prayed unto the Lord, yea, even with all his heart, in behalf of his people. And it came to pass as he prayed unto the Lord, there came a pillar of fire and dwelt upon a rock before him; and he saw and heard much; and because of the things which he saw and heard he did quake and tremble exceedingly. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-1.5-6">1 Nephi 1.5–6</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>So here’s the order:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Lehi listens to prophets that Jerusalem will be destroyed (4)</li>
<li>Lehi prays for his people, hoping they won’t be (5)</li>
<li>Lehi sees a pillar of fire, sees many things (6)</li>
<li>Lehi returns home (assumes he’s not home), and is overcome with what he saw (7)</li>
<li>Lehi then has another, more pronounced vision (8)</li>
</ol>
<p>What a way to start off the Book of Mormon: this is a book about personal revelation, written by people who had revelations, and it teaches us the pattern. In this case, we care about others. When we do, the heavens open as we pray.</p>
<p>We prob won’t have visions, but we <em>will</em> have the spirit.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I will give unto the children of men line upon line, precept upon precept, here a little and there a little; and blessed are those who hearken unto my precepts, and lend an ear unto my counsel, for they shall learn wisdom; for <strong>unto him that receiveth I will give more</strong> <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-28.30">2 Nephi 28.30</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-pillar-of-fire-on-rock.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Pillar of fire on a rock</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>scripture of the day</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>revelation</category>
  <category>prophets</category>
  <category>epistemology</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-Nephi-1-he-prepares-us-to-teach-us.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 09:29:53 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
