<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>No Empty Chairs?</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/no-empty-chairs.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>With those who have a view of eternity, they may consider the desire to have “no empty chairs” in the world to come. This simply implies that they want to see everyone in heaven.</p>
<section id="the-origin-of-the-phrase" class="level1">
<h1>The origin of the phrase</h1>
<p>I recently heard the 1998 classic, “<a href="http://bearlakemonsters.blogspot.com/2010/09/no-empty-chairs.html">No Empty Chairs</a>”, written by the late Senator Orrin Hatch. It talks about this theme clearly.</p>
<p>I tried briefly tracking down the origin of this phrase. It was mentioned once in general conference by <a href="https://www.lds-general-conference.org/">Elder Benson in 1984</a>, “…that all will be worthy, without a single empty chair. That is my fervent hope and prayer for each family in the Church…”</p>
<p>In a <a href="https://scriptures.byu.edu/#:t109b&amp;%22empty%20chairs%22:st&amp;&amp;1830&amp;2023&amp;gjt&amp;n&amp;30@0$%22empty%20chairs%22">1986 article by David B Haight</a>, he also paraphrased President Benson’s family motto:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>President Benson loves his family and keeps in constant touch with them—his six children (all faithful in the Church), thirty-four grandchildren, and twenty great-grandchildren. He and Sister Benson have a motto in their family, that in this life and the next there will be “no&nbsp;empty chairs.” Can you think of a more heavenly goal?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Church news posted about the theme in <a href="https://www.thechurchnews.com/1990/7/28/23261560/no-empty-chairs">1990</a>, again referring to President Benson.</p>
<p>But I believe Lucy Mack Smith, an LDS pioneer and father of Joseph Smith, wins the award. She had the phrase “please - no empty chairs” <a href="https://latterdaysoprano.com/2008/03/08/no-empty-chairs/">written on a memorial to her.</a></p>
</section>
<section id="the-impact-of-concept" class="level1">
<h1>The impact of concept</h1>
<p>For some, this concept can be inspiring. One person recounted how the idea <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/ensign/2013/03/no-empty-chairs?lang=eng">helped lift them out of drug addiction</a>.</p>
<p>But times have changed. I don’t know any close friend who doesn’t have several family members no longer in the church. Families are split in terms of people who are religious vs not. Parents who stay in the <a href="https://www.ldsliving.com/6-tips-for-parents-of-adult-children-who-dont-believe-in-the-church/s/90940">church struggle</a> knowing how to keep relationships with children who have left. They feel bad they don’t have 34 grandchildren all “active” like President Benson.</p>
<p>But I think for most people who leave the church, they struggle with this concept on the other side. They want to know how to identify themselves to those who are still in the church. They want relationships with their family members and don’t know how to do that since so much of their life has been in the church.</p>
<p>I was talking to my friend the other day at church and he felt like he had to identify, “I don’t really come that often, so I guess I’m like less active or something?” People like identities, and they try to categorize themselves.</p>
<p>This language misaligns their focus.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-focus-should-be-on-a-relationship-with-the-savior" class="level1">
<h1>The focus should be on a relationship with the Savior</h1>
<p><a href="../book-review/how-to-decide-simple-tools-for-making-better-choices.html">How to Decide: Simple Tools for Making Better Choices</a> lays out how “resulting” is the process of evaluating the quality of a decision based on how it turned out. Instead you should focus on how you went about making the decision because outcomes can always be uncertain.</p>
<p>“No empty chairs” focuses on the outcome, and not the process.</p>
<p>Focusing on “no empty chairs” isn’t the doctrine. It’s actually anti-doctrine. 1/3 of hosts of heaven didn’t come to earth. Lots of empty chairs. Agency is the doctrine.</p>
<p>Whether you’re in the chair or not, whether less active or active, etc is just the wrong mindset. The only mindset that matters is: do I have a relationship with the Savior? Am I coming to know Him?</p>
<p>“No empty chairs” takes the focus off the Savior and instead perhaps puts it on a social construct or pact “we’re all in this together and you’d better be there. No empty chairs.” It’s probably not meant that way, but it can be chosen to be interpreted that way.</p>
<p>Instead, the framework could be “help teach and invite everyone to enjoy a meaningful relationship with the Savior, so they can have greater peace and joy”. If that’s the mentality, then as people come to the Savior (truth, light), then they will have a reason to sit down.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> is an amatueur husband, father, Christian, and tech writer, but a professional data scientist. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/no-empty-chairs.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>An Unknown God</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/unknown-god/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-tip no-icon">
<div class="callout-body d-flex">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container">
<p>This post speaks to how I manage spiritual doubts, such as whether God exists. It got me thinking after reading a few religious posts by <a href="https://robjhyndman.com/unbelievable/ch1.html">Rob Hybdman</a>, someone whose professional (data science) work I greatly admire.</p>
<p>Here’s a summary of some points I try to make here:</p>
<ul>
<li>He doesn’t try to convince us to believe Him without a doubt, He asks us to follow him</li>
<li>People who saw Christ didn’t even recognize Him as the Savior</li>
<li>Christianity is hard to grasp and won’t make total sense when you think deeply about it.</li>
<li>Our job is to keep learning, and ask Him to teach us about His nature</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>I think too many people grow up thinking of God in black/white terms and when one, linking piece of the puzzle doesn’t fit or is missing, some throw Him out all together. Here’s my take on why people misrepresent God, and how this can lead to personal doubts of faith in Him and His Son.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/unknown-god/photo.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Christ asking his disciples, “Whom say he that I am?”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="an-unknown-god" class="level1">
<h1>An unknown God</h1>
<p>A certain philosopher named Korihor once reasoned that people should stop paying tithing or following restrictive religious commandments because they’re wasting their time. Here’s his thinking:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Yea, they durst not make use of that which is their own lest they should offend their priests, who do yoke them according to their desires, and have brought them to believe, ==by their traditions and their dreams and their whims and their visions== and their ==pretended mysteries==, that they should, if they did not do according to their words, ==offend some unknown being, who they say is God==—a being who never has been seen or known, who never was nor ever will be. - <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/alma/30?id=p28&amp;lang=eng#p28">Alma 30:28</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I love this because the argument of whether God exists or if Christ was the Savior is nothing new. (And many people I highly regard and esteem are tackling this “new” issue head on, as many in the world are questioning their faith.) But a lot of the same arguments that have existed continue to exist: why believe?</p>
<p>…It’s not like anyone’s ever seen God anyway.</p>
<p>Let’s assume for a minute that they have seen God. They saw His Son, His mortal example, walk the earth (<a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/nt/john/5?id=p19&amp;lang=eng#p19">John 5:19</a>).</p>
<p>While with His disciples, Christ himself took a moment to reflect on who people thought he was, and whether people actually recognized Him for who He is:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>When Jesus came into the coasts of Cæsarea Philippi, he asked his disciples, saying, ==Whom do men say that I the Son of man am?== And they said, Some say that thou art John the Baptist: some, Elias; and others, Jeremias, or one of the prophets. <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/nt/matt/16?id=p13-p14&amp;lang=eng#p13">Matthews 16:13-14</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>People had no idea who Christ was even though I’d bet either He or His disciples them His name many times while He was healing them.</p>
<p>People are funny like that.</p>
<p>Consider your own life. Have you ever misinterpreted a situation, even as it’s being explained to you?</p>
<p>Let’s consider a magician who does a magic trick for you. She doesn’t show you how it’s done, but she does explain it to you with only words. Since you don’t specifically see how the magic trick is done, perhaps your mind wanders and you doubt what really happened.</p>
<p>Do you trust the Magician? When He tells you who He is, after healing you, do you believe Him? When an unexplainable coincidence happens in your life, what do you chalk it up to?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Nah, that’s so highly improbable it must just be <em>luck</em>”… (whatever <em>luck</em> is…)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I can’t imagine how it must have felt for people around Christ to be healed by rubbing mud on their eyes or washing in a river a few times or, or, … I can only honestly believe these people felt absolute wonder to the point of mental disassociation. How else do you mentally cope with being a paralytic your whole life and then you’re able to walk?</p>
<p>It’s entirely reasonable, then, that they just figured He must be like the other miracle workers they knew - Elias, John the Baptist, etc. They try to frame Him in their believable mental reference, i.e., “luck”.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-strange-god" class="level1">
<h1>A strange God</h1>
<p>Perhaps though we can relate to when Paul, a lifelong Non-Christian <em>and</em> Christian persecuter, preached to his fellow Gentiles:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>16 Now while Paul waited for them at Athens, his spirit was stirred in him, when he saw the city wholly given to idolatry. 17 Therefore ==disputed he in the synagogue with the Jews==, and with the devout persons, and in the market daily with them that met with him. 18 ==Then certain philosophers== of the Epicureans, and of the Stoicks, encountered him. And some said, ==What will this babbler say?== other some, He seemeth to be a setter forth of strange gods: because he preached unto them Jesus, and the resurrection. <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/nt/acts/17?id=p16&amp;lang=eng#p16">Acts 17:16-18</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Paul got them. He was once like them: a gentile. An unbeliever. A <em>disbeliever</em>. But he eventually was converted to knowing Christ, and, as such, appeared to seem like a babbler when trying to talk to people who once were like him. They considered him and his teachings strange:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>19 And they took him, and brought him unto Areopagus, saying, ==May we know what this new doctrine==, whereof thou speakest, is? 20 For ==thou bringest certain strange things to our ears==: we would know therefore what these things mean. <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/nt/acts/17?id=p19&amp;lang=eng#p19">Acts 16:19-20</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Meeting Christ can be strange.</p>
<p>Understanding him, so too.</p>
</section>
<section id="putting-a-box-on-god" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Putting a box on God</h1>
<p>Consider the question, “why does God let good people suffer?”</p>
<p>(Other important questions like, “why did God encourage Abraham/Isaac/Israel to be polygamists but Adam not?”, or “why did God restrict the <em>entire</em> earth from receiving his Gospel until <em>after</em> Christ died, commanding His <em>people</em> not to marry or mingle with <em>them</em> but then change his tone ~33 AD?”, are worth similar consideration.)</p>
<p>It’s a false dichotomy: if God exists and loves us, He surely wouldn’t let us suffer. If suffering exists, especially of <em>good</em><sup>1</sup> people, God must not then exist.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;What is Good without God?</p></li><li id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;The world is filled with unjust, seemingly unnecessary suffering. Consider innocent children starving across the world, being bombed in Gaza/raped in Israel, bombed in Ukraine, Yemen, gassed in Germany in the Holocaust, starved in Stalin’s camps, nuked by the United States in Japan, etc, etc, etc. (I sincerely don’t write this easily, nor to make light of the suffering.) all of the suffering is horrible. But it doesn’t for a moment mean God doesn’t exist. It actually affirms His existence, because if evil exists the opposite of evil must too.</p></li><li id="fn3"><p><sup>3</sup>&nbsp;I don’t mean that in the Marxist political sense, because who’s to declare who’s suffering at any given moment? Is an affluent child born with cancer not a sufferer despite them not being poor?</p></li></div><p>Consider all the suffering of innocent children<sup>2</sup>. The reality of human nature is sufferers vs non sufferers<sup>3</sup>. Any suffering is painful to bear, and nobody better understands this than Christ himself (<a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/19?id=p16-p19&amp;lang=eng#p16">D&amp;C 19:16-19</a>).</p>
<p>The point is, we can falsely equivocate that because God loves us and He had the power to stop suffering, He should stop it.</p>
<p>Do you do this with any other relationship? Consider the hypothetical:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Father Joe loves his children. But Joe let his son Bob get hit with a toy by little sister Susie. Joe let Susie suffer. Therefore, Joe acted in an evil and therefore does not exist.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This line of thinking is absurd to anyone with a brain, let alone to anyone who is a parent. They understand that sufferig is part of life, can be good for teaching, and that it doesn’t mean the parent doesn’t exist. <em>Yet sometimes we wonder if God exists because we’re suffering.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="consider-alternative-viewpoints" class="level1">
<h1>Consider alternative viewpoints</h1>
<p>To be comfortable with unanswered questions from a yet unknown God, we should consider how the question is already answered.</p>
<p>For example, did Hod stop Christ from suffering? No.&nbsp;Did Christ stop himself from suffering on the cross when He had the power to turn water to wine for the thirsty, heal the suffering swordsman’s ear, or even raise Himself from the dead?</p>
<p>I’m trying to rally around the point: we set up for ourselves false philosophical arguments about who or what God is and should be like when there’s a lot of nuance to be considered.</p>
<p>In my view, He’s more of a Magician who “explains but doesn’t show” than one who tries “to convince us about every little thing”. Because it’s quite human to be like “oh, yea that magic trick isn’t cool anymore” once you understand it. And His goal is to invite us to <em>believe</em> His son so that we’ll <em>follow</em> Him. His goal isn’t for us to know <em>everything</em>, though he <em>is</em> willing to teach us a lot. Remember: “ask and ye <em>shall</em> receive”.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And now come, saith the Lord, by the Spirit…and let us reason together, ==that ye may understand;== <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/50?id=p10&amp;lang=eng#p10">D&amp;C 50:10</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>He just didn’t say <em>when</em> He’d tell us.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-he-explains-but-doesnt-try-to-convince" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Why he explains but doesn’t try to convince</h1>
<p>Why do I believe that He likes to explain but not convince? A few ideas:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>He taught people they would get to heaven by eating His flesh (sacrament), and people misunderstood and thought this was a “hard” teaching. They walked no more with him (John 6), but he didn’t run them down to try to bring them back. <em>Why</em> <em>didn’t he</em>?<sup>4</sup></li>
<li>He was chained by the Romans, spat on, crowned with thorns, and whipped. But instead of showing them signs and wonders He let them abuse Him. Then He forgave them after they nailed Him to the cross multiple times and speared Him in His side and gave Him vinegar to drink (Psalm 69, John 19).</li>
<li>He knew He couldn’t convince them. He once healed a withered man’s hands and the Pharisees wanted to destroy Him because he did so on the sabbath (<a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/nt/matt/12?id=p10-p15&amp;lang=eng#p10">Matthew 12:9-14</a>)<sup>5</sup>. How too are we like the Pharisees where we say “God shouldn’t be like X!!!” Shouldn’t we instead let God reveal Himself?</li>
</ol>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn4"><p><sup>4</sup>&nbsp;Consider this in a humorous way: Why didn’t He say “oh sorry!! Please come back! I’ve got a quota of disciples to reach and if I don’t have you with me…””</p></li><li id="fn5"><p><sup>5</sup>&nbsp;I love how instead of engaging with the Pharisees, He “withdrew” from them and “healed them all”, kind of as a divine rebel just saying, “you’re mad about me healing one guy on the Sabbath? Fine, I’ll heal everyone.”</p></li></div><p>These three clues, among many others, give me perspective on why He’s okay being misunderstood by us.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-god-of-purpose-children-of-purpose-and-promise" class="level1">
<h1>A God of purpose, children of purpose and promise</h1>
<p>Why does He want us to live by faith? Lots of reasons. But there’s only one I’ll speak to: He’s a God of purpose:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>37 And the Lord God spake unto Moses, saying: The heavens, they are many, and they cannot be numbered unto man; but they are numbered unto me, for they are mine. 38 And as one earth shall pass away, and the heavens thereof even so shall another come; and there is no end to my works, neither to my words. 39 For behold, ==this is my work and my glory—to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of man==. - <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/pgp/moses/1?id=p37-p39&amp;lang=eng#p37">Moses 1:37-39</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>His goal is to prepare an environment to teach and challenge us. Our goal should be to learn who, how and why.</p>
<p>Our purpose should not be to put God in a box or imagine Him black and white. It should be to learn who He is, so He’a no longer an unknown God.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And this is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom thou hast sent. - <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/nt/john/17?id=p3&amp;lang=eng#p3">John 17:3</a></p>
</blockquote>


</section>


<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> is an amatueur husband, father, Christian, and tech writer, but a professional data scientist. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>theology</category>
  <category>faith</category>
  <category>doubts</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/unknown-god/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/unknown-god/photo.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post Christmas blues? Remember the empty tombs</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/christmas-empty-tomb/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="an-empty-spot-in-the-room" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>An empty spot in the room</h1>
<p>Just cleaned up the Christmas tree and all its ornaments and needles. The glittering, shimmering, and sparkling lights that have warmed us for the last month are officially gone. Packed up. Shipped out. Sent home.</p>
<p>My child remarked, “it feels so empty without the tree!” I couldn’t help but agree.</p>
<p>The thought dawned on me, perhaps this is what the disciples felt once His light left the earth. Some accounts declare there was thundering and lightning and three days of darkness that covered the earth after He gave His life.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/christmas-empty-tomb/deadtree.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">A dead Christmas tree reminds us of a Christ who died for us <em>on</em> a tree, the cross.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="an-empty-room-an-empty-tomb" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>An empty room, an empty tomb</h1>
<p>But just as His easily preventable departure left friends and parents weeping (because they didn’t fully understand what He was dying for, (<a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/nt/matt/16?id=p21-p23&amp;lang=eng#p21">Matthew 16:21-23</a>), perhaps we can remember a little of that sadness that they felt as we clean up the tree. The child was born. He was born to break the bonds of death. He died, some describing He died on a tree. And now, my pine tree representing Christ(mas) is also dead.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Who his own self bare our sins in his own body on the tree, that we, being dead to sins, should live unto righteousness: by whose stripes ye were healed. (1 Peter 2:24)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Perhaps it’s also symbolic we cut down the tree to put it in our homes. It has an expiration date, just like Christ’s life. He knew it was time (<a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/nt/john/13?id=p26-p27&amp;lang=eng#p26">John 13:26-27</a>), even if nobody else could comprehend.</p>
<p>But remember what happened after? He resurrected. He brought His light back to His friends.</p>
<p>Perhaps New Year’s lights can remind us of His return. And perhaps a New Year’s resolution can remind us that He invited His disciples to change their ways and go and preach to the gentiles (people previously not allowed to have His gospel and His gift of baptism and the Holy Ghost), to share the gift of Christ(mas) with everyone.</p>
<p>The death of Christ marked the fulfillment of prophecy and the fulfillment of the Law of Moses, which meant that the Jews and the house of Israel were no longer the only ones chosen by God but now everybody could receive the gospel (Galatians 3:29).</p>
<p>Let’s take this new year to remember all are loved. All are remembered. All are invited to happiness and peace through Christ.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/christmas-empty-tomb/photo.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Dead tree? Remember the living Christ!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> is an amatueur husband, father, Christian, and tech writer, but a professional data scientist. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/christmas-empty-tomb/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/christmas-empty-tomb/photo.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>His is the light that we should share</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-24-he-is-the-light-that-we-should-share/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>When Christ was teaching his disciples, he invited them to share their light to the world. But then he elaborated in an interesting way:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/3-ne/18?id=p24&amp;lang=eng#p24">3rd Nephi 18:24</a> Therefore, hold up your light that it may shine unto the world. Behold I am the light which ye shall hold up—that which ye have seen me do. Behold ye see that I have prayed unto the Father, and ye all have witnessed.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Lord is their light. He is our light. He is the light we hold up to the world and let shine. He is our light that we let shine.</p>
<p>The pronouns here are impactful by their implication:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>He assumes we have light</li>
<li>He assumes we have Him as our light</li>
<li>He invites us to share the light we possess</li>
<li>The light we possess is His light</li>
<li>But it is ours. And it is his. Our light is His light. His light is our light.</li>
</ol>
<p>“Let your light so shine before men that they may see your good works…”. Read in this new way: obtain the Lord as your light. Then shine His light before men.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-24-he-is-the-light-that-we-should-share/photo.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> is an amatueur husband, father, Christian, and tech writer, but a professional data scientist. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-24-he-is-the-light-that-we-should-share/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-24-he-is-the-light-that-we-should-share/cover.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Christ Child</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-24-the-christ-child/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The story of the Savior’s birth brings many wonderful concepts to memory and can teach us a lot about what will bring us true joy and happiness in this life.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-24-the-christ-child/photo.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>
<p>This is my favorite video of the Christmas story. The most powerful part is the moment when Mary sings a lullaby to Jesus. I remember reading somewhere that this moment was completely impromptu by the actress, and it speaks volumes to the sacredness of the moment where Mary first laid eyes on her beloved son.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yXWoKi5x3lw?si=JogPuTvWW1X-aD-S" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>So what does this story give me perspective on at this time of year?</p>
<ul>
<li>Christ was the rightful, bloodline heir to King David’s throne. He was the King of the Jews. But he never sought authority. He never sought a throne. He instead taught <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/nt/matt/22?id=p17-p21&amp;lang=eng#p17">“Render therefore unto Caesar the things which are Caesar’s”</a>. He didn’t engage in turf battles. In rebellion. In insurrection. He just wanted people to find happiness in their circumstances by living with lovingkindness in their hearts for their God, their neighbor, and themselves.</li>
<li>In his role as a Savior and Judge of the world, he sought to not condemn the sinner trapped in the act of sin. Instead he came to liberate. To forgive. To support.</li>
<li>If you believe Christ was the Creator and Savior of the world, consider how He chose to come into the world. He was born in a stable, mucked with animal feces and rotting food scraps, covered with the stench of…a stable. He was rejected of a room in the inn. He was laid in a manger, perhaps a feeding trough. Maybe Mary had help giving birth, maybe she didn’t. He was born generally alone. I wonder if He chose to do his birth this way because nobody can say he had it easy. He didn’t have the special treatment of a King’s birth. No, he was born to an exhausted, weary traveler, likely on the cold hard floor of a dirty barn.</li>
<li>If we think about the Savior being the architect of this birth, think about how he planned for angels to show up to shepherds. Not King Herod. The shepherds. He would be the prophesied sacrificial Lamb. He would be the Good Shepherd. Yet these people were perhaps the minimum wage, forgotten ones outside the city gate. Yet these are those who had the privilege to see Him first. And He invited them to come and see. His whole life was an invitation.</li>
<li>He also invited the rich wise men. All are invited. He wanted all to see, and he wanted the world to know that He was for everyone regardless their circumstances. And that all of us, whether destitute or traveling with caravans, can bring the gifts of our heart to Him. We don’t need to bring gold. He just wants a <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/3-ne/9?id=p20&amp;lang=eng#p20">“broken heart and contrite spirit.</a></li>
</ul>
<p>How can we apply these things to our life, today?</p>
<ul>
<li>Seek out the forgotten. The people in our life that seem forgotten. The servants in our life (person on the other end of the customer support line, the checkout person, your supervisor) but even, your <a href="https://youtu.be/tX8TgVR33KM?si=Jdwq-B9W0dhWYhLA">best friend who seems to be doing great…</a></li>
<li>Seek not riches or wealth. Harod sought these things. Christ sought relationships and truth.</li>
<li>Don’t seek for power. Christ deserved it. Christ had it. He turned water to wine, cursed a tree, and made a host of <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/nt/john/18?id=p4-p6&amp;lang=eng#p4">men fall over at the sound of his voice</a>. Yet he didn’t touch the Romans.</li>
<li>Seek to invite. To share. To uplift. Christ made shepherds feel important. He invited them to his crib side. And ” his hand is stretched out still.” (Isaiah 9:12)</li>
</ul>
<p>He came like all of us, as a child. But he came to show us how a God would live. And he did.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-24-the-christ-child/standing.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The Christ as a Child, before worshipping Wise men</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> is an amatueur husband, father, Christian, and tech writer, but a professional data scientist. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-24-the-christ-child/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-24-the-christ-child/photo.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Christmas celebrates a Living Christ</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-17-christmas-celebrates-a-living-christ/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-17-christmas-celebrates-a-living-christ/photo.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Away in a manger.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="old-news" class="level1">
<h1>Old news</h1>
<p>Elder Neil Anderson’s invitation here is worth listening to. It’s an invitation to ponder the reality of the birth of our Savior. It’s rather simple, but it evokes a profound question we should all consider.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet blockquote">
<p lang="en" dir="ltr">
How wonderful it is to celebrate the birth of our Savior and Redeemer. Jesus Christ is the central figure of all human history.<br><br>I know He lives. I know He was born. I know He has been resurrected. I know He is our Savior and Redeemer. And with you I rejoice in this beautiful… <a href="https://t.co/YDQpIzgk0n">pic.twitter.com/YDQpIzgk0n</a>
</p>
— Neil L. Andersen (<span class="citation" data-cites="AndersenNeilL">@AndersenNeilL</span>) <a href="https://twitter.com/AndersenNeilL/status/1736400958928933230?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 17, 2023</a>
</blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
</section>
<section id="did-he-come" class="level1">
<h1>Did He come?</h1>
<p>Nothing Elder Anderson shares here is new. It’s rather repetitive. Same old story. Same-old old-guy telling me to believe in a Jesus.</p>
<p>If you consider the most currently interesting things in this world, Artificial Intelligence, some may tell you that there exists a future utopia where we’re supported by infinitely intelligent digital agents who can solve complex world problems and bring us to…utopia.</p>
<p>Ok. We’ve also heard this before. The Tower of Babel tried to approximate heaven, and now humanity is trying to approximate Godlike intelligence.</p>
<p>The void of Christ in one’s life produces a desire to create Christ. A savior. Something to literally save us from our woes.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet blockquote">
<p lang="en" dir="ltr">
i think AI is going to be the greatest force for economic empowerment and a lot of people getting rich we have ever seen
</p>
— Sam Altman (<span class="citation" data-cites="sama">@sama</span>) <a href="https://twitter.com/sama/status/1625186078599811072?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">February 13, 2023</a>
</blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>Let’s be real. I’m a tech optimist. I say bring it on. But I’m also a Christian. In my view, the most important question isn’t “what will AGI do to/for humanity?” Instead, the most important question is “was Jesus Christ the promised messiah?”</p>
<p>If Christ came, and was indeed the prophesied Christ, then all of life’s ultimate questions are already answered.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Why are we here? To die and be resurrected to live again.</p></li>
<li><p>Where did we come from? The same place He came from: the presence of God.</p></li>
<li><p>Who are we? We are sons and daughters of God worth saving.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Yes, the questions are already answered: it doesn’t matter what happens with AI. Because the end is known: the Lord will come again.</p>
<p>Let us treasure this time to reflect on a Savior who already came. Who lives. Who loves us beyond mortal (or AI) comprehension.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-can-we-do" class="level1">
<h1>What can we do?</h1>
<p>Let’s take a moment, perhaps an hour, to consider the miracle of Christmas:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet blockquote">
<p lang="en" dir="ltr">
As Christmas approaches, I realize that some may have concerns and perhaps some anxiety about the future. <br><br>There may be a lot of “noise” in your life: more or less constant engagement online without downtime, without time to be quiet and reflect and think, without time to look… <a href="https://t.co/4rqS2F6No9">pic.twitter.com/4rqS2F6No9</a>
</p>
— D. Todd Christofferson (<span class="citation" data-cites="ChristoffDTodd">@ChristoffDTodd</span>) <a href="https://twitter.com/ChristoffDTodd/status/1735676334968295559?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 15, 2023</a>
</blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> is an amatueur husband, father, Christian, and tech writer, but a professional data scientist. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-17-christmas-celebrates-a-living-christ/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Three Little Pigs</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-13-three-little-pigs/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-13-three-little-pigs/photo.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="first-glance" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="first-glance">first glance</h2>
<p>Yes this is a book review about “The Three Little Pigs”.</p>
<p>The first pig is lazy. So he builds his house of straw.</p>
<p>The second is lazy too. So he builds his house of sticks.</p>
<p>Then the third is the smart one who builds his house of bricks.</p>
<p>But the first two brothers just make fun of the mason. Why waste your time?!? We’re having fun!</p>
<p>So the wolf comes and blows down the houses of the lazy brothers. They run and hide in brick brother’s house.</p>
<p>Moral of the story: be lazy but have a great, well prepared brother!</p>
</section>
<section id="not-quite" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="not-quite">not quite</h2>
<p>I’ve always been bothered by this as I read to my kids. But I’ve recently changed my opinion. Because im very much the first and second brother. We all are.</p>
<p>Were inadequate. Maybe we’re not smart enough to know how to create bricks and such. Maybe we don’t have enough resources and the straw is the best we can do. And maybe we hide behind these insecurities by laughing at those who have more.</p>
<p>Maybe we hide behind our insecurity and question God. The Wise One.</p>
<p>See, Christ is our Brick. He’s the safety. He’s the home we can run to when the world blows us over. He’s the Prepared One who was wishing for us to come to him the whole time. The cry of “you’ll be sorry” by this brother could perhaps be His loving warning of “please be wise. There’s a wolf out there.” Yet we don’t listen. We want to play.</p>
<p>I love the third pig because he lets them in.</p>
<p>Also, the third pig never had to worry about almost getting eaten. Sure, first two enjoyed their fiddle and dance. But they almost died. The third pig is like the non-prodigal son. The one who stayed home and enjoyed the safety of the home the whole time.</p>
<p>Be wise. Be forgiving. And yes, we always have a wise elder Brother who will accept us.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> is an amatueur husband, father, Christian, and tech writer, but a professional data scientist. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book review</category>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/2023-12-13-three-little-pigs/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
