<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<<<<<<<-Updated upstrea
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 09:09:36 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>The Power of Habitual Prayer</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/the-power-of-habitual-prayer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I want to share my experience with how prayer has turned from not very meaningful to substantively helpful in a matter of a few short weeks.</p>
<p>Consider the scene:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote page-columns page-full">
<p>Children jumping on beds. Refusing to get dressed or brush their teeth or go to the bathroom. Screaming from the other room. Screaming from this room. Exhausted after a long day. I just want things to change and be different.<sup>1</sup></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;while writing this the insight came: I’m in the state of mind of wanting them to change. This is a mindset of control (<a href="../christianity/stop-trying-to-change-people.html">Stop trying to change people. Stop it.</a>). The fallacy a mind believes is “if only they’re better I’d be at more peace”. Consider the alternative: if they were peaceful but I’m still in a mindset of control. Would I be happier? Perhaps I would feel more comfortable (less noise in my ear). But I’m going to posit that a person in a mindset of control, regardless of whether they’re being listened to and their control is being obeyed, aren’t happy and aren’t mindful. They aren’t present with what is. A healthier mindset for me might be: “anything could happen, delightful that they’re food now, but it’s okay if they misbehave. They’re kids! How can I <a href="../christianity/find-the-fun.html">Find the Fun</a> in this moment?”</p></li></div></blockquote>
<p>Any parent comes across this more than once per day.</p>
<p>Most of last year I felt like I wasn’t getting a whole lot out of my prayers. A few comments:</p>
<ul>
<li>I try praying daily. But I found it hard to focus. Praying out loud helps with this, but I didn’t do it often.</li>
<li>even though I felt my prayers not well focused, I do believe God heard them regardless and by praying in an unfocused state I could still get <em>something</em> out of the experience. I believe God looks down on us when we’re trying, rather ineffectually, to do our best</li>
<li>I felt like my prayers were ineffective because I’d pray and mumble and think about work until I’d come back to me being in a prayer and then I’d say Amen. I’d always wondered what my experience would be like if I really felt a connection to God.</li>
</ul>
<p>Okay. So that’s last year. Lots of prayers. I know God loves me regardless of how effective they are. And I know they could be better.</p>
<p>Back to the scene. There were several times last year when the kids were nuts and I needed to calm myself down. It was hard. I tried a few times to go and pray but just felt like “it’s not working!” Im praying! Why can’t I get to a better state of mind?! This prayer thing isn’t working for me and I’m doing it wrong.</p>
<p>I never felt like prayer wasn’t good or useful. Just that I couldn’t get it to do what I wanted it to do for me: fix me. I figured: maybe I need to pray differently. Or try XYZ thing.</p>
<p>Okay, so throw up a prayer and hope it sticks. Change me! I’m here.</p>
<p>Nope. Didn’t work. I’d still be struggling with patience in those circumstances.</p>
<p>Last night I had a new experience. I <em>did</em> pray the same way I’ve prayed before when stressed. No, I didn’t get fixed - God doesn’t fix us like that. Instead, while praying I remembered a mindset <a href="../christianity/find-the-fun.html">Find the Fun</a> that I had discovered last week. That’s all that came to mind. I left the prayer still agitated because a kid was about to jump on another kid while I was praying and I had to leave the prayer.</p>
<p>What happened though? I was just like 20% less stressed as I tried focusing on <a href="../christianity/find-the-fun.html">Find the Fun</a>.</p>
<p>Okay, so the night went better than it did last week. I had something in my mind to hold on to.</p>
<p>What’s the difference between the me yesterday and the me of three weeks ago? I changed my relationship with prayer.</p>
<p>I’ve been trying to have just one good prayer per day. It’s a goal for this year. And a good prayer is one where I try to get some type of insight. Like meditation. Just pray until an insight. Setting a timer helps me. Doing it in my office or a place where I’m alone helps too. And when I’m done, I write down the insight.</p>
<p>Most of the time the insight isn’t like from God or anything. I don’t hear a voice. I don’t have any mental image. The insight for me usually comes from me hearing myself pray. “Oh, I didn’t realize that was on my mind” or “oh, how did I think of that?” I’ve come to learn that this is a spiritual prayer. This <em>is</em> praying by the spirit. When I desire to connect with God (get something out of my prayer), I’m elevated ever so slightly (<a href="../gratitude/small-things.html">I’m grateful for small things</a>).</p>
<p>And that’s it: I’ve been doing this for about two or weeks now and my relationship with prayer is changing. I no longer want it to fix me. I see it as a way to try to connect with heaven in a small way.</p>
<p>And that’s the realization: the power of prayer isn’t in the hail Mary’s. It’s in the consistent relationship with it.</p>
<p>I <em>do</em> believe a Hail Mary is better than no Hail. So hail away.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And now the Lord was slow to hear their cry because of their iniquities; <strong>nevertheless the Lord did hear their cries</strong> <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-21.15">Mosiah 21.15</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Lord hears your cries even if you’re wicked. Pray regardless. But there is a concept of Him being slow to hear at times: feeling the effect of prayer requires consistency. But he’s happy to help any time we come to Him. He’s not vindictive. He’s not “I told you so” or “you should be coming to me more often than this”. That’s how we treat each other, with pride. God isn’t like that. Heavenly Father wants us to come to him, and he’ll hear our cries.</p>
<p>Translating this to me: i wasn’t wicked or anything. I was just a stressed out dad. But I think the principle applies: if I have a lackluster relationship with prayer then he’ll be slow to hear. Or, said another way, <em>I’ll</em> be slow to hear. Slow to see. More reactive. More knee jerky and less patient. More thinking “why doesn’t this prayer thing work for me?”</p>
<p>So that’s my insight. Make prayer meaningful and it starts to pay dividends slowly. Very slowly. But I also believe in compounding interest.</p>
<p>if your investments gain 0.1% each day of the year, do you know what your returns would be over a year? 44% increase. So if you invest $100 today, by the end of the year you’ll have $144 if you keep reinvesting your returns. Thats insanely good! But that’s math. that’s compounding interest.<sup>2</sup></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;The math is this: 1.001^365=1.44. Or, your daily return is 1.001. Invest $10 and you’ll have $10.01 by the end of day one. Invest $10.01 on day two and gain 0.1% and you’ll have $10.02001 by end of day two. Do this 365 times and you’ll have $10*1.001^365=$14.40</p></li></div><p>So shoot for a 0.1% prayer. That’s all it’s gotta be to get massive returns.</p>
<p>So that’s the invitation: try to make prayer meaningful (whatever that means to <em>you</em>, not me). And try to do it consistently.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>But this is not all; ye must pour out your souls in your closets, and your secret places, and in your wilderness. <a href="../scriptures/alma-34.26">Alma 34.26</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-pray-in-your-wilderness.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Pray alone in your wilderness. Find somewhere.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>




<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>my testimony</category>
  <category>personal stories</category>
  <category>prayer</category>
  <category>scripture of the day</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>featured</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/the-power-of-habitual-prayer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 09:09:36 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 8 - Think for yourself</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-8-what-others-think.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This is an interesting scripture:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>and they were in the attitude of mocking and pointing their fingers towards those who had come at and were partaking of the fruit. And after they had tasted of the fruit they were ashamed, because of those that were scoffing at them; and they fell away into forbidden paths and were lost. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-8.27-28">1 Nephi 8.27–28</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Imagine you’re eating at a Michelin star restaurant and across the street there’s a food court at the mall with a bunch of people eating McDonalds and Burger King. And <em>they’re</em> mocking <em>you</em>.</p>
<p>Reasons this relationship is so fascinating:</p>
<ul>
<li>the people in the building don’t know what the tree tastes like.</li>
<li>The people in the building are far away.</li>
<li>The people eating the fruit are able to be numbed by the perceptions of others, and aren’t focusing on their own experience.</li>
</ul>
<p>If those who became ashamed had focused instead on their own experiences it would have been delicious.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-lehi-dream.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Lehi’s dream</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-8-what-others-think.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 00:23:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2024-01-21 Come Follow Me CTR 7 Jan 15-21 1 Nephi 6-10</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-21-jan-21.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Activity ideas</p>
<section id="studies" class="level1">
<h1>Studies</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-6-god-of-the-covenant.html">1 Nephi 6 - God of the Covenant</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-7-commitment.html">1 Nephi 7</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="activity-ideas" class="level1">
<h1>Activity Ideas</h1>
<ul>
<li>“let me see” (<a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-11.1.html">1 Nephi 11.1</a>) - show a video to one kid, have him share or try to draw it. Have others try to understand. They just have to see for themselves.</li>
</ul>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me lesson plan</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-21-jan-21.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 23:34:29 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 7 - Make a Choice, Don’t go Halvsies</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-7-commitment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="nephi-7" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>1 Nephi 7</h1>
<p>This exchange is fascinating:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Now behold, I say unto you that if ye will return unto Jerusalem ye shall also perish with them. <strong>And now, if ye have choice, go up to the land, and remember the words which I speak unto you, that if ye go ye will also perish;</strong> for thus the Spirit of the Lord constraineth me that I should speak.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Laman and Lemuel don’t want to be in the wilderness, but when Nephi tells them they have their agency, they’re not brave enough to go back to Jerusalem.</p>
<p>In other words, he catches them in their rouse. “Nobody’s forcing you”, go back if you want, but if you do you’ll remember that you’re going to die there.</p>
<p>How often do we like to complain about something but not actually do anything about it? Reminds me of the quote “So then because thou art lukewarm, and neither cold nor hot, I will spue thee out of my mouth.” (<a href="../scriptures/revelation-3.16">Revelation 3.16</a>)</p>
<p>If you don’t want to do anything about it, don’t complain. Vote with your feet, not your mouth. (They were voting with their feet to leave Jerusalem but voting with their mounts against it.)</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-walking-away.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">If you’re gonna walk, walk. If you’re gonna follow the prophet, follow.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>16 And it came to pass that when I, Nephi, had spoken these words unto my brethren, they were angry with me. And it came to pass that they did lay their hands upon me, for behold, they were exceedingly wroth, and they did bind me with cords, for they sought to take away my life, <strong>that they might leave me in the wilderness to be devoured by wild beasts.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-7.15-16">1 Nephi 7.15–16</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Also interesting is how they didn’t directly want to kill Nephi (didn’t have the courage here to try), but instead just decided to leave him to die (Joseph of Egypt style).</p>
<p>This is one of those “I’m not actually sinning because I didn’t do the sin” things. Tying someone up isn’t killing them. Should they die, that’s an unfortunate derivative consequence. But <em>we</em> didn’t kill him. <sup>1</sup></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;They were living the Old law. Perhaps this was legal. But the law of the heart says: this is attempted murder.</p></li></div><p>Backing up to a higher point: how often do we skirt the issue and not take full accountability? They can’t go back to Jerusalem and they can’t even properly attempt murder. They’re just lazy and without conviction all around.</p>
<p>But so are we. We all have these tendencies to disassociate from accountability for our life:</p>
<ul>
<li>well X person is annoying. “Are you going to talk to them?” No…</li>
<li>Etc…</li>
</ul>
<p>Own up. # Other Verses of Interest</p>
<p>Today I liked these verses:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wherefore, the things which are pleasing unto the world I do not write, but the things <strong>which are pleasing unto God and unto those who are not of the world.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-6.5">1 Nephi 6.5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Am I someone who is not of this world? Fascinating question because it makes me wonder what is “the world”. What was Nephibtrying to define here? Perhaps he was summarizing in his own way that those who have their head in the spiritual clouds will love these things, while those who live by “the world” won’t. It’s also reflective of his experience trying to share the gospel that some people don’t care. They just want to enjoy the pineapples and what not. Am I distracted by money, fame, greed, envy?</p>
<hr>
<p>I also got a little ahead and listened to this scripture:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For it came to pass after <strong>I had desired to know the things that my father had seen, and believing that the Lord was able to make them known unto me</strong>, as I sat pondering in mine heart I was caught away in the Spirit of the Lord, yea, into an exceedingly high mountain, which I never had before seen, and upon which I never had before set my foot. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-11.1">1 Nephi 11.1</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>My kids love to come up to my phone and say “let me see!!!” If they hear audio in another room they come sprinting.</p>
<p>Why do kids love seeing? They want to see. They’re sponges. They’re also without much experience in life so they want to see it all! Make up for lost time…</p>
<p>To become like a little child is to want to see for ourselves.</p>


</section>


<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>commitment</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <category>epistemology</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-7-commitment.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 23:34:11 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 6 - God of the Covenant</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-6-god-of-the-covenant.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Nephi introduces the concept of the “God of Abraham” in the Book of Mormon:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For the fulness of mine intent is that I may persuade men to come unto the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, and be saved. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-6.4">1 Nephi 6.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Why? Well, repetition helps us remember. Calling out multiple names also tells us that there were several generations of believers. Also, many people are descendants of these folks so using their name invokes their ancestry. These are three reasons why Nephi (and others) may use this triple threat to identify the God we can worship.</p>
<p>But I think there’s one more reason: the God of the Old Testament is Jesus. He’s the god is the covenant. The covenant of Abraham in which all seeds of the earth shall be blessed. God of Isaac and Jacob - who also received more covenants.</p>
<p>When we worship a God of covenants, we become empowered by those covenants.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>scripture of the day</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-6-god-of-the-covenant.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 23:56:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
are at b<lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 22:59:28 GMT</lastBuildDate>
>>>>>>>+Stashed changes
om a ruthless Laban. Sariah gets very nervous (v1-3), perhaps thinking they’ve been killed.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-weary-wanderer-waiting.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Waiting in the wilderness</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Then once she sees them come back (mission accomplished) she rejoices:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And she spake, saying: Now I know of a surety that the Lord hath commanded my husband to flee into the wilderness; yea, and I also know of a surety that the Lord hath protected my sons, and delivered them out of the hands of Laban, and given them power whereby they could accomplish the thing which the Lord hath commanded them. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.8">1 Nephi 5.8</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But what if they hadn’t come back? Is this just confirmation bias?</p>
<p>No.&nbsp;</p>
<p>See, Sariah had been promised her sons safe return:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>and I know that the Lord will deliver my sons out of the hands of Laban, and bring them down again unto us in the wilderness. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.5">1 Nephi 5.5</a> (Lehi talking)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Because of this (a specific promise), we often fixate in contrary to the exact thing we should be expecting.</p>
<p>Consider Adam and Eve: don’t eat that one tree. Eat anything else. Everything else. Just not that one. → which one?<sup>1</sup> this one? Oh, we ate it.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;im being funny here, because there’s a lot more to the Adam and Eve story - they were supposed to eat it. Point is: we focus on what we’re told not to do.</p></li></div><p>Perhaps Sariah fixates on her sons not returning because that is what a prophet promised her.</p>
<p>Interestingly, there must be a space in time between when a promise is made and a promise is delivered (<a href="../scriptures/alma-40.6-9">see Alma 40.6–9</a> for similar logic). We are not told the length of that in between time. Could be today. Could be tomorrow. Who knows how long Sariah was waiting.</p>
<p>An interesting corollary: she wasn’t doubting something she <em>wasn’t</em> promised.</p>
<p>Consider all the promises in the scriptures. Abraham is promised the gospel will be in his seed. Nephi is promised his seed will be destroyed (he was the righteous one) and Laman and Lemuel were implicitly promised their seed would remain (even though they were wicked). Joseph of Egypt promised some things, Enos is promised other things, etc. We’re all unique.</p>
<p>Let’s consider Peter and John. The Lord offered them whatever they wanted. John wanted to tarry on earth and Peter wanted to be done with the earth and go to heaven. Peter seems to have gotten tiffed with John because John one-upped Peter on the righteous desires contest with Jesus as the Judge:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And for this cause the Lord said unto Peter: If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee? <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-7.4">Doctrine and Covenants 7.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>(The savior goes on to explain how both Peter and John’s desires were great.<sup>2</sup>)</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;side note: the Lord doesn’t compare Peter against John. He just says “John wanted to do more than what <em>he</em> has previously done.” “I say unto thee, Peter, this was a good desire; but my beloved has desired that he might do more, or a greater work yet among men than what he has before done. Yea, he has undertaken a greater work; therefore I will make him as flaming fire and a ministering angel; he shall minister for those who shall be heirs of salvation who dwell on the earth.” <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-7.5-6">Doctrine and Covenants 7.5–6</a></p></li></div><p>Back to Sariah - here are three ways we tend to worry:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>we can worry about things promised to us. We’re just rarely promised a timeline. Trust. Wait. And see.</li>
<li>Where we aren’t promised anything, we have nothing to think of or worry about.</li>
<li>We may individually be promised different things. The path of everyone is unique.</li>
</ol>
<p>But we’re all promised eternal life if we follow the Lord (eternal happiness):</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Verily I say unto you, ye shall both have according to your desires, for ye both joy in that which ye have desired. <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-7.8">Doctrine and Covenants 7.8</a></p>
</blockquote>




<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>faith</category>
  <category>covenant</category>
  <category>individual covenant</category>
  <category>promised blessings</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-5-trusting-a-promise.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 22:59:28 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Church Culture of Missionary work</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/sacrament-talk-on-missionary-work.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A friend gave a talk in church about missionary work, which is the Lord’s invitation to share His gospel and good news with the world. Having been a missionary for two years, it’s much less about “effective sales” strategies and much more about trying to live like a good person and invite others to enjoy the benefits of following Christ.</p>
<p>I bring up the point about sales because a lot of people outside of the church can see LDS missionaries as salespeople. To one degree, they are: they’re trying to change people’s belief system. Adopt Christianity. <sup>1</sup></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;From the ultra cynical: “they just want more tithing!” But, like, if you think about it this argument doesn’t work in so many ways. Mainly that the missionaries are paying to be there (don’t get any tithing) and most of tithing goes to maintaining the church (buildings, books, temples, missions, etc).</p></li></div><p>Yea, that’s certainly a reasonable way to look at it from one angle. But the reality is more like “I have something that’s great and I want other people to benefit from it the same way I benefit from it”. Or better said: there’s so much…misinformation about my church and Christianity in general, how do I have a productive conversation with you about it without knowing where you are? I’d love to talk to you about it, but are you deeply inwardly vehemently against it for some obtuse reason I’m not aware of? That’s what provoked some fear in sharing His good news.</p>
<p>But these fears aren’t warranted. Because that isn’t the right focus from my end. The best focus for “missionary work” is: if I have something that’s great in my life, I should share it like anything else great in my life.</p>
<p>Did I see a good movie over the weekend? Great, share it. Did i hear a great talk on Sunday at church? Great, share it. Did I have a good hike? Awesome, share it. Did I have a funny experience while teaching some kids on Sunday? Yea, dope. Share it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-orange-juice-rainforest.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Mind if I drink this? Oh, you’d like some? I didn’t want to offend you by offering but sure I’d love to share - Elder Uchtdorf analogy paraphrased</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<p>Things I liked from my friends talk:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Over the past several months, (my wife) and I have implemented a new fad into our lives in an attempt to improve our well-being, which is the practice of cold plunging. Some of you may have heard of this trend as many gurus talk about it on social media because of its benefits, such as reducing stress and mood enhancement. Cold plunging is submerging your body in very cold water (typically around 50 degrees) for a period of 3 to 6 minutes. Sounds absolutely terrible, right? Well, it is terrible! No matter how many times we do it, it is still very hard and very uncomfortable. Nonetheless, we continue to do it, almost every day, because of the way it makes us feel afterwards. Immediately after getting out of the water I feel alert, energized and confident I can tackle the tasks of the day. Sitting in that cold water is always uncomfortable, but the discomfort is always worth it. <strong>By having felt what’s on the other side, I can get comfortable with the uncomfortable.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This cold plunge analogy is interesting: because it’s always hard. Always intimidating. I think that’s true in my personal experience. But for me it’s more like… the opposite of hyperextending my knee.</p>
<p>When I was in high school I got a knee injury. I hyperextended it. The first time was incredibly painful. I was out a few days. But then I came back and was fine-ish. Then a few weeks later I did it again. Then a few days later: again. By the end of the season, I was hyperextending it every other day. It was bad news. A few weeks after the season ended I was playing in a bball tournament and again big hyperextending.</p>
<p>I stopped playing sports that summer and let myself heal up. Haven’t had problems since.</p>
<p>Same with sharing the gospel, but the opposite. At first it’s really intimidating. You do it once and you realize it’s not that bad. Then the more you do it the more it becomes part of your day.</p>
<p>Kinda like writing in this blog. At first I’m trying to find my voice. Now I don’t care and just want to write. I hope it’s beneficial for you.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>On the other hand, some may be thinking none of those sound any easier and maybe you sometimes feel that you aren’t contributing because missionary work is generally intimidating and uncomfortable to you. That is OKAY. <strong>All efforts, no matter how small, are important and impactful.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This reminded me of <a href="../concepts/president-russel-m-nelson.html">President Russel M. Nelson</a>’s invitation:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Anytime you do anything that helps anyone—on either side of the veil﻿—take a step toward making covenants with God and receiving their essential baptismal and temple ordinances, you are helping to gather Israel. It is as simple as that. <a href="../scriptures/hope-of-israel">Hope of Israel</a></p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>As a missionary in (Some Area) I had one mission president for my first year and another for my second year. Both presidents elevated the success of the mission with different approaches and leadership styles. In my first year under my first mission president, the mission accomplished a big goal of doubling the number of baptisms from the previous year. During this time our mission president wasn’t fond of us spending too much time with members and our success came from focusing on other areas of the work. By contrast, my second mission president changed the culture and encouraged us to spend as much time with the members as we could, even if we did not have someone to teach with the members. He taught us to focus on the number of lessons with a member participating as the most important key indicator. As a result, the mission’s baptisms started to skyrocket and the number more than doubled again. I know that our success can be attributed to us striving to have as many members as possible participating in our lessons and our emphasis on members and missionaries working together.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If your note a member of the church you may balk at “baptism skyrocketing”. It kinda gives a cultish vibe if that’s how you see it - our goal is to baptize everyone!! I get it. Not great language from the outsider’s perspective <em>if</em> that’s how you see it.</p>
<p>Having been a member of the church my whole life, I’ve heard this rhetoric a lot - get baptisms. But I think this is more of a sociological misrepresentation of a deeply inward desire to share what’s good in your life with others.</p>
<p>Do I want to baptize the world? Umm…do I want everyone to have world peace? Yea.</p>
<p>Will baptizing someone give them peace? No.&nbsp;Well, not <em>just</em> dunking yourself in a hot-tub sized mini pool.</p>
<p>Will someone who has a sincere desire to follow Christ the rest of their life benefit from being baptized because it gives them a chance to publicly commit to following Christ and thus be supported by a community of like-minded people also trying to self-improve constantly? Yea. Baptism would be great here.</p>
<p>Do I want to baptize everyone? No.&nbsp;I <em>would</em> love it if everyone desired to follow Jesus a little more in their life. Learn a little more about him. So, yea I want everyone to be baptized.</p>
<p>This is the spirit which my friend is describing.</p>
<p>So doubling baptisms is this notion of a very fascinating cultural experience: we have as a church more success in helping other people discover the joy of following Christ by <em>how</em> we package “the message”. Yea, it’s sales at some level. What’s a better strategy? Cold calling or referrals? Always referrals. There’s trust there. The product doesn’t seem as strange. Likewise, it takes a lot to change a set of religious beliefs. Having seen someone you know and enjoy associating with benefit from the religion helps make it more palatable at first to begin discussions.</p>
<p>Lastly, this strategy is fascinating: focus on teaching people who already believe in God about <em>why</em> they believe in God, or more about His story. These refreshers help enliven the mind, no different than perhaps me going back to some Stat 121 material and just really appreciating its elegance (even though I do more advanced math in my day to day). Teach people the basics and they’ll remember what they love about it.</p>
<hr>
<p>End/rant.</p>




<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>opinion</category>
  <category>lds culture</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/sacrament-talk-on-missionary-work.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 21:05:30 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 4 - Why not?</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-4-why-not.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Nephi asks a faith-opening question:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>for behold he is mightier than all the earth, <strong>then why not mightier than</strong> Laban and his fifty, yea, or even than his tens of thousands? <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-4.1">1 Nephi 4.1</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>As I wrote in <a href="../christianity/unknown-god.html">An Unknown God</a>, Nephi demonstrates the ability to find a way with his questioning. Instead of asking doubtfully, he asks faithfully.</p>
<p>It reminds me of Enoch:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>31 And when Enoch had heard these words, he bowed himself to the earth, before the Lord, and spake before the Lord, saying: <strong>Why is it that I have found favor in thy sight</strong>, and am but a lad, and all the people hate me; for I am slow of speech; wherefore am I thy servant? 32 And the Lord said unto Enoch: <strong>Go forth and do</strong> as I have commanded thee, and no man shall pierce thee. <a href="../scriptures/moses-6.31-32">Moses 6.31–32</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Lord didn’t tell him why he was chosen. He just said “go forth”.</p>
<p>The Lord’s thoughts are above our thoughts. Too often we put limiting beliefs on ourselves - I’m not good enough, why me? Or, why would God want to help me?</p>
<p>Why not instead ask, “why <em>wouldn’t</em> Heavenly Father want to help me? He loves me and has promised he <em>would</em> help me.”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-why-wouldn't-an-angel.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Angels want to help</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I love this quote by Jared after just going through something really hard:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass that Jared spake again unto his brother, saying: Go and inquire of the Lord whether he will drive us out of the land, and if he will drive us out of the land, cry unto him whither we shall go. <strong>And who knoweth but the Lord will carry us forth into a land which is choice above all the earth?</strong> And if it so be, let us be faithful unto the Lord, that we may receive it for our inheritance. <a href="../scriptures/ether-1.38">Ether 1.38</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just lost your job? Who knoweth but the Lord will provide a better one? Just lost your house? Who knoweth but the Lord will give you a promised land? (They had lost their jobs and house and were wandering at this point.) I love the optimism here.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-4-why-not.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2024 23:23:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 3 - Dreamed a Dream</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-3-dreamed-a-dream.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A great quote leading up to MLK Jr day:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Behold I have dreamed a dream <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-3.2">1 Nephi 3.2</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Lehi dreamed many dreams. It got him in trouble with his boys, as Laman and Lemuel “did murmur in many things against their father, <strong>because he was a visionary man</strong>” (<a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-2.11">1 Nephi 2.11</a>).</p>
<p>Lehi’s wife, Sariah, also murmured against him, “she also had complained against my father, <strong>telling him that he was a visionary man;</strong> saying: Behold thou hast led us forth from the land of our inheritance, and my sons are no more, and we perish in the wilderness.” (<a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.2">1 Nephi 5.2</a>)</p>
<p>Lehi’s response to this is great:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I <strong>know that I am a visionary man</strong>; for if I had not seen the things of God in a vision I should not have known the goodness of God, but had tarried at Jerusalem, and had perished with my brethren. But behold, I have obtained a land of promise, in the which things I do rejoice; yea, and I know that the Lord will deliver my sons out of the hands of Laban, and bring them down again unto us in the wilderness. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.4-5">1 Nephi 5.4–5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This response teaches me a few things:</p>
<ul>
<li>when people struggle, they can complain against a good thing and make it a bad thing. “Why do you always have to be such a goodie two shoes?”</li>
<li>The response is “if I weren’t such a goodie two shoes I’d be miserable”. Helps remind people of the value of their own biases.</li>
</ul>
<p>Complaining is a natural part of life. Just be careful what you complain about.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-3-dreamed-a-dream.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 22:52:51 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lint</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/poem-lint.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="lint" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lint">Lint</h2>
<pre><code>Lint between your fingers
Lint between your toes
Where does it comes from?
Only the windtraps know

You clench it like a prized possession
Its presence makes you my obsession</code></pre>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-baby-feet.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Cute toes</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Seriously, it’s like a <a href="https://dune.fandom.com/wiki/Windtrap">windtrap</a> of Arrakis (<a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>). Just appears.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>babies</category>
  <category>parenting</category>
  <category>poem</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/poem-lint.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2024 23:50:31 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 2 - Receiving a promised land</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-2-receiving-a-promised-land.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>While Lehi wandered in the wilderness, Nephi recounted he left the “land of his inheritance”:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass that he departed into the wilderness. And he left his house, and the land of his inheritance, and his gold, and his silver, and his precious things, and took nothing with him, <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-2.4">1 Nephi 2.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-leaving-the-promised-land.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Leaving the promised land</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Yet by the end of the Chapter, Nephi is promised a land of inheritance:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And inasmuch as ye shall keep my commandments, ye shall prosper, and shall be led to a land of promise; yea, even a land which I have prepared for you; yea, a land which is choice above all other lands. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-2.20">1 Nephi 2.20</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Amazing how they lose one thing but gain another. Also amazing is how they had prophets warning them of Jerusalem’s destruction - why didn’t the Lord make <em>those</em> prophets leave?</p>
<p>He has a plan for us individually.</p>
<p>CS Lewis remarked something along the lines of “We don’t chase God, God chases us”.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Both Malcolm Muggeridge and C.S. Lewis attest to this. Muggeridge wrote, “I had a notion that somehow, besides questing, I was being pursued.” Lewis said that, “…night after night…I sensed the steady, unrelenting approach of Him whom I so earnestly desired not to meet. Finally, I gave in, and admitted that God was God, and knelt and prayed…” (<a href="https://www.stettlerindependent.com/community/man-can-not-sidestep-thinking-about-god-faith-and-reflection-6606319">link</a>, also discussed in <a href="../book-review/the-oxford-inklings-lewis-tolkien-and-their-circle.html">The Oxford Inklings: Lewis, Tolkien and Their Circle</a>) (<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/681434-you-must-picture-me-alone-in-that-room-in-magdalen">good reads link</a>)</p>
</blockquote>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>covenant</category>
  <category>individual covenant</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-2-receiving-a-promised-land.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2024 10:52:34 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Find the Fun</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/find-the-fun.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-find-the-fun.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Find the fun</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Kid screaming? why?</p>
<p>Milk on the floor? why is that a funny thing?</p>
<p>Poop on the ground? (<a href="../creative/poem-the-dove-forevermore.html">The Dove (Forevermore)</a>) It won’t last. it’s endearing.</p>
<p>No, this isn’t just fanciful thinking - this is a choice. You’ve chosen to be angry at that spilled milk, lost your cool when bro slapped sis, and walked out of the room when you heard that last cry for “more breakfast!!”.</p>
<p>But <em>why</em> did you get overwhelmed? Stressed about all there is to do, and now there’s one more thing? Stressed about “am i a good parent”? Stressed about raising your kids right and you have to instruct them on everything they do wrong in order to do that?</p>
<p>My new philosophy: Kids are kids. They’re optimizers. Anyone in tech knows that an optimizer is a thing trying to find the optimal point of another thing. It’s like battleships - you keep guessing until you find. Then you guess around until you get all the points, until you know where to look.</p>
<p>Kids do this all day. They say something crazy trying to get a reaction. They say a not-funny joke 100 times until it’s funny again. Humans do that too.</p>
<p>So they’re optimizing. Exploring. Exploiting. That’s all their doing - exploring the space, exploiting the emotional signal.</p>
<p>Knowing that, find the fun in the moment. They won’t always be like this. And when it’s gone, you’ll wish it wasn’t. <a href="../creative/poem-the-dove-forevermore.html">The Dove (Forevermore)</a></p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>parenting</category>
  <category>mental health</category>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>A/B testing</category>
  <category>mindset</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/find-the-fun.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2024 10:26:44 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
  <title>Stop trying to change people. Stop it.</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/stop-trying-to-change-people.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>One thing I’ve seen a lot of people, including myself, do is try to change other people.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-chameleon-and-iguana.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Come on! Why won’t you chang  <title>Stop trying to change people. Stop it.</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/stop-trying-to-change-people.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>One thing I’ve seen a lot of people, including myself, do is try to change other people.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-chameleon-and-iguana.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Come on! Why won’t you change colors?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’m not sure why this is or why we do this. Perhaps we want others to be happier and we feel in our own egos that we know the better way. Perhaps we want our own problems to go away. Etc. etc.</p>
<p>The gospel isn’t about healing others. The gospel of Jesus is about individuals coming to Him for personal healing.</p>
<p>We can pray for others, sure. But what’s the point of that prayer?</p>
<ul>
<li>To ask Heaven to send good vibes to someone else or,</li>
<li>to have the <em>process</em> of praying change <em>our</em> own hearts. (<a href="../christianity/the-power-of-habitual-prayer.html">The Power of Habitual Prayer</a>)</li>
</ul>
<p>When we pray, it changes us. <em>What</em> changes us? <em>He</em> does. Heavenly Father changes us through the power of the Savior’s atonement. Prayer is never about changing other people’s hearts, even if you pray their heart might be softened. But by praying for their heart to be softened, it actually softens your own heart.</p>
<p>When Alma and their people prayed for deliverance from captivity, they prayed for softened hearts:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Therefore they hushed their fears, and began to cry unto the Lord that he would soften the hearts of the Lamanites… <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-23.28">Mosiah 23.28</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The hearts softened, but the more important thing that happened is that they developed enough faith in the Lord in order to be able to sneak out and not be afraid of being hunted down or what not. Like the Israelites in Egypt it can be dangerous to just go into the desert. Takes a lot of faith. But the prayers and Miracles of Moses softened the Israelite’s hearts and prepared them to follow Moses.</p>
<p>But what about Alma praying for his kids?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Behold, the Lord hath heard the prayers of his people, and also the prayers of his servant, Alma, who is thy father; for he has prayed with much faith concerning thee that thou mightest be brought to the knowledge of the truth; <strong>therefore, for this purpose have I come to convince thee of the power and authority of God, that the prayers of his servants might be answered according to their faith.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-27.14">Mosiah 27.14</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Surely this is about God sending an angel to change someone. Pray hard and miracles happen, even if they don’t see an angel.</p>
<p>But the reality is more nuanced.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And now I say unto thee, Alma, go thy way, and seek to destroy the church no more, that their prayers may be answered, <strong>and this even if thou wilt of thyself be cast off</strong>. <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-27.16">Mosiah 27.16</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The angel didn’t come to change Alma.</p>
<p>But you’d think there would be a strong correlation between seeing an angel and changing your ways though, right? A piece of counter evidence is found with Laman and Lemuel who were visited by an angel while bearing up Nephi:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And after the angel had departed, Laman and Lemuel <strong>again began to murmur</strong>, saying: How is it possible that the Lord will deliver Laban into our hands? Behold, he is a mighty man, and he can command fifty, yea, even he can slay fifty; then why not us? <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-3.31">1 Nephi 3.31</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Or what about the people who saw Jesus heal and then condemn him for doing so on a Sunday? Evidence abounds that spiritual encounters don’t forcibly change us. Angelic visitations don’t change us. Jesus appearing to people didn’t change them.</p>
<p>This is agency. This is Heavenly Father’s plan.</p>
<p>When Alma saw the angel, the angel said “I’m visiting you to answer the prayers of your dad.” So yes, absolutely, the Lord does things on our behalf <em>because</em> we pray. But he doesn’t change us.</p>
<p>This very same angel gave Alma an out: “even if thou wilt of thyself be cast off”…The angel gave agency. But Alma could easily have acted like Laman and Lemuel or the Pharisees and hardened his heart. It’s also why the Lord was able to do many miracles in the Americas that he couldn’t do in Jerusalem (3 Nephi): they had faith. They chose to follow Him. They had agency.</p>
<p>The gospel isn’t about us changing others through prayer. It’s about us allowing the Savior to change our hearts. This same scripture could be applied when trying to change another person:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>why beholdest thou the mote that is in thy brother’s eye, but considerest not the beam that is in thine own eye? <a href="../scriptures/matthew-7.3">Matthew 7.3</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Or this:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>When we feel hurt, angry, or envious, it is quite easy to judge people. This topic could actually be taught in a two-word sermon. When it comes to hating, gossiping, ignoring, ridiculing, holding grudges, or wanting to cause harm, please apply the following:</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Stop it! <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/friend/2013/06/stop-it?lang=eng">Uchtdorf</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Instead, find the good in others. Focus on changing and improving yourself to be more understanding, more accepting, more go with the flow.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>prayer</category>
  <category>agency</category>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <category>perspective</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/stop-trying-to-change-people.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 13:16:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
>>>>>>>-Updated upstrea
: he was>>>>>>>+Stashed changes
 Second, he had a vision.</p>
<p>But that’s not how the vision came. First, it began with prayer.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wherefore it came to pass that my father, Lehi, as he went forth prayed unto the Lord, yea, even with all his heart, in behalf of his people. And it came to pass as he prayed unto the Lord, there came a pillar of fire and dwelt upon a rock before him; and he saw and heard much; and because of the things which he saw and heard he did quake and tremble exceedingly. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-1.5-6">1 Nephi 1.5–6</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>So here’s the order:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Lehi listens to prophets that Jerusalem will be destroyed (4)</li>
<li>Lehi prays for his people, hoping they won’t be (5)</li>
<li>Lehi sees a pillar of fire, sees many things (6)</li>
<li>Lehi returns home (assumes he’s not home), and is overcome with what he saw (7)</li>
<li>Lehi then has another, more pronounced vision (8)</li>
</ol>
<p>What a way to start off the Book of Mormon: this is a book about personal revelation, written by people who had revelations, and it teaches us the pattern. In this case, we care about others. When we do, the heavens open as we pray.</p>
<p>We prob won’t have visions, but we <em>will</em> have the spirit.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I will give unto the children of men line upon line, precept upon precept, here a little and there a little; and blessed are those who hearken unto my precepts, and lend an ear unto my counsel, for they shall learn wisdom; for <strong>unto him that receiveth I will give more</strong> <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-28.30">2 Nephi 28.30</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-pillar-of-fire-on-rock.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Pillar of fire on a rock</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>scripture of the day</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>revelation</category>
  <category>prophets</category>
  <category>epistemology</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-Nephi-1-he-prepares-us-to-teach-us.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 09:29:53 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2024-01-14 Come Follow Me CTR 7 Jan 7-14</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-14-jan-14.html</link>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
=======
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="summary" class="level1">
<h1>Summary</h1>
<p>This week I’ve learned how much doctrine is captured in the first five chapters of the Book of Mormon. I didn’t know Lehi saw a pillar. I studied how Sariah had to wait on the Lord and that all promises are filled in His own time and way. There’s doctrine in how to respond to people when they’re complaining (good parenting tips). To have a positive attitude when things are crazy: ask “why not?”</p>
</section>
<section id="studies" class="level1">
<h1>Studies</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-1-praying-for-other-people.html">1 Nephi 1 - Praying f>>>>>>>-Updated upstrea
<li><a h  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="summary" class="level1">
<h1>Summary</h1>
<p>This week I’ve learned how much doctrine is captured in the first five chapters of the Book of Mormon. I didn’t know Lehi saw a pillar. I studied how Sariah had to wait on the Lord and that all promises are filled in His own time and way. There’s doctrine in how to respond to people when they’re complaining (good parenting tips). To have a positive attitude when things are crazy: ask “why not?”</p>
</section>
<section id="studies" class="level1">
<h1>Studies</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-1-praying-for-other-people.html">1 Nephi 1 - Praying for Other People</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-Nephi-1-he-prepares-us-to-teach-us.html">1 Nephi 1 - He prepares us to teach us</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-2-receiving-a-promised-land.html">1 Nephi 2 - Receiving a promised land</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-3-dreamed-a-dream.html">1 Nephi 3 - Dreamed a Dream</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-4-why-not.html">1 Nephi 4 - Why not?</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-5-trusting-a-promise.html">1 Nephi 5 - Will a promise be delivered?</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="fhe-idea" class="level1">
<h1>FHE idea</h1>
<ul>
<li>study how a seed is planted.</li>
<li>Watch a video of how long it takes for seeds to come above ground. Some seeds pop up instantly (sprouts). Others can take many weeks. (Coco de Mer takes a few years to pop up). We’re above ground. The Lord is below ground. We just gotta keep watering and we’ll see what he’s promised to us pop up when He’s ready. Just gotta have faith.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level1">
<h1>Notes</h1>
<p>Miracles they saw: - Lehi’s vision 1 Nephi - Got the plates - Saw an angel</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me lesson plan</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-14-jan-14.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 09:20:44 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 1 - Praying for Other People</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-1-praying-for-other-people.html</link>
>>>>>>>+Stashed changes
hi-1-he-prepares-us-to-teach-us.html">1 Nephi 1 - He prepares us to teach us</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-2-receiving-a-promised-land.html">1 Nephi 2 - Receiving a promised land</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-3-dreamed-a-dream.html">1 Nephi 3 - Dreamed a Dream</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-4-why-not.html">1 Nephi 4 - Why not?</a></li>
<li><a href="../christianity/1-nephi-5-trusting-a-promise.html">1 Nephi 5 - Will a promise be delivered?</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="fhe-idea" class="level1">
<h1>FHE idea</h1>
<ul>
<li>study how a seed is planted.</li>
<li>Watch a video of how long it takes for seeds to come above ground. Some seeds pop up instantly (sprouts). Others can take many weeks. (Coco de Mer takes a few years to pop up). We’re above ground. The Lord is below ground. We just gotta keep watering and we’ll see what he’s promised to us pop up when He’s ready. Just gotta have faith.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="notes" class="level1">
<h1>Notes</h1>
<p>Miracles they saw: - Lehi’s vision 1 Nephi - Got the plates - Saw an angel</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me lesson plan</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-14-jan-14.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 09:20:44 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1 Nephi 1 - Praying for Other People</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-1-praying-for-other-people.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This scripture stood out to me:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wherefore it came to pass that my father, Lehi, as he went forth prayed unto the Lord, yea, even with all his heart, in behalf of his people. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-1.5">1 Nephi 1.5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>There are many verses like this, such as Enos praying for his people, or Christ saying “Oh Jerusalem”, or Enoch.</p>
<p>I’m reading <a href="../book-review/the-oxford-inklings-lewis-tolkien-and-their-circle.html">The Oxford Inklings: Lewis, Tolkien and Their Circle</a> right now and considered just how influenced these authors were by their surroundings. WWI, the rise of machines, etc.</p>
<p>Aren’t we all influenced by the people around us? What role do those people play in our lives? What role do the loved ones play in our lives? What role do we play in theirs?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-christ-praying-oh-jerusalem.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Oh Jerusalem</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/1-nephi-1-praying-for-other-people.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 23:59:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scriptures within Scriptures</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/scriptures-within-scriptures.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-white-fruit-delicious-zoom-in.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The Scriptures are precious and worth our time</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Nephi recounts how they had obtained some scriptures:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And <strong>we had obtained the records which the Lord had commanded us</strong>, and searched them and found that they were desirable; yea, even of great worth unto us, insomuch that we could preserve the commandments of the Lord unto our children. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.21">1 Nephi 5.21</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>A few things that stand out to me:</p>
<ul>
<li>He thought about his children. In <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-25.26">2 Nephi 25.26</a> it’s mentioned “that our children may know to what source they may look for a remission of their sins.”</li>
<li>They had the scriptures because they accomplished the task laid before them, “I know that the Lord giveth no commandments unto the children of men, save he shall prepare a way for them that they may accomplish the thing which he commandeth them.” <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-3.7.html">1 Nephi 3.7</a></li>
<li>These scriptures were “desirable”. Know what else is desirable? The fruit of the tree of life:</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And it came to pass that I beheld a tree, whose fruit was desirable to make one happy. <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-8.10">1 Nephi 8.10</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The scriptures, especially the Book of Mormon, are precious to help our families know of Christ, have been obtained and written by those obedient to Christ, and are desirable and great to consume.</p>
<p>In <a href="../tech/a-knife-to-a-gun-fight.html">A Knife to a Gun Fight: Why I’m off Social Media</a>, I talk about how tech workers talk of social media as “snackable content”. Frequently the word “consumption” is used to describe how app “users” “consume” content.</p>
<p>It’s mostly not the stuff worth consuming in great quantities. Don’t settle for snacks. Enjoy a feast:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Wherefore, do not spend <strong>money</strong> for that which is of no worth, nor your labor for that which cannot satisfy. Hearken diligently unto me, and remember the words which I have spoken; and come unto the Holy One of Israel, and <strong>feast upon that which perisheth not</strong>, neither can be corrupted, and <strong>let your soul delight in fatness.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-9.51">2 Nephi 9.51</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>Replace “money” with “time”.</em></p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>scripture of the day</category>
  <category>scriptures</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/scriptures-within-scriptures.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 23:33:40 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My testimony: Moving across the Country</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/my-testimony-2024-01-07.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>Today is fast Sunday, a day when testimonies are shared in church. Here’s my testimony I shared today. Someone had just spoken about moving to a new place and seeing God in their lives, even if it was far away from where they had thought they needed to be. They had moved away from family.</em></p>
<p>I was reminded today of why I live where I do. Without going into personal details, as a family we decided it was time to leave the east coast and move west. As I wondered how it might be possible, I was encouraged by my wife to reach out to an old contact on a random spreadsheet I had kept seven years prior when I was first looking for jobs. The guy had since changed jobs from when he had interviewed me, but he referred me to his new company.</p>
<p>Well, this company was otherwise impossible to get noticed at, even with referrals. Turns out this guy was a lot higher than I had known. It was enough to get me the first interview. Four years later we’re still on the west coast. It’s definitely a better situation for our family in many ways.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-u-haul-moving.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Moving because when we had a desire, the Lord opened the door for us</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And in terms of family, I grew up living far away from cousins. My church congregation became my family. My parents friends became my Sunday school teachers and mentors. My friends at church became my closest confidants and kept me company in living the principles I believed in.</p>
<p>Recently, this church family helped us with meals, gifts, and emotional warmth. I don’t know what I’d do without belonging to a group of people who care for one another (I know many communities are like this, but I think it’s extra special in a Christian context where everyone wants to help and strengthen each other in kindness. We all try their best.)</p>
<p>Christ’s design that we have a church is inspired:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>There is <strong>one body, and one Spirit</strong>, even as ye are called in one hope of your calling; One Lord, one faith, one baptism, One God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all. <a href="../scriptures/ephesians-4.4-6">Ephesians 4.4–6</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>And are we not all family? The spiritual children of Christ and sons and daughters of Heavenly Father.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And now, because of the covenant which ye have made <strong>ye shall be called the children of Christ, his sons, and his daughters;</strong> for behold, this day he hath spiritually begotten you; for ye say that your hearts are changed through faith on his name; therefore, ye are born of him and have become his sons and his daughters. … therefore, I would that ye should take upon you the name of Christ… <a href="../scriptures/mosiah-5.7-8">Mosiah 5.7–8</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I testify the <a href="../concepts/hand-of-god.html">Hand of God</a> is real. He leads and guides people to where they need to be gathered. And when we gather together as one body, miracles happen.</p>
<hr>
<p>I also love this scripture, how Lehi was guided to a “land of promise”.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>behold, I <strong>have obtained</strong> a land of promise <a href="../scriptures/1-nephi-5.5">1 Nephi 5.5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>He wrote “have obtained” while he was struggling for food and water in the desert. He saw ahead to when he’d eventually live in a near rain forest paradise.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>fast sunday</category>
  <category>my testimony</category>
  <category>memories</category>
  <category>let god prevail</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/my-testimony-2024-01-07.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 14:52:13 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What does it mean to preside?</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/what-does-it-mean-to-preside.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The responsibility of a Father is to preside:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>By divine design, <strong>fathers are to preside over their families in love and righteousness</strong> and are responsible to provide the necessities of life and protection for their families. <a href="../scriptures/the-family-proclamation">The Family Proclamation</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve long wondered what this meant. Earlier in my marriage I wondered: does this mean a father leads all family gatherings, has the first or last word, or delegates who says the prayer? That’s probably because the word “preside” is used synonymously with lead with respect to church callings and such:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Verily, I say unto you, saith the Lord of Hosts, there must needs be presiding elders to <strong>preside</strong> over those who are of the office of an elder; And also priests to <strong>preside</strong> over those who are of the office of a priest; 62 And also teachers to preside <strong>over</strong> those who are of the office of a teacher, in like manner, and also the deacons <a href="../scriptures/doctrine-and-covenants-107.60-62">Doctrine and Covenants 107.60–62</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I never really wondered if this was “who calls the shots”, or “who runs the show” - that never felt like a thing because my father is a gentle, servant leader. But I know some wonder what the details of this phrase mean. And what does it mean for single moms?</p>
<p>Well, I recently learned what <em>I</em> think it means. I started getting slightly more-than-average stressed with being sleep deprived after having a newborn.</p>
<p>I noticed, by consequence, my kids appeared more agitated. I remembered my <a href="../posts/your-mood-is-contagious.html">Mood is Contagious</a>.</p>
<p>Once I got more sleep, I realized the kids model my behavior as a father than follow my words. The way I talk to them is how they talk to each other - for better or worse.</p>
<p>Every parent knows this.</p>
<p>So while “preside” technically means to lead a meeting, it also means to lead a gathering. Is a family not a gathering?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>…how oft have I gathered you as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings, and have nourished you. And again, how oft would I have gathered you as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings, <a href="../scriptures/3-nephi-10.4-5">3 Nephi 10.4–5</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-water-color-a-mother-hen-with-a-chicken-under-her-wing-as-its-raining.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Shouldn’t we preside more like this?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Maybe we can preside more like Christ: with kindness, gentleness, and love unfeigned.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>doctrine and covenants</category>
  <category>priesthood</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <category>the family a proclamation to the world</category>
  <category>parenting</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/what-does-it-mean-to-preside.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 13:37:28 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Vaulted Ceilings</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/vaulted-ceiling.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Every chapel I’ve been in has a vaulted, high ceiling. This is common across many church architectures.</p>
<p>It reminds me of the stable where he was born. It reminds me of above, how he came down. It reminds me that there’s space for everyone. Even if it’s crowded on the ground, there’s a ton of space Above. This is why he came: to make space for all of us.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For God so loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have everlasting life. <a href="../scriptures/john-3.16">John 3.16</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-lds-chapel.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">A simple chapel with vaulted ceilings</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/media/image/cedar-city-tabernacle-interior-2e43275?lang=eng">Source: Chapel with vaulted ceilings</a></p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>sacrament symbol</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/sacrament-symbols/vaulted-ceiling.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 10:30:10 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
=======
<item>
  <title>2024-01-07 Come Follow Me CTR 7 Jan 1-7</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-07-jan-7.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>5 min intro.</p>
<section id="book-of-mormon-overview-10m" class="level1">
<h1>Book of Mormon overview (10m)</h1>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3dNYpXZIN_c?si=dFOPuGvklJ1XOK2k" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</section>
<section id="keystone-activity-10m" class="level1">
<h1>Keystone Activity (10m)</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“I told the brethren that the Book of Mormon was the most correct of any book on earth, and the keystone of our re>>>>>>>-Updated upstrea
et nearer to God by abiding by its precepts, than by any other book.” <a href="../scriptures/introduction">Introduction</a></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-tip no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Activity
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Bring magnitiles. Have them try to build a triangle without any supporting pieces.</p>
<p>Test the strength of their creations. Pull out one piece and see if it falls.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="read-the-book-of-mormon-daily" class="level1">
<h1>Read the Book of Mormon Daily</h1>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-tip no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Activity
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Have the kids write down some things they do every day.</li>
<li>Is the Book of Mormon one of them?</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<p>Goal: spiritual closeness with the Savior every day.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The voices and pressures of the world are engaging and numerous. But too many voices are deceptive, seductive, and can pull us off the covenant path. To avoid the inevitable heartbreak that follows, I plead with you today to counter the lure of the world by <strong>making time for the Lord in your life—each and every day.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/russell-m-nelson-make-time-for-the-lord">“Make Time for the Lord”, Russell M. Nelson</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Read the Book of Mormon every day</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>My dear brothers and sisters, <strong>I promise that as you prayerfully study the Book of Mormon every day, you will make better decisions—every day</strong>. I promise that as you ponder what you study, the windows of heaven will open, and you will receive answers to your own questions and direction for your own life. I promise that as you daily immerse yourself in the Book of Mormon, you can be immunized against the evils of the day, even the gripping plague of pornography and other mind-numbing addictions. <a href="../scriptures/russell-m-nelson-the-book-of-mormon-what-would-your-life-be-like-without-it">“The Book of Mormon: What Would Your Life Be Like without It?”, Russell M. Nelson</a></p>
</blockquote>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>come follow me lesson plan</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/come-follow-me-2024-01-07-jan-7.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 08:58:34 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How I use the Book of Mormon</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/how-to-use-the-book-of-mormon.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The Book of Mormon is the most powerful book I’ve read.</p>
<p>This is how I get the most out of the book:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I say unto you that ye must pray always, and not faint; that ye <strong>must not perform any thing unto the Lord save in the first place ye shall pray unto the Father</strong> in the name of Christ, that <strong>he will consecrate thy performance unto thee</strong>, that thy performance may be for the welfare of thy soul. <a href="../scriptures/2-nephi-32.9">2 Nephi 32.9</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve read a lot of self help books. It’s not like that. This is a book that inspires personal revelation and a relationship with Christ and Heavenly Father. I get the most out of it when I have a true desire in my heart:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And when ye shall receive these things, I would exhort you that ye would ask God, the Eternal Father, in the name of Christ, if these things are not true; and if ye shall ask with a <strong>sincere heart, with real intent,</strong> having faith in Christ, he will manifest the truth of it unto you, by the power of the Holy Ghost. <a href="../scriptures/moroni-10.4">Moroni 10.4</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>When I read it in a rush, I don’t get much out of it. When I don’t pray before hand, or if I’m not sincere, I don’t really get anything substantive.</p>
<p>It’s like texting vs calling a friend. If you’re in a rush, you give a half thought text. But if you’re on a long drive and want to build a relationship, you give the friend a call.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-plant-a-seed-and-grow.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">If you plant a seed, you need to nourish it</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The best insight doesn’t come from the Book of Mormon. It comes from the Holy Ghost. So I can read the book as a literary critique and not see its divinity. But as I read it trying to build a relationship with Heavenly Father, then I feel that relationship grow.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Now, we will compare the word unto a seed. Now, if ye give place, that a seed may be <strong>planted in your heart</strong>, behold, if it be a true seed, or a good seed, if ye do not cast it out by your unbelief, that ye will resist the Spirit of the Lord, behold, it will begin to swell within your breasts; and when you feel these swelling motions, ye will begin to say within yourselves—It must needs be that this is a good seed, or that the word is good, for it beginneth to enlarge my soul; yea, it beginneth to enlighten my understanding, yea, it <strong>beginneth to be delicious to me.</strong> <a href="../scriptures/alma-32.28">Alma 32.28</a></p>
</blockquote>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>testimony</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/how-to-use-the-book-of-mormon.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 08:40:59 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>When a Person Changes their Perspective on Christ</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/a-change-in-witness.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The Book of Mormon had 12 witnesses of its divinity - the three spiritual testimonies by the Three Witnesses, the Eight Witnesses with a physical witness, and Joseph Smith, the one who translated it as prophet, seer, and revelator. Powerfully, all Three Witnesses left the church years later (1937/38) nearly 8-9 years after writing their testimony (1829), but never left their testimonies:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Despite differences with Joseph Smith that led each of the Three Witnesses to part ways individually with the Church (Cowdery and Harris later returned), they continued to affirm their testimony as witnesses throughout their lives. <a href="https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/history/topics/witnesses-of-the-book-of-mormon?lang=eng&amp;id=html">Witnesses of the Book of Mormon</a></p>
</blockquote>
<section id="when-a-loved-one-leaves-their-testimony" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>When a loved one leaves their testimony</h1>
<p>Let’s consider the world where these three denied their testimonies. (It’s easy to see that they “never doubted their own witness, therefore it must be true”.) But I think this is a sandy foundation because a thing should be true regardless of what three individuals say about it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-three-witnesses-one-missing.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">What if one had forsaken their testimony - would you still believe he saw it?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Those who believe in Christ hold strong beliefs in Him, and it must be a belief because they cannot see Him. They rely on the faith built on personal witness and also built by the testimony of others. But what do you do when a loved one abandons their testimony, or becomes an <a href="../book-review/unbelievable.html">unbeliever</a>? Do you doubt everything you learned from them? Perhaps.</p>
<p>Who do you trust - the “them” now that un-believes, or the “them” <em>then</em> that once believed?</p>
<p>Consider a hard-and-fast alternative: what if someone began doubting the existence of gravity? What if they were once your physics professor? Easy: you just go to the apple tree and demonstrate the principle by dropping an apple. “No, that’s magnetism”, the professor now claims.</p>
<p>You’re kind of stuck: well, if you think it’s magnetism, there’s not much I can do - this concept is called gravity. Similarly, people leave God’s path and believe the Hand of God that acts in their live is now, and always has been, just coincidence, luck, etc. what else could it be?</p>
<p>But what is coincidence? Luck? (I ponder these things often as a statistician. For another time…)</p>
</section>
<section id="putting-a-name-on-a-concept" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Putting a name on a Concept</h1>
<p>There’s precedence for this - when Ammon appeared to the Lamanites, they thought he acted by the Great Spirit. Instead of telling them they were wrong, he instead clarified, “that great spirit <em>is</em> God”.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>26 And then Ammon said: Believest thou that there is a Great Spirit? 27 And he said, Yea. 28 And Ammon said: This is God. And Ammon said unto him again: Believest thou that this Great Spirit, who is God, created all things which are in heaven and in the earth?<br>
<a href="../scriptures/alma-18.26-28">Alma 18.26–28</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Likewise, when unbelievers doubt the Hand of God, or re-cast their old ways according to a <em>new</em> belief framework, perhaps they’re just labeling a concept in a different way. (It’s also really hard to know what someone once considered “God” vs not in their life, so take this point with a grain of salt.)</p>
<p>After all, when people leave God some claim they were under <a href="https://robjhyndman.com/unbelievable/ch4.html">confirmation bias</a>, the concept that you favor the evidence that supports your belief. Hyndman argues confirmation bias can go both ways, for believers and unbelievers, but <em>does</em> claim that evidence favors the skeptics because there should be evidence. I’d argue he relies solely on <em>physical</em> evidence. There is <em>spiritual</em> evidence to be considered. <em>Spiritual</em> evidence is what we believe in. It’s what the Three Witnesses relied on. It’s unprovable to anyone else, and only receivable by the Holy Ghost. If God exists, let Him reveal himself. Let Him prevail:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>But whom say ye that I am? 16 And Simon Peter answered and said, Thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God. 17 And Jesus answered and said unto him, Blessed art thou, Simon Bar-jona: for <strong>flesh and blood hath not revealed it unto thee, but my Father which is in heaven.</strong><br>
<a href="../scriptures/matthew-16.15-17">Matthew 16.15–17</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The most powerful thing about being a Christian is that <em>it cannot be proven</em> Christ <em>didn’t</em> exist or walk the earth. Even if you falsify the entire bible, erase history, or discover that “Mary” was an invented concept by some creed or counsel bound to oppress us - there’s still a question: did the Man exist? We can debate it. Pharisees debated if He was That Messiah. Nobody now can know, except God reveals it to them.</p>
<p>Why? Because to claim God doesn’t exist, or the plates weren’t real, you’d also have to have evidence. Counter-evidence <em>isn’t</em> evidence. Lack of evidence likewise. Don’t we continually find new fossils? New animals in the wild? Lack of evidence doesn’t mean they don’t exist.<sup>1</sup></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;The other side may say (as Hyndman) does), I might as well believe in the Tooth Fairy, or Santa, because I don’t have evidence they don’t exist. Fair. Then belief is a choice, and must follow the principle of “by their fruits ye shall know them”. Did Baal call down Fire? No, only Elijah’s God. “Was that story of the Bible invented?” Perhaps. If so, explain why living Christ’s gospel brings me joy? “Because they’re good principles”, well, what is good, if not God? “Well then why not Zeus, or Baal to be your God?”, because I believe in the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob - not the God of Baal. I believe the scriptures because they teach good things. “What about the misogyny, racism, war and killing in the Bible etc etc etc”, well, perhaps some was commanded by God for reasons and context we don’t have. Perhaps some of the Bible isn’t truely written. “If some isn’t true it’s all not true because parts of it say it’s all true”. Well, what’s true is true, what’s not isn’t. “Who’s to say what God inspired?” Well, who’s to say what’s not inspired? Only God. “We’re not getting anywhere”. Ahh, but we are. Because I believe in God, and after believing Him I exercised faith in His son to pray on His name and open myself to trying to follow His ways. I’m far from perfect, but once I did this, I received spiritual knowledge, and having seen more of the Hand of God in my life, I can say there are miracles of events I can’t explain by chance or delusion alone. Miracles only a loving God could produce. This is my knowledge, which follows faith. <a href="../scriptures/alma-32.34-36">Alma 32.34–36</a> And we also have the Book of Mormon, which is a powerful second witness of Christ that brought reality to the truth in the Bible, and continually helps me feel the fruits of the Spirit, which is the Holy Ghost telling me it’s true.</p></li><li id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;my whole life until 21 I had no idea Joseph Smith had so many (up to 42) wives. “Some say he was a womanizer, pimp, etc”. Perhaps. But perhaps he was a prophet commanded to do so. Were we there? God at one point commanded Abraham to raise seed and have many wives. “Maybe Abraham was a philanderer too.” Okay, but does that definition of chastity and virtue not depend on the very construction of marriage as ordained by God who married Adam and Eve as husband and wife? If it’s from God, it’s His law, and He chose the rules. “But Joseph altered the rules and made stuff up so he could get with women and teenagers.” Perhaps. That assumes we know him, he told us that, and he believed it to be true. So we’ll leave it as an opinion. In my opinion he followed a commandment from an Angel, despite me not understanding it entirely or being comfortable with the idea. Let the man speak for himself.</p></li></div><p>To prove the Abrahamic God doesn’t exist people just say “well I found all this stuff about the bible, about church leaders, etc” was wrong or misconstrued. So? First, we have to make sure the “new stuff” learned is actually true (could be a lie), but if it is true (that something you once believed is a lie or misunderstanding) we must find out how this fits into Christ’s bigger picture.<sup>2</sup></p>
<p>You can’t claim that Joseph Smith <em>didn’t</em> see God and that the <em>Three Witnesses</em> <em>didn’t</em> see the plates at some point. Because you weren’t there in 1829. Even if they <em>had</em> later denied, from reading <a href="../book-review/killers-of-the-flower-moon.html">Killers of the Flower Moon: the Osage Murders and the Birth of the FBI</a>, it’s quite clear how people can be manipulated in the courts of law, influenced by money, influenced by their own delusions, etc. Since delusions go both ways, relying on people at all isn’t how we learn the existence of a Divine. Peter learned of Christ’s divinity the way we all must (quote above). Show me the evidence, says the scientist in me: the <em>spiritual</em> evidence. # Flip Floppers on Both Sides</p>
<p>Floppers flip both ways. The quote above said another way: who’s witness do you trust - the <em>you</em> of today, the <em>you</em> of yesterday, or the <em>you</em> of tomorrow? We can all come and go with our testimonies. This is life. We must have an unalterable way to learn truth, one independent of our path.</p>
<p>We’ve got the Paul’s of the world who were once Christian persecutors who flip to believers, and we’ve got those who claimed Joseph Smith was a fallen prophet after being in vision with him.</p>
<p>We’re all more like Laman and Lemuel than we realize. We see things that make us believe, we come to God, and then we forget and wonder if they never happened.</p>
<p>We’re all flip floppers. Let us not seek truth alone from others, or even rely solely on the Prophet. Our testimonies must be on Christ, and learning truth by the Holy Ghost, who will then guide us to understand the words of prophets and imperfect leaders. It’s good science.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In coming days, it will not be possible to survive spiritually without the guiding, directing, comforting, and constant influence of the Holy Ghost.<br>
<a href="../scriptures/russell-m-nelson-revelation-for-the-church-revelation-for-our-lives">“Revelation for the Church, Revelation for Our Lives”, Russell M. Nelson</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’m glad the Three Witnesses never denied their testimonies, but I’m glad there’s a way to know the Book of Mormon is true without them. After all, those dudes didn’t answer my prayer about the book’s truth. Heavenly Father did.</p>


</section>


<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>come follow me</category>
  <category>book of mormon</category>
  <category>epistemology</category>
  <category>theology</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/a-change-in-witness.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 09:11:17 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Love Thy Neighbor, But Have Friends</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/love-thy-neighbor-but-have-friends.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Christ invited us to love our neighbors:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself: I am the Lord. <a href="../scriptures/leviticus-19.18">Leviticus 19.18</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But He himself had his friends: his disciples. He didn’t try hanging out with the Pharisees or the Romans. He spent time at dinner with his apostles and followers.</p>
<p>He had four brothers. Did he call them to apostleship? No.&nbsp;Did he <em>not</em> love them? No, he loved them.</p>
<p>He loved the Roman as much as he loved John the Beloved: enough to die for them and prepare the way for them to rejoin him in heaven.</p>
<p>But he also spent time with those he loved. What does this teach us about love?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-lunch-with-friends-impressionist.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Go get lunch with a friend</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>love</category>
  <category>family</category>
  <category>friendship</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/love-thy-neighbor-but-have-friends.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Share your testimony</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/share-your-testimony.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>At least a dozen people claimed to have seen the gold plates from which the Book of Mormon was translated by Joseph Smith.</p>
<p>There were the “Three Witnesses”, the “Eight Witnesses”, Emma Smith, Joseph Smith, and perhaps a few others.</p>
<p>What’s powerful to me is this testimony that the Eight shared:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>And we give our names unto the world, to witness unto the world that which we have seen. And we lie not, God bearing witness of it. <a href="../scriptures/testimony-of-eight-witnesses">Testimony of Eight Witnesses</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I admire any who live with such conviction. It calls to mind the John Hancock’s of the world.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Be it known unto all nations, kindreds, tongues, and people, unto whom this work shall come: <a href="../scriptures/testimony-of-eight-witnesses">Testimony of Eight Witnesses</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>We’re invited to “stand as witnesses of God at all times and in all things, and in all places that ye may be in,” (<a href="../scriptures/mosiah-18.9">Mosiah 18.9</a>), to share what we’ve seen.</p>
<p>May we stand boldly, which doesn’t mean confrontational, contentiously, or loudly. It just means unequivocally. Sincerely.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-three-witnesses.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Stand by what you know to be true. Stand together</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <category>testimony</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/share-your-testimony.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/the-church-of-jesus-christ-of-latter-day-saints.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’ve been a member of this church, also known as the Mormon church, my whole life. I’ve studied it, learned its history, and have come to believe that it provides a marvelous sense of purpose and guidance. I believe it teaches the most truth about Jesus Christ and His plan of happiness for us, and I believe it’s people (including my own) have a lot to learn from those teachings.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>christianity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity/the-church-of-jesus-christ-of-latter-day-saints.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
</channel>
</rss>
