<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-0.9.615</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Getting Things Done</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-reviews/2022-06-24-getting-things-done/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-reviews/2022-06-24-getting-things-done/photo.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>After 21% my takeaways are:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>“My mind is weighed down by all of the ideas of things I can do.” I waste my time on todos that are just “go to doctor”, but should be “schedule appointment to go to doctor”. Anything that only takes 2 min should be done immediately. Anything longer later. But I love that clarity - I’ve often written lots of todos but not from the “next action to take” perspective.</li>
<li>“Visions can be built from the ground up rather than just top down.” I’ve tried writing down big visions for my 10 year future and it never works for me. I’ve got anxiety when I try to think where I want to be in 10 years. I mean, I know I want to be happy, be best friends with my wife and kids and have meaningful relationships but whether I’m still a data scientist or a farmer by then is anyones guess. (I wanna keep my options open.) But as I look at the things on my todo list and “eventual” to do list, a different picture emerges. I know I want to be a writer (hence this blog), I know I want to travel to XYZ location, to be involved in giving back, etc. TLDR: I know things I want to experience in life. I don’t have to craft value statements and invent ideas of what to do (seems forced). Instead I can reflect on what’s currently exciting and important to me and categorize those things into high levels values/missions. This will help me when I need to prioritize so not every whim of an idea gets my attention.</li>
<li>GTD book just lays out what a todo is. It breaks down the problem of doing things (big and small) into what they are (time sensitive, someday, etc). Whether I’ll follow the system is up for debate, but I love the ideas so far. It very much fits my naturally organized mind, but may not work for more spontaneous folks that don’t like as much structure and list keeping.</li>
</ol>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-reviews/2022-06-24-getting-things-done/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-reviews/2022-06-24-getting-things-done/photo.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New ideas are distractingly exciting</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-23-new-ideas-are-distractingly-exciting/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>When a new idea comes to my mind, I want to act on it right away. Perhaps it’s an exciting analysis idea, a new business strategy I want to scope out, or a question to ask a team member.</p>
<p>But as I look back at my backlog of things to work on, all of these ideas were also equally exciting.</p>
<p>Why is it that new ideas have more weight than old ideas?</p>
<p>They say that effectiveness is working quickly on tasks. Efficiency is knowing what to work on. Discipline is the ability to overcome the excitement of a new idea and place it in proper context of all ideas. Sanity is actively saying no to many ideas so you don’t get inundated.</p>
<p>Perhaps a good strategy is to have a “gut check” for ideas. If they don’t pass the highest threshold then let them go.</p>
<p>Process:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>What’s the new idea?</li>
<li>What’s the potential impact? What would I do with the output of this idea?</li>
<li>How feasible is it?</li>
</ol>
<p>Step 3 is tricky because I don’t want a good idea to go to waste just because it’s hard. Judgment is weighing the trade off between impact and feasibility.</p>
<p>I like Google Forms for logging ideas. It’s easy to save a Google Form URL to the home screen of my iPhone to make logging new ideas easy. Grooming those ideas is important. Letting go of old ideas is essential. If only I could do the essential…</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>productivity</category>
  <category>priorities</category>
  <category>ideation</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-23-new-ideas-are-distractingly-exciting/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Downstream Impact</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-22-downstream-impact/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-22-downstream-impact/photo.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Online experiments are powerful tools to see the causal impact of a business strategy. Tweak something, see what users do.</p>
<p>The limitations of online experiments is that once you manipulate your user experience there’s no going back. Users are forever impacted by your choice.</p>
<p>If you give out a credit card with $100, $300, and $500 lines, people are going to spend more on the $500 line. They might also default more because they’re less able to pay back $500 than they are $100. As a result, you may lose these $500 users forever and might impact other aspects of their life, not to mention impact the marketing department’s strategy.</p>
<p>A group of users is like a single living organism, if you treat it like that. If you only measure one metric (conversion rate) on the entire massive audience, then you’ll optimize for the “average” user.</p>
<p>But nobody is average. We are all distinct. We fall into categories, sure. But to really optimize the whole business we need to optimize for pockets of users. Or, we just need to set up a system that’s personalized.</p>
<p>Takeaway? Personalize your experiments where possible. Consider the ethical and downstream impacts of the experiment.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>data science</category>
  <category>experimentation</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-22-downstream-impact/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-22-downstream-impact/photo.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Power of Party Pay by Visible</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-21-the-power-of-party-pay-by-visible/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-21-the-power-of-party-pay-by-visible/photo.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="visibles-party-pay-madness" class="level1">
<h1>Visible’s party pay madness</h1>
<p>Visible wireless offers $25 off to users who join a party. So a user who signs up to pay $50 for unlimited data can click one button to join a party and only have to pay $25/mo from then on. Why not just offer users $25 to begin with?</p>
<p>It’s really confusing to me as a user - why not just give me the $25 automatically if it takes nothing to join a group? Because of gamification.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-it-works" class="level1">
<h1>Why it works</h1>
<p>I think their strategy is as follows:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>They hope some people get brought in on marketing and never remember to activate a party pay. Let’s say this number is 20-40%. Perhaps these users fund the rest of the discounts.</li>
<li>Joining a party pay group for free is an easy way to make your customers win. I.e., a user gets $25 off for joining. Gimmicky, but I think it works. So a user has an immediate sense of gratification - a great way to build a strong emotional bond. “Click a button to get $25 off in perpetuity? Nice!” Anyone would agree this feels better than just starting off with $25.</li>
<li>This makes users want to share and tell others. Especially if customers feel they’ve gamed the system. Who today doesn’t like a hack?</li>
</ol>
<p>But even if (1) is wrong, and that 95% of people join a party I’m sure they’ve done the math to consider how many people they need to sign up to make the money work.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-larger-strategy" class="level1">
<h1>The Larger Strategy</h1>
<p>Why would Verizon cannibalize their own sales? I switched my wife out of a $70 unlimited plan on Verizon to a $25 plan on visible for the same service. Well some customers will stay with Verizon because of its prestige and the add on benefits. But users who are cutting the cord are going somewhere else, I’m thinking Verizon wants to stay ahead of the curve. It’s a race to the bottom, sure. But it doesn’t hurt to try to win the race.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>startups</category>
  <category>strategy</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-21-the-power-of-party-pay-by-visible/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-21-the-power-of-party-pay-by-visible/photo.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Products for dads</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-21-products-for-dads/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-21-products-for-dads/photo.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="products-i-enjoy-as-a-dad" class="level1">
<h1>Products I enjoy as a dad</h1>
<p>Third times a charm - I hope by(/if) kid number four I’ll have this all figured out. It’s amazing how I feel so new to it all despite raising two kids in the last five years. In starting fresh a third time I feel inspired to write down some things I’m rediscovering.</p>
<p>To anyone getting started on their baby journey, perhaps these suggestions can help. Your baby is definitely different than mine, so your mileage may vary! But since I’m still using this stuff five years later maybe it can help you too. Either way, congrats and good luck!</p>
<section id="products-i-still-use-on-baby-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="products-i-still-use-on-baby-3">Products I still use on baby 3</h3>
<p>Since I’m a mega influencer (on my very established data science blog here), I get paid $500 every time you click a link below. So please, go crazy.</p>
<p>I’ll also credit my wife for figuring out to buy these products in the first place.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Stretchy swaddle, like <a href="https://a.co/d/dir4b63">this</a>. I like stretchy swaddles because they’re forgiving. The cotton muslin swaddles are nice and soft, but if the fabric doesn’t stretch the right way you may have to redo the swaddle.</li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/d6MPwOc">Ollie swaddle</a> (nighttime). This thing is ridiculously overpriced for a swaddle. $70? Don’t get it. But if you do, I like it because its super easy to put on and very sturdy (hard for baby to break). At month 2 the baby gets strong and the basic swaddles are so easy to break. That and I feel like I’m gonna hurt my kid if I try to make a cotton swaddle unbreakable. Enter Velcro! I can be gentle on the swaddle but have it be unbreakable. There are a lot of random contraption swaddles that tie the baby up like a pretzel. This is your classic burrito. Insert baby, wrap right side, Velcro left side and you’re done.</li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/0nVYMOK">Ubbi Steel Odor Locking diaper</a>pail. I also hated the thought five years ago of shelling out $70 for a trash can. Five years since and the thing still performs. I know how well it’s working when garbage day rolls around and I open it to change it. Smells like a gentle coastal breeze, maybe. To this day my wife hasn’t changed it more than a time or two because thankfully I have an iron stomach and unfortunately she does not. Point is: it keeps the diaper smell inside (for the most part) and uses normal garbage bags (cost saver).</li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/akOhRqv">Baby K’tan Original Baby Wrap Carrier, Infant and Child Sling</a>. I’ve tried several carriers. Boba wraps take way too much patience to learn how to put on (patience I ran out of quickly as a new dad). This thing is just two circular fabric swaths, which means it takes two seconds to throw on. The convenience is huge - baby crying? Grab the carrier and snuggle up in 10 seconds or less.</li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/4dLDr0D">DockATot Deluxe+ Dock</a>. We just got one off Facebook marketplace for $50 for third kid. We got it because let’s be real - sleeping is hard. The hardest thing about sleeping is the uncertainty what’s happening on the other side of the room in the crib. Grunting. Coughing. Is baby waking up? Needs a pacifier? When it’s 5am and you’re on feeding three of the night, being able to just roll over and plop the little one into the co-sleeper and monitor the situation close up is nice.</li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/6fwsNIZ">4moms rockaRoo Baby Swing</a>. There are a thousand ways to solve the “where do I put my baby while cooking dinner” problem. We’ve liked this one.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="must-haves" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="must-haves">Must Haves</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>Dish soap. Honestly, nothing gets out a blowout stain like dish soap. That and drying in the sun is a miracle worker. (Apparently this is how <a href="https://blog.cottonbabies.com/cloth-diapering-101-sunning-your-cloth-diapers/">cloth diaper people do it.</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.verywellfamily.com/healing-diaper-rash-by-going-diaperless-289241#toc-raw-apple-cider-vinegar">Apple cider vinegar for diaper rash</a>. Once the little pimples appear, you’ll try anything to get them to go away. We just discovered this hack recently and I was delightfully surprised how easily it worked.</li>
<li><a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=CCI2EsJ-pEY">This is the right way to carry a car seat</a>. A friend of mine that has three kids didn’t know this was a thing until he saw me do it. It’s a thing. Do it! Your forearm will thank you.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="toddler-time" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="toddler-time">Toddler Time</h3>
<p>Down the road, these products have hit home runs for me.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/8c6jGRF">Munchkin Miracle 360 Trainer Cup</a>. Every time I put this cup together I consider applying to Munchkin for a job to be their sales rep. This company has very clever designs on their products and this one just crushes it for me. Acts like a normal cup. Performs like a sippy. (I’ll admit I’ve taken a few swigs out of this just to understand how it works!)</li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/aNxfM8f">Contigo Spill-Proof Kids Tumbler</a>. I think we have 80 water bottles in a junk drawer somewhere. Cheap ones. Expensive ones. They all end up scattered in pieces like the zebra herd before the lion that is your innocent child. This cup is no exception: I’ve lost a straw on one already. But! If you want a water bottle you’ll have the problem of spare parts. (Uhh, this isn’t a recommendation so far…) So why this cup? This cup is just good. I don’t know. It’s easy to assemble and clean (wide top). Doesn’t spill. Kids like straws?</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="books" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="books">Books</h3>
<p>Not that you’ll have time to read…</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/9XvE8ll">The Happiest Baby on the Block; Fully Revised and Updated Second Edition: The New Way to Calm Crying and Help Your Newborn Baby Sleep Longer</a>. I’m sure there’s a quick YouTube video showing the 5 ways to sooth a baby. (Here’s an <a href="https://www.happiestbaby.com/blogs/baby/the-5-s-s-for-soothing-babies">article</a>.) But if you like books this is a good one. TLDR: sucking, swaddle, shushing, swinging, and side are all soothing to a crying baby.</li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/iTaqWOM">1-2-3 Magic: Gentle 3-Step Child &amp; Toddler Discipline for Calm, Effective, and Happy Parenting</a>. This is for toddlers, but I’ve learned this technique has been very helpful for giving me sanity in the terrible two phase. The approach doesn’t always work, but I’ve learned when it does, which is important. TLDR: don’t talk (engage in debate) with your toddler or show emotion when they’re misbehaving. Count them when they do bad acts. That’s 1. That’s 2. That’s 3. Break time. The book explains the method. YouTube is probably a friend here too.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="final-word" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-word">Final word</h3>
<p>Fatherhood has pushed my limits in all the ways. But I thank God every day I’m a dad. I do a nightly gratitude journal of my favorite moments of the day. If I’m paying attention during the day, at night it’s always my kids that have brought me the happiest moments and greatest joys of the day.</p>
<p>Just remember: the clothes/products/trips are like the tools used to construct a fine painting. At the end of the day, it doesn’t matter what tools you use. Nobody cares and neither will you. It’s the output that matters most. I’ve found by just really paying attention to and getting curious about my kids in any moment helps me see the beauty of it all, while distractions cause me to think I need this or that be a better dad.</p>


</section>
</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>productivity</category>
  <category>fatherhood</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-21-products-for-dads/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-21-products-for-dads/photo.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Blogging with Quarto, and why I don’t use Medium anymore</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-20-blogging-with-quarto/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-20-blogging-with-quarto/photo.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="been-here-before-eh" class="level1">
<h1>Been here before, eh?</h1>
<p>I probably shouldn’t write this post considering I’ve also written posts “blogging with Jekyll”, “Blogdown”, and “distill” before. I’m flaky, what can I say. I’ve changed my blogging framework 7 times in 5 years (I started with blogger.com and Wordpress before Jekyll, and even used Medium for 25 posts.)</p>
<p>But it’s not my fault. There are too many static site generators and it seems that Rstudio is as flaky as me. Meaning, they built rmarkdown, created hugodown, blowdown, bookdown, and distill. Hugodown is a lightweight version of blogdown, and I never figured out why it exists. Then there’s workflowr and so many other great, random products out there.</p>
<p>Why quarto for me? It seems to have all the stuff that distill has, and then some. And given its design and collaboration with Wes McKinney (pandas guy) in building quarto, and given that Wes wrote his latest book with it, I think this will be here to stay for at least 5 years.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-do-i-avoid-medium" class="level1">
<h1>Why do I avoid Medium</h1>
<p>Why don’t I blog with Medium? I wrote 25 posts there over 9 months and loved it. It makes writing and publishing incredibly easy, which is why I did it. With distill/blogdown the limiting factor was I’d have to be at my computer to get a post in. I love writing on my phone - I have over 2000 journal entries with Day One over seven years, several of which are “draft” posts for a blog that won’t see the light of day since I don’t care about them after I’ve written it. I want to be able to blog frequently, a short little blurb to keep up my writing, and medium enabled this.</p>
<p>But 1) I didn’t get many views (not that I care) and 2) my writing is stuck on their platform (confirmed to me this week as I’ve tried several old, broken tools that attempt to export posts out of medium).</p>
<p>I got 50x the views on my blogdown site just from organic google searching. From reading other people’s <a href="https://hulry.com/medium-vs-own-blog/">posts</a> about leaving Medium, it’s seems that most traffic to Medium posts comes from outside of Medium.</p>
<p>So while I’m certainly not into blogging for the money, I wouldn’t mind getting the content to people who it can help. And if medium didn’t enable this, what is its purpose?</p>
<p>So I’m back and finally decided that I’m going to own my own platform. Seth Godin wrote a blog about this topic once. Why be on Medium, substack, Facebook, etc or any other up an coming platform? We’ll they’re all skewed toward the 1% of people who make money on the platform. Everyone else is wasting their time. So might as well own your content. And better to focus on writing than waste time catching up on every platform.</p>
<p>Also, it’s fun! There’s a fuzzy feeling to blogging.</p>
</section>
<section id="future-of-quarto" class="level1">
<h1>Future of quarto?</h1>
<p>I’m speculating here, but <a href="https://quarto.org/docs/get-started/">Quarto can be used with</a>R Studio, Jupiter or VS Code. The last editor seems excitingly suspicious.</p>
<p>Perhaps R Studio sees the writing on the wall that VS Code is taking over the IDE world and perhaps taking over the long term future of R Studio IDE. I personally don’t see why anyone would pay for R Studio when VS Code is free and has a better interface. And while R Studio has a few better integrations for R at the moment, it won’t once enough people see the light for VS Code and turn their contributions there. I’ve been using R on VSCode for two years now and it rivals R Studio in 95% of the feature set, but 100% has better window management.</p>
<p>So Quarto seems like a great opportunity for R Studio to begin monetizing on a publishing platform like R Studio connect. Platforms like Notion and Confluence are great for everyone except data scientists trying to share reproducible research. But a quarto server seems like a great way to finally bring in Python data scientists into the markdown-flavored documentation world. (Man, I personally can’t use Jupyter/Google colab notebooks when I can use R Markdown!) I’d heartedly welcome this prospect, though I have no idea what their plans for Quarto really are.</p>
<p>Till next blog post about what blogging tool I’m going to use…</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>data science</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-20-blogging-with-quarto/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2022-06-20-blogging-with-quarto/photo.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Author’s Angle Matters</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2021-07-17-authors-angle-matters/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 







<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>communication</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2021-07-17-authors-angle-matters/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jul 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2021-07-17-authors-angle-matters/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Productivity notes</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2020-12-18-productivity-notes/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="time-management" class="level1">
<h1>Time Management</h1>
<ul>
<li>Calendar my ToDos.</li>
<li>Shorter work is better. Less to edit. Less mistakes. Keep it simple.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="distractions" class="level1">
<h1>Distractions</h1>
<ul>
<li>Block 30 min for email and review team members work twice a day.</li>
<li>Aggressively filter email spam.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="analysis" class="level1">
<h1>Analysis</h1>
<ul>
<li>Start with a story. End with story.</li>
<li>Iterate quickly with stakeholders.</li>
<li>always have one nights sleep before sending a presentation. Edit.</li>
</ul>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>data science</category>
  <category>productivity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2020-12-18-productivity-notes/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2020-12-18-productivity-notes/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to mock the value of an ML solution</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2020-12-16-pretotyping-ml-solutions/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>IBM once launched a demo of speech-to-text in the early day’s of the technology. But there was a twist: it was smoke and mirrors. A typist in behind the stage was translating and typing.</p>
<p>This is a mechanical Turk.</p>
<p>In data science, we can present results or dashboards to audience members before they see anything. If you see a big reaction, you know you found a number they cared about.</p>
<p>Go ahead, write the conclusion first. Fake the chart first. Then back out the code that could produce the insights they need.</p>
<p>Sometimes, unique insights appear along the way. But most of the time you can properly gut-check whether someone will care about what you’re doing. Save time. Work backward.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>data science</category>
  <category>innovation</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2020-12-16-pretotyping-ml-solutions/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2020-12-16-pretotyping-ml-solutions/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Get rid of the todo list. Calendar everything.</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2020-12-15-calendaring-todos/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2020-12-15-calendaring-todos/image.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>I’ve had less meetings and more unstructured time during WFH. It can be isolating, which can slow down productivity.</p>
<p><a href="https://link.medium.com/6xW8fKHSfcb">Here’s a tip I read</a> today on how to be productive with unstructured time: put your to-do list directly into a calendar.</p>
<p>That way, you’ll always have time for the important things. Remove the things that take up your time and aren’t as important. I like it.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>productivity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2020-12-15-calendaring-todos/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2020-12-15-calendaring-todos/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="64" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Data Beats Opinions</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2020-12-15-data-beats-opinions/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>When I co-started a company several years ago, my founders and I would canvass neighborhoods knocking doors. We’d discuss our ideas for a new product one door at a time. After each conversation, the product took a new form. Eventually, the product took shape and we had a successful kickstarter launch.</p>
<p>Since that time, I’ve thought about how valuable it was to get information straight from the source.</p>
<p>Alberto Savoia’s new book, “The Right It”, is re-teaching me this principle. Data beats opinions, he says. In another book I’m reading, “Trustworthy Online Controlled Experiments”, the former CEO of Netscape is quoted saying,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>If we have data, let’s go with data. If all we have are opinions, let’s go with mine. - Jim Barksdale</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Data sourced from your manager, your stakeholder, or your customer are invaluable to help you know if you’re solving their problem. Too often it’s easy to get stuck in the original solution that comes to our mind.</p>
<p>Data from customers directly shape the product. Data sourced at scale from online experiments refine it.</p>
<p>Opinions from the customer shape the product. Their behavior (captured as data) speaks louder than their words. Frequently, it’s challenging to correlate the two. We’re left to guess why someone actually clicked, bought, churned. It’s a beautiful cycle.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>data science</category>
  <category>decisions</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2020-12-15-data-beats-opinions/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2020-12-15-data-beats-opinions/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Starting with Jekyll</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2016-11-07-starting-with-jekyll/starting-with-jekyll.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Hello world.</p>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>I wanted to start a blog. I wanted to set it up for free, use a custom URL (and not <em>something.bloggingplatform.com</em>), and be able to both blog and create tutorials. I didn’t mind it possibly being technical<sup>1</sup>. Enter Jekyll.</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;Specifically, I was interested in being able to use the command line for my posts. Additionally, I didn’t mind seeing or using a little bit of code.</p></li></div></div>
<p><em>If you want to get your blog in 10 minutes, skip to below.</em></p>
<section id="why-blog-with-jekyll" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Why Blog with Jekyll?</h1>
<p>Here’s why you can and should blog with Jekyll (if you’re a data scientist):</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Jekyll has beautiful, free, open-source templates.</li>
<li>GitHub will host your website for free<sup>2</sup>.</li>
<li>Jekyll is <a href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2015/11/modern-static-website-generators-next-big-thing/">static</a>.</li>
<li>Jekyll can be simple to set up<sup>3</sup>.</li>
<li>I tried Wordpress and blogger.com and got frustrated.</li>
<li>The blogging content you create is very portable (easy to take your posts from one blog site to another).</li>
<li>Creating blogs in Markdown syntax is a dream (even for non-technical folks).</li>
<li>You can manage your blog from your terminal</li>
<li>You can manage your blog from your phone (if you have a GitHub-editing app)</li>
</ol>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;Someone has to <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=what+does+it+mean+to+host+a+website&amp;oq=what+does+it+mean+to+host+&amp;aqs=chrome.0.0j69i57j0l4.2810j0j9&amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;ie=UTF-8">host</a> it (i.e., store and display all the files). I started off trying to set up a WordPress blog, but you have to pay another company to <a href="http://www.webhostingbest10.com/web-hosting-reviews">host</a>. I didn’t want to bother.</p></li><li id="fn3"><p><sup>3</sup>&nbsp;If you try to set it up by following the instructions on <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">jekyllrb.com</a>, that’s the complicated way. That’s how I originally started, got lost for five hours, and stopped. Six months later, I found a better way.</p></li></div><p>But if you don’t like debugging occasional errors, you probably shouldn’t blog with Jekyll.</p>
<p>What is Jekyll, you ask? Jekyll is an open-source blogging platform. Anyone can write a template and post it, and anyone else can use that template. Perusing <a href="http://jekyllthemes.org/">Jekyllthemes.org</a>, you can pick out any template you’d like.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-did-i-get-started-with-jekyll" class="level1">
<h1>How did I get started with Jekyll?</h1>
<p>As a blogging noob, I’ve discovered there are hundreds of ways to generate a blog (e.g., WordPress, Squarespace, blogger.com, Weebly, etc.). But when my colleague <a href="http://luiarthur.github.io/">Arthur Lui</a> showed me his blog, I wanted something similar. I first tried Wordpress, then tried blogspot, then gave up and followed Arthur’s example and landed with Jekyll.</p>
</section>
<section id="set-up-a-blog-in-10-minutes" class="level1">
<h1>Set up a blog in 10 minutes!</h1>
<p>I followed this Jekyll <a href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2014/08/build-blog-jekyll-github-pages/">tutorial</a> to set up my first blog. I’ll simplify those steps here to get you up and running quickly:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Get a GitHub account. (2 min)</li>
<li>Go to <a href="http://jekyllthemes.org/">Jekyllthemes.org</a>. All of these blog themes are free. Find one you like, and Fork the repo (i.e., “repository”). (2-60 min, depending on how long you peruse)</li>
<li>In GitHub, rename the newly-forked repo from “REPO name” to “yourgithubusername.github.io”. (1 min)</li>
<li>Now go to “githubusername.github.io”. Voila, you have a blog.</li>
</ol>
<p>And if you want to start writing posts, go to your “_posts” folder. Then create new files and follow the default templates that the repository provides. (The blogs will need to be written in Markdown syntax.)</p>
<p>That was my 10 minute promise. If you feel a bit cheated or lost, go to the well-done <a href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2014/08/build-blog-jekyll-github-pages/">tutorial</a> and do all the steps. But the steps I listed are the essential steps to setting up a blog from scratch. So if you want to make a few blogs really quickly, after you figure out the first one the others follow nicely. For example, once I finished the tutorial, I followed those steps above to try two other themes before deciding on the <a href="https://github.com/bencentra/centrarium">Centrarium</a> theme.</p>
<p>To get Centrarium to work, I did have to change some configurations in the “_config.yml”, so there can be some minor debugging depending on the theme you choose. But with a little patience and some Googling, you’ll get it.</p>
</section>
<section id="add-to-jekyll-a-custom-url-from-godaddy" class="level1">
<h1>Add to Jekyll a custom URL from GoDaddy</h1>
<p>You’ll notice I have a custom URL and not “bryanwhiting.github.io”. I used GoDaddy to get a domain. (I have no affiliation with GoDaddy.) Here’s how I linked GoDaddy with my GitHub Jekyll blog:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Get a domain.</li>
<li>In your Github repo, change (or create) a CNAME file in the main directory. (See my <a href="https://github.com/bryanwhiting/bryanwhiting.github.io/blob/master/CNAME">CNAME</a> file for an example). And for the CNAME file contents, just type in the new “www” that you registered through GoDaddy.</li>
<li>Then, on GoDaddy, go to the section “DNS Management”. Here’s where you tell GoDaddy how to connect your newly purchased “www” with GitHub. Create the following connections:</li>
<li>[Type, Name, Value, TTL] = [A, @, 192.30.252.153, 600 seconds]</li>
<li>[Type, Name, Value, TTL] = [A, @, 192.30.252.154, 600 seconds]</li>
<li>[Type, Name, Value, TTL] = [CNAME, ftp, yourgithubusername.github.io, 600 seconds]</li>
<li>[Type, Name, Value, TTL] = [CNAME, www, yourgithubusername.github.io, 600 seconds]</li>
</ol>
<p>If you have the CNAME file in your GitHub folder, GitHub and GoDaddy will talk and after a few minutes your custom “www” will work. You don’t technically need the two [A] steps, but those connections allow users to type “<a href="http://www.bryanwhiting.com">bryanwhiting.com</a>” instead of “www.bryanwhiting.com”. It can take up to 24 hours before these [A] connections enable, so don’t be worried if the short URL doesn’t work first try. But the full URL should work soon enough.</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>productivity</category>
  <category>blogging</category>
  <category>jekyll</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/2016-11-07-starting-with-jekyll/starting-with-jekyll.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
