<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 13:42:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>What’s your decision framework?</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/whats-your-decision-framework.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Annie Duke asks the question “how do you make decisions? What’s your framework?” (<a href="../book-review/how-to-decide-simple-tools-for-making-better-choices.html">How to Decide: Simple Tools for Making Better Choices</a>)</p>
<p>She remarks that many people don’t have one. Many CEO’s just go off their gut.</p>
<p>I encountered this in my investing days (ahem, internship). I lead a discussion on a paper I had read about how emotions affect our judgment and investment decisions.</p>
<p>I proposed an idea: that the investors should make a spreadsheet with labels on their feelings for that decision. They can use this as further information later on when evaluating their buy/sell/holding decisions.</p>
<p>I was laughed out of the room.</p>
<p>“Hey! Why don’t we all get some mood rings?!” Well, that guy (the boss) was later fired, but that’s not the point.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-unhappy-investor-vector.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Don’t let your emotions cloud your judgment.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Point is: if you think you’re making decisions independent of your emotions, you’re incredibly mistaken. Judgment is based off reason and gut. Decisions usually rely on gut though. You have to “feel good”.</p>
<p>I had seen this boss make many decisions without explaining his thinking. “Hold.” Why? The company is tanking per reports. “Sell”, but this one’s looking good!</p>
<p>The point is nobody could replicate his decision making. Half the time it felt arbitrary.</p>
<p>Only later did I learn that one of the most famous investment company, Bridgewater Capital, does this very thing. It’s not for everybody, nor do I do it, but I think it’s a good idea 😄. # proposal</p>
<p>Make a spreadsheet for your decisions.</p>
<ul>
<li>What to decide</li>
<li>Description</li>
<li>Decision: what you chose</li>
<li>Rationale: why you chose it</li>
<li>Facts: supporting facts</li>
<li>Emotional Reasoning: how you “felt” about it.</li>
</ul>
<p>Do this for all decisions: even the “hold” decisions (maintain status quo). Because decision to not change course is a decision in and of itself.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>insights from books</category>
  <category>investing</category>
  <category>memories</category>
  <category>personal stories</category>
  <category>emotional intelligence</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/whats-your-decision-framework.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 13:42:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Organization and Minimalism</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/organization-and-minimalism.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It’s hard to be a minimalist as a parent. Or as…a human…in this economy. We all want more stuff.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-bear-with-messy-stuff.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">When in doubt, toss it out</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>With a small living space and a growing family I’ve grown accustomed to throwing stuff out. I grew up in a bigger house than I have now so there was space for everything. Now there’s space for very little. It’s actually a great feeling because I know what’s in every box (after doing some deep cleaning over winter break).</p>
<p>I remember helping a friend move in high school. Endless hoards of products, products, products. Three moving trucks. Why? I wondered.</p>
<p>My philosophy now is: RAM and Hard drive.</p>
<p>RAM: the random access memory. The things you see when you open doors affect your brain state. Your brain can only hold so much. If you live in clutter you have clutter. So the things you see in your house should reflect what you can hold in memory.</p>
<ul>
<li>Toys should have a theme (blocks, action figures, doll house). If it doesn’t match a theme, it’s gone (begone random slap bracelet! “Afuera!!!”, (quote from new Argentine President))</li>
<li>Things you see should be things you use. Don’t use flower every day? Don’t have it in the pantry. Put it in the corner thing. Cereal every day? Put that front and center.</li>
</ul>
<p>Then long-storage is the hard drive. It’s about keeping stuff you know you’ll want. This is easier to say than do.</p>
<ul>
<li>Holiday decoration? (Theme) keep those in the attic, out of sight out of mind. But when you need it you know where it is.</li>
<li>You get the point.</li>
</ul>
<p>The same goes for code. Maintenance and search cost increase as you add garbage. When it doubt, delete code. Afuera!!</p>
<p>When in doubt, “afuera!!”</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1fXr95TcSxY?si=dVxufSBO5XWz5gX0" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>minimalism</category>
  <category>organization</category>
  <category>software</category>
  <category>parenting</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/organization-and-minimalism.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 10:38:11 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Dune: Messiah</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/dune-messiah.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Sequel to <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-dune-messiah.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Dune Messiah</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Notes: - sometimes lies are easier to believe than the truth - He may be a mentat, Benegesseret, etc but he’s still human. He has a weakness.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/dune-messiah.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 22:07:10 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Knife to a Gun Fight: Why I’m off Social Media</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/a-knife-to-a-gun-fight.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Tim Ferris describes why he doesn’t have social media on his phone:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_Fn-giKevmo?si=f1Lz9H2U08BQhKwv" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>I recently deleted social media from my phone 14 days ago. I had been using Instagram until April when I quit and Twitter all year. I realized within days how much better I felt without social media. Happier. Legitimately happier.</p>
<p>And why? What do I get out of it? I’m not growing closer to friends. That’s what texting and calling and spending time in person does. But I’d argue even texting doesn’t really strengthen a relationship because it’s so hard to properly interpret emotions and cues via text: you interpret them how you read those texts. You interpret it according to your emotional state, not the sender’s.</p>
<p>Phone provides vocal emotional cues. Body language another set of emotional cues. I can get probably 70% of this out from FaceTime or <a href="../gratitude/zoom.html">Zoom</a>. But being in person is what we’re meant for.</p>
<p>This is why we strengthen relationships locally, and fail to continue ones from high school or our previous job.</p>
<p>So what was I doing on social media? Watching clips of either strangers I don’t care about or college associates I friended (once lived locally with) that I no longer talk to.</p>
<p>So what’s the knife you’re bringing to the gun fight? When at YouTube I heard the CEO praise a team for increasing “seconds watched” by 15% by reducing the lag of the swipes between YouTube shorts (TikTok clone). The lag reduction was in the milliseconds. Your attention is being bought and manipulated by the shareholders of these companies.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-knife-gun-fight.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Yes, they’re targeting specifically you. You don’t stand a chance. And you have a pocket knife, and you’re 50 feet away. Who’s gonna win?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>They A/B test everything. This isn’t morally wrong. It’s actually quite human: we all A/B test everything every day. A joke here. A smile there. We put out feelers and see if we get a reaction. Don’t believe me? Ask my kid why he keeps throwing things in the toilet!</p>
<p>Billions of dollars and the brightest minds on earth are working at FAANG. Why? They need to provide for their families and academics doesn’t pay. Non-profits don’t pay. This isn’t immoral, it just is. There are very good people working there: honest, moral people. Some of the best I’ve seen in the industry. But when you get paid to maximize swipes, you maximize swipes. It’s just human nature. And some of them buy into the odd notions of “snackable content”, as if swiping for 30 minutes while on the toilet is what anyone wakes up excited to do. Keep on snacking…</p>
<p>Social media and Netflix provide a ton of value to the world in my opinion. I can use them to call anyone I want, raise money for a cause, or get likes on a cute pic of my cat (I don’t have a cat). I <em>do</em> see the value.</p>
<p>But the costs for me have outweighed the value.</p>
<p>I <em>do</em> miss laughing about some random Reel. There’s nothing that can get you laughing faster than a 10 second clip paired with the right cuts and music and everything. The right meme just nails it in a way nothing else can. I miss seeing memes from my friends. But when all I do is send memes to these friends, is that a friendship?</p>
<p>Since being off social media I feel like my senses have grown. I now find my kids a lot funnier, my wife funnier, and I’m able to make heavy situations lighter much easier.</p>
<p>There’s a quote in <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a> that’s something like “If you rely only on your eyes, your other senses weaken”. I’d argue my other relationships weakened too. Time to leave the fight. I was losing.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>personal experiments</category>
  <category>A/B testing</category>
  <category>social media</category>
  <category>big tech</category>
  <category>incentives</category>
  <category>decisions</category>
  <category>relationships</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>emotional intelligence</category>
  <category>purpose of life</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/a-knife-to-a-gun-fight.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 11:24:09 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Becoming an expert is kind of a fallacy</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/becoming-an-expert.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Just watched this clip:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/I2ZK3ngNvvI?si=p4BCDVMWKBoc4KJQ" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Important discussion points: as a novice you’re worried about where to go or picking the wrong thing.</p>
<p>I remember not taking an opportunity to learn C++ because “that’s not what I want to do”. In another occasion I wanted to learn PySpark over SQL because Python…</p>
<p>While I don’t regret that choice per se, because I chose something else I was interested in, I’ve largely come to realize that I don’t care what programming language I’m using. I care about getting the job done.</p>
<p>Also, I’m probably over the 10,000 hours of <em>something</em>, I just don’t know what. Am I an ML expert? Data expert? SQL? Python? R?</p>
<p>Is it the application of the skill that makes you an expert? I’m not sure. Because I think novices can do some incredible things if they hone in.</p>
<p>If you read one book on a topic, you’re by no means an “expert”, but you probably know more about that topic than 99% of the nation. I learned this when I spent 6 months diving into the home security industry for my first job. Pretty sure I knew more about that than anyone I spoke to. Was I an expert? I really only had maybe 300 hours. Maybe I was inexperienced. Sure.</p>
<p>And who spends literally 10,000 hours on any one thing? Like 10,000 hours on XGBoost? Image classification? Deep learning? Machine learning? A/B testing? Spreadsheets? Generalist vs specialist, etc. if you’re an ML scientist at Google, you worry about very different things than an ML scientist at a startup. At a startup, you worry about your bigquery allocation and pipeline failures. At Google you worry about what your 5th skip VP is going to deprecate that month.</p>
<p>That’s just the nature of education. There are so many things in the world to know…that being an “expert” is a relative thing. But I agree that working hard and learning useful things helps you innovate faster.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-rocky-balboa-expert.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">I’d change my opinion on being an expert if I needed to beat Rocky.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Last thing, the crux is: don’t compare yourself to others. Compare yourself to yourself. That’s how you assess your progress.</p>
<p>But I’d argue: why even compare yourself to yourself? Compare your solution to the problem. Does it matter if you have 10,000 hours? No.&nbsp;What matters is if the solution fits. This is why innovations and disruptions come from unexpected places: because novices can nail solutions.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>personal development</category>
  <category>growth</category>
  <category>grit</category>
  <category>life lessons</category>
  <category>data science</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/becoming-an-expert.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 22:55:24 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AI won’t replace us. We’ll always create.</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/ai-will-not-replace-human-creativity.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I recently got back into writing some poems. <a href="../creative/poem-the-dove-forevermore.html">The Dove (Forevermore)</a> was fun to write. After the fact, I tried getting ChatGPT to create something similar. I only tried once before declaring victory.</p>
<p>Why is this poem meaningful to me? Because it has my soul in it. It’s the summation of my experience as a parent. Should you find it interesting, perhaps that’s why.</p>
<p>Reading <a href="../book-review/the-best-of-edgar-allen-poe.html">The Best of Edgar Allen Poe</a> recently I’m amazed (besides how depressing he is) at how excellent a writer he is. He peers into the mind and soul and extricates anything interesting. It’s interesting because a human wrote it.</p>
<p>Do we still paint, even if a camera can take a picture? Do we still ride bikes and horses even with cars and things? Do we still read even though we have TV and movies?</p>
<p>Words. Creative expression. They will always be interesting to us. Humans are interesting to us. Stories. Social acceptance is a fundamental human need. We desire connection. We’ll like reading something because a human wrote it.</p>
<p>But what about that guy I heard about who makes a ton of money using ChatGPT to create fake digital books on Amazon. People don’t <em>know</em> it’s AI-written. Digital GenAI images now are insanely accurate - it’s only 2024. It’s very possible great AI art will inspire us more than non-AI art (whatever that means because everyone uses photoshop anyway).</p>
<p>I’m not saying we won’t find value in AI art (creative writing, digital, video, etc.). We will. It’s clear we’ll have a really hard time knowing what’s human vs not.</p>
<p>But I am saying that creativity will never disappear. We’re always going to be interested in creating - even if machines can do it better. Machines can beat us at Go and StarCraft (<a href="../posts/2023-12-25-ai-robots-are-mastering-tasks-faster-than-humans-/index.html">AI Robots are mastering tasks faster than humans</a>), but we’ll still play. Because what else will there be to do?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-leonardo-painting-the-mona-lisa.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">I guess I’ll pick up painting now…</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>futurism</category>
  <category>humanity</category>
  <category>creativity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/ai-will-not-replace-human-creativity.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 23:21:29 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What startups and musicians have in common</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/what-startups-and-musicians-have-in-common.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I was reminded of a video I watched a while back on YouTube. It was a great documentary about these new artists and their debate about whether to sign a record label (there’s a recent trend to selling music as an independent artist).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-musician-signing-record-label-watercolors.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Putting pen to ink</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I forget all the details, but there are some roughly insane trends that are generally interesting as I recall:</p>
<ul>
<li>new record labels are for $500k give or take. This is so the artist can invest a year into their music and get an album out, pay for production, etc.</li>
<li>many artists at that early stage aren’t financially literate and end up wasting the (they’re musicians, not bankers)</li>
<li>Some have to pay back the money</li>
<li>Up to 85% of the streaming royalties are owed to the label (started when streaming became a thing)</li>
<li>Labels also take a large portion of touring revenues now (something that wasn’t common 10 years ago)</li>
</ul>
<p>Why is this similar to tech startups? Lots.</p>
<p>Musicians have to find product market fit. They need to find their customers. Their monthly listeners.</p>
<p>They need to keep them coming back.</p>
<p>They need to differentiate.</p>
<p>Those who are customer focused and build a following are those who succeed. (Money in the bank and relying too much on the label can cripple you)</p>
<section id="the-musicians-in-town" class="level1">
<h1>The Musicians in Town</h1>
<p>I remember hanging out with some new artists while I was running my startup (we both used the same videographer). I couldn’t help but notice how similar the dynamics were. The founders. The first hires (replacements). The convos about who gets what. It’s all very fascinating.</p>
<p>Not much else to say.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>startups</category>
  <category>music</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/what-startups-and-musicians-have-in-common.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 20:53:53 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The future wave of AI hype</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/the-future-wave-of-ai-hype.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Reading about Airplane’s failure per OnlyCFO. A few notable quotes:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Airplane’s shutdown and future shutdowns like this will have negative consequences for many early stage companies. For many years buyers of these tools haven’t had to deal with a tool being abruptly killed. It only takes this happening once for you to really second guess purchasing a startup tool that is mission critical, deeply integrated, or would take a long time to replace.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/the-future-wave-of-ai-hype.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 20:32:46 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Write a thousand songs</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/write-a-thousand-songs.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I listened to an interview with Imagine Dragons. The lead singer talked about how he writes several songs per day.</p>
<p>No wonder he’s so successful. Repetitions breeds opportunity.</p>
<p>This has two affects on the brain. 1) lowers the pressure of individual songs. Don’t need to knock it of the park. 2) you get better at writing that much faster.</p>
<p>I heard once about a photography that let one half of the students only take 5 photos in a semester. The other half had to take 100. Which group had the better photos?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>You miss 100% of the shots you don’t take. <del>Wayne Gretzky</del> Michael Scott</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-hockey-shots-surreal-impressionist-water.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">More shots is more opportunities for a goal. Worry about good shots later.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>creativity</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/write-a-thousand-songs.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 15:10:01 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>When Leaders Lose their People</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/losing-to-yesmen.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In a scene in <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>, Paul notices that his warrior turns into his worshipper. He laments the loss, wondering if his non-religious warrior will be lost too.</p>
<p>Being a worshipped means you’re worshipped. Unchallenged. Can do no wrong. As such, you’re left with the intellect of one.</p>
<p>As a leader, you need to avoid worshippers. People who fail to challenge you out of fear or an abundance of praise. This all has to do in the decisions you make as a leader. The culture you decide to build. Is every voice heard, or does one voice rule them all?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-king-one-voice-to-rule.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">One voice to rule them all</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/losing-to-yesmen.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 14:31:39 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Multiverse of Careers</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-multiverse-of-careers.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Spoken about in <a href="../tech/dreaming-software.html">The Dream State of Software</a>, Paul of <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a> has a moment where he’s both past and present in his mind. He doesn’t know even whether he’s had his kid or not.</p>
<p>In a podcast I listened to lately on happiness, one suggestion was to write out all your goals and cross them off from day one. Pretend like it doesn’t even matter if you accomplish them. This helps free you.</p>
<p>Careers are like both of these things. We want everything. We can pretend like we have it. We can come to terms with it. And we can say “doesn’t matter if I don’t get that, because I’ve got a life outside my career.”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-multiverse-of-choice.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Which path you choose isn’t as important as who you choose as companions</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Consider your career from your deathbed (<a href="../posts/my-tombstone.html">My Tombstone</a>). What path did you take that mattered? What were all the alternate realities and multiverses you could have had.</p>
<p>Put them all together. In one multiverse you’ve been fired. In another you end up getting insanely wealthy. In another you start your own company. In another you become an online blogger.</p>
<p>All of them can’t be true when you do this exercise extensively enough. And choosing which one probably doesn’t matter as much (right vs wrong path thinking). If you’ve ever left a job you realize that nothing really comes over with you. Most relationships at work are short lived and contextual, like your relationships in high school. And that’s life.</p>
<p>Happiness is perhaps being okay with not having everything you desire, except for the few things that are truly attainable: peace with God, self, and cherished relationships.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <category>deathbed meditation</category>
  <category>career</category>
  <category>decisions</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-multiverse-of-careers.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 13:00:31 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>30 Seconds is All You Get</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/30-seconds-for-payment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Apple iTunes changed the music industry forever with one simple decision: the preview of a song should be 30 seconds long.</p>
<p>This little change dramatically altered how music sounds today. I’ve recently listened to some bangers that were only 90 seconds long. They left me hanging.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-listening-to-music-colorful.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Enjoy the music while it lasts</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Why was my song so short? Because nobody gets paid after 30 seconds.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Apple’s decision made artists want to have more interesting 30 seconds in the iTunes Store</li>
<li>That evolved into: an artist doesn’t get paid if you don’t listen at least 30 seconds. And they don’t get paid any more if you listen 31 or 900 seconds. In fact, they get paid more if you listen to two songs, 30s a piece.</li>
</ol>
<p>Spotify, Amazon, YouTube, Apple, etc all pay based on views. They each define views their own way, but they need to negotiate with the labels who already decided to agree to Apple’s 30s schemes in the early 2000’s. They may have different payment schemes, but some have a scheme of “take all revenue, distribute it according to the artist’s share of views.” So if I pay $10/mo for Spotify and don’t use it, my money goes to someone I didn’t listen to.</p>
<p>So how do small artists compete? They’ve got to build their following. Proportionally, the major artists (rather, their labels) soak up all the streaming royalties.</p>
<p>What would be more fair is if my $10 went to the artists I actually listened to, as if I bought their music.</p>
<p>Why does any of this matter? Algorithms. Optimization. Monetization.</p>
<p>Incentives drive outcomes. How we designed our music payment incentives altered music forever (try to be super catchy for 30s). Now, with AI, music can be created much faster which will dilute the pool.</p>
<p>In the end, one simple decision changed billions of lives. 30s? That’s all you need to get paid.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>music</category>
  <category>economics</category>
  <category>incentives</category>
  <category>posts</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/30-seconds-for-payment.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Your Mood is Contagious</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/your-mood-is-contagious.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-mood-sharing.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Moods flow. Keep the negative waves at bay</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There’s no question that moods are contagious. I once asked someone at the beach to leash their dog, and they slightly rebuked me, “this is a dog friendly beach.” <em>Well, so it is,</em> I thought, grumpily. I complained to a family member about this grumpy dog owner.</p>
<p>Moods escalate. And negative moods are even more pervasive and contagious than positive ones. They say a disgruntled customer tells more friends and family than happy ones. Why is this?</p>
<p>In the “Black Cat” (<a href="../book-review/the-best-of-edgar-allen-poe.html">The Best of Edgar Allen Poe</a>), Poe describes a gruesome tale man who wanted to do evil just for the sake of it. That it’s in his nature. Not because you want to do the thing, but because you want to do a forbidden thing. The same goes the other way, for sure. But I think we trend slightly pessimistic because being an optimist is more beneficial, more rewarding and therefore more difficult.</p>
<p>A leader once told me when I was managing a team, “They’ll pick up on <em>everything</em> you do or say.” Oddly, I was picking up on what he was saying.</p>
<p>So when you lead, lead carefully. Whether in home or work, lead with kindness, compassion, and restraint. Speak three kind words before a negative. Ask to understand before assuming. Lead as a servant. It takes all the effort to overcome negative vibes, and who better equipped than the leader to do it?</p>
<p>Don’t be Moriarty:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ncbEucjsNFU?si=rYhBqqavn4Nergap" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>“Why can’t you be more hopeful for a change?”</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <category>parenting</category>
  <category>emotional resilience</category>
  <category>grit</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/your-mood-is-contagious.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Dream State of Software</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/dreaming-software.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-dreaming-software.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Dreaming code working is ever coders dream</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I returned from vacation yesterday and tried running my code. It didn’t work. I looked at code I had written, it had my imports correctly and all - why wasn’t it running?</p>
<p>The file it was importing didn’t exist.</p>
<p>I thought I created that. I swear I made it. My coworker remarked, “oh so you set up all the scafffolding but didn’t write the actual code?” I was in disbelief. maybe it was deleted by accident or stashed on another branch. But the <code>git log</code> shows all: the imported file never existed.</p>
<p>In <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>, Paul Atriedes has many visions and the author uses this feature to skip the book ahead three years. Paul wakes up one morning and doesn’t know what’s past or future. It’s all one in his mind.</p>
<p>So it is with software. It gets created in the mind near instantly. Coding is a burden, the journey of many failures and design choices to enable the simple vision of the mind.</p>
<p>Perhaps Gen AI can help us dream software faster. I look forward to when my dreams are realities, and not the rude awakening I still have coding to do.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>design</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>futurism</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/dreaming-software.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Steve Jobs (Biography)</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/steve-jobs-biography.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 








<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/steve-jobs-biography.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My Tombstone</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/my-tombstone.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>They call it a death meditation, to look back from the end of your life and reflect as if you had just died (out of body style). Here’s my tombstone:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Here lies Bryan, son of Aragon, data scientist extraordinaire who knew how to use regular expressions and properly test linear regression assumptions</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Seem like a good tombstone?</p>
<p>Why do we measure our lives by something nobody cares about? Consider Steve Jobs, Isaac Newton, or whomever you idolize. What are they known for? Only a few things.</p>
<p>I read <a href="../book-review/steve-jobs-biography.html">Steve Jobs (Biography)</a> a while back. And I also read <a href="../book-review/leonardo-da-vinci.html">Leonardo da Vinci</a>. First was 25 hours, second was 17 hours. And guess what - that’s less than two days combined. Two “impressive” lives summed up in a few days.</p>
<p>My grandma’s obituary was brief. Yet her life was filled with millions of unwritten sentences - many written on my life. The in between moments. The laying around moments. The relationship moments. (Maybe it’s called a relation-“ship” because it sails the waters of life continuously, despite the infrequent dock postings.)</p>
<p>Nobody’s going to remember me, except those who call me dad, husband, brother, son, and friend. And I’m okay with that. I was never that good at data science anyway 😉.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-data-scientist-tombstone-on-beach.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">If I’m going out as a data scientist, at least my resting spot will be cool</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>mortality</category>
  <category>work</category>
  <category>work life balance</category>
  <category>perspective</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <category>priorities</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/my-tombstone.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Leonardo da Vinci</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/leonardo-da-vinci.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Read this back in 2021. Great book.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/leonardo-da-vinci.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Psychology of New Software Releases and its Parallels with Fashion</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/why-we-want-new-software.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>What is it about a new release that gets people excited? Would you buy software that never changes? How about a hammer?</p>
<p>Why are we okay with buying a hammer, but not stagnant software? Our culture is addicted to new widgets. A/B testing.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-ship-fashion-software.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Shipping software like fashion, every season</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Software releases are free, but development is not. Therefore, research and development is constant, whereas the Hammer company hasn’t needed to update its product in a couple…millennia. That’s why they call it software. It’s not hard to make.</p>
<p>Is there a way to sell software like you sell a hammer?</p>
<p>No.&nbsp;Because per <a href="../book-review/innovators-dilemma.html">Innovator’s Dilemma</a>, those who can out-do you will. And software is easy to alter and improve. I’m not convinced all “updates” done in the software industry are actually improvements, but people like change. Ever see a fashion line repeat itself?</p>
<p>Software is like fashion.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>business strategy</category>
  <category>saas</category>
  <category>sales</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/why-we-want-new-software.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Innovator’s Dilemma</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/innovators-dilemma.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 








<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/innovators-dilemma.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>“Socrates A Life Worth Living” by Devra Lehman</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/socrates-a-life-worth-living.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/book-socrates.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Socrates, a Life Worth Living</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Notes: - socrates had a voice he felt was from Gods. Daimonion - Memorization. Lots of it. - Humanism - treated sacrifices to the gods as transactional. This meant they relied on themselves rather than gods to teach them. - Odd relationships (pedophelia) - function: intended purpose. Virtue: quality of function.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>book-review</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/book-review/socrates-a-life-worth-living.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
