<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 21:59:18 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Become a Data Scientist in 10 Weeks</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/a-10-week-self-guided-data-science-intro-course.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>How do you get a job in data science if you currently aren’t a data scientist?</p>
<p>I asked this question while working as an analyst 8 years ago and wanting to break into data science. I wrote about it back then (lost the post), so I’m gonna revisit it now.</p>
<p>I was asked this question today: “how do I get started and get a job in data science if I don’t have any experience?”</p>
<p>Simple: get experience. For free. In 10 weeks. Write a good resume. Network like crazy - try to connect with real people (and not just spam).</p>
<p>There are a million ways to do this, and a million blog posts like this one. But here’s my biased opinion, so enjoy!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-plato-socrates-archimedes-and-r-a-fisher.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Some O.G. Data scientists</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="no-single-data-science-definition" class="level1">
<h1>No Single Data Science Definition</h1>
<p>Look at 10 job postings for data science and you’ll see 10 unique definitions for a data scientist. Roughly, I’d categorize them as such:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Human decision support: someone who supports others in their decision making. This would be their boss, their team, etc. Decisions are: should we shut this line of business down? Are our customers churning and how do we prevent that?</li>
<li>Machine Decision Support: someone who helps machines make automated decisions, like whether to approve a loan, recommend a YouTube video, etc.</li>
<li>Product developer: someone who uses data to build a web product or service. This is similar to machine decision support, but the role might be in a SaaS capacity.</li>
</ol>
<p>Most of these things below will help with 1-2. Today, AI products are all the rage and I offer one week on deep learning. That being said, all the principles in each one of these sections is important in any field you pursue. # Mindset</p>
<p>While doing the following, on weeks 2-10, write one blog post to outline what you learned.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Where did you start? Why was it hard to learn? What did you want to know?</li>
<li>What concepts were new to you?</li>
<li>Do something with that knowledge. Search the internet to find data you can write about.</li>
</ol>
<p>If you don’t get very far, just move on to the next topic. Breadth is better early on to find out what you enjoy. Don’t get caught up in the details. Skim more. Write more. Worry less. You got this.</p>
<p>In all things, use ChatGPT to tutor you. Ask it questions. Be relentless. Have it explain things to you like you’re five.</p>
<p>Balancing learning between real books and ChatGPT is the best combo. ChatGPT is a better teacher, and the books have real info in them you can more fully trust. Using both together will get you there faster.</p>
<p>If any of the books below don’t vibe for you, there are a million free books out there. Find a simpler one and the same topic (and post in the comments so I can add it!)</p>
</section>
<section id="week-1-prepare-to-share" class="level1">
<h1>Week 1: Prepare to Share</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>By creating a blog you demonstrate the following: you like to learn, you can communicate, you can do hard things, you’re naturally curious, you’re contributing to the ecosystem. Lots of ways to show those things, but having a blog is at least one way.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Set up a blog.
<ul>
<li>Medium.com</li>
<li>Substack.com</li>
<li>(Harder) Or use <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a> and publish on GitHub</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Find 5 blogs by top data scientists. Read their posts. See what they write about.</li>
<li>Your first blog post is about what you like about these 5 blogs.</li>
<li>Share your blog post on all social media. LinkedIn, Twitter, Facebook.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="week-2-storytelling" class="level1">
<h1>Week 2: Storytelling</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>You can’t get credit for great data science work unless you can tell a story. Now that you have a blog, learn how to write about data.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://tellingstorieswithdata.com/">Telling Stories with Data</a></li>
<li>Find three data-focused blogs that use charts and analysis. Economist, FiveThirtyEight, DataIsBeautiful, etc.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="week-3-analytics" class="level1">
<h1>Week 3: Analytics</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>To be able to make predictions about the future, you first need to understand how to understand the past.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Analytics is the foundation of data science. It’s the process of manipulating data and reshaping it to see it in new ways.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://wesmckinney.com/book/">Python for Data Analysis, 3E</a> - written by the creator of <code>pandas</code></li>
<li><a href="https://r4ds.hadley.nz/">R for Data Science (2e)</a> - written by the creator of <code>dplyr</code>, the best data manipulation language ever.</li>
</ul>
<p>Both these books are great. Read both. It’s good to learn early that there are multiple right ways of doing your analysis the wrong way 😉. Seeing how to think in two languages is actually easier than getting stuck on one.</p>
</section>
<section id="week-4-data-visualization" class="level1">
<h1>Week 4: Data Visualization</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Learning how to make a plot is like learning how to write. Learn how colors work. When to use them. When to use a bar vs.&nbsp;a line chart. How to make ideas shine.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://jjallaire.github.io/visualization-curriculum/">Visualization Curriculum</a></li>
<li><a href="https://r-graphics.org/">R Graphics Cookbook, 2nd edition</a></li>
</ul>
<p>This is after analytics because analytics is more important (knowing what to look for and how to think about data) than plotting it.</p>
<p>There are two types of plots: those for you to learn from and those for others to learn from. First, learn what’s in the data. Learn for yourself.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Look at the plot. Look at the plot. No seriously, look at the plot.” Chris Peterson, Capital One</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Second, plot for other people. After you’ve learned something by sifting out all the noise, learn how to communicate that externally.</p>
<p>Beautiful plotting is really hard and time consuming. Details can take hours. Focus on the basics at first. The simplest plot focuses on “what’s the one thing I want someone to take away from this?”</p>
</section>
<section id="week-5-get-data-you-dont-yet-have" class="level1">
<h1>Week 5: Get Data You Don’t Yet Have</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>If you work at a company &gt; 50 people, your company’s data is probably stored in a database. Learning how to get this data so you can do data analytics and visualization will help you be self sufficient.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Analytics is more important than this, because someone else may be able to get you the data. Or, once you know analytics then you can use SQL to <em>do</em> analytics.</p>
<p>Three primary ways to get data include the following:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>SQL (from a database, returns a spreadsheet like table)</li>
<li>API (get data from a website, returns JSON data)</li>
<li>Webscraping (getting it yourself, this is considered “unstructured” data)</li>
</ol>
<p>Interactive tutorials here are the way to go. Just google around for some good ones.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://sqlbolt.com/">SQLBolt - Learn SQL - Introduction to SQL</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.dataquest.io/blog/python-api-tutorial/">Python API Tutorial: Getting Started with APIs – Dataquest</a></li>
<li><a href="https://realpython.com/python-web-scraping-practical-introduction/">A Practical Introduction to Web Scraping in Python – Real Python</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="week-6-intro-to-machine-learning" class="level1">
<h1>Week 6: Intro to Machine Learning</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>This book nails the foundations of machine learning. Doesn’t get too mathy, but teaches you the principles.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.statlearning.com/">An Introduction to Statistical Learning</a></li>
<li>For reference, a more mathy and dense book that supports the Intro book is <a href="https://hastie.su.domains/Papers/ESLII.pdf">Elements of Statistical Learninf</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="week-7-regression-analysis" class="level1">
<h1>Week 7: Regression Analysis</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Regression Is key to getting insights out of data. It’s what sets you apart from a data analyst role.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://peopleanalytics-regression-book.org/">Welcome | Handbook of Regression Modeling in People Analytics: With Examples in R, Python and Julia</a></li>
<li><a href="https://avehtari.github.io/ROS-Examples/">Regression and Other Stories</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="week-8-choose-your-own-adventure" class="level1">
<h1>Week 8 Choose your own Adventure</h1>
<section id="ab-testing-and-kpi-optimization-for-online-companies-applies-to-offline-too" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ab-testing-and-kpi-optimization-for-online-companies-applies-to-offline-too">A/B Testing and KPI Optimization for Online Companies (applies to offline too)</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>All big internet companies use A/B testing, or split testing, to make decisions about how to improve their product. If you’re interested in software, or understanding how all modern websites and software are improved, you need to understand A/B testing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If You’ve taken stat 101, this is where the “t.test” gets used to literally make Big Tech billions of dollars. I’m not kidding. It’s simple, but it’s powerful.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://netflixtechblog.com/its-all-a-bout-testing-the-netflix-experimentation-platform-4e1ca458c15">It’s All A/Bout Testing: The Netflix Experimentation Platform | by Netflix Technology Blog | Netflix TechBlog</a></li>
<li>A seven part series by Netflix: <a href="https://netflixtechblog.com/netflix-a-culture-of-learning-394bc7d0f94c">Netflix: A Culture of Learning. Martin Tingley with Wenjing Zheng… | by Netflix Technology Blog | Netflix TechBlog</a> I put here the seventh post because it likes to parts 1-6 in the intro. This part 7 is probably the best to start with because it explains the context behind A/B testing.</li>
<li><a href="https://experimentguide.com/">Experiment Guide – Accelerate innovation using trustworthy online controlled experiments</a> This book tells you how Microsoft, Amazon, and Google use online experimentation to make billions of dollars. It’s written by the people who invented online experimentation and who are top data scientists at those companies.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="time-series-data" class="level1">
<h1>Time Series Data</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>All modern data is time series data in some way (data collected over time). Even though you may not use forecasting in everything or what not, understanding the nature of that data will set you apart. Focus on principles, not techniques as you may not use these specific techniques.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://otexts.com/fpp3/">Forecasting: Principles&nbsp;and&nbsp;Practice (3rd&nbsp;ed)</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="week-9-intro-to-deep-learning" class="level1">
<h1>Week 9: Intro to Deep Learning</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Deep learning is all the rage, and will change the future for everyone. It’s vital you know how these systems work because this is the future of society.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.fast.ai/">fast.ai - fast.ai—Making neural nets uncool again</a>
<ul>
<li>Great courses that teaches you how to build ChatGPT and Image Generators and understand it.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>This YouTube videos and others by him are great:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zjkBMFhNj_g" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Also this:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jkrNMKz9pWU" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</section>
<section id="week-10-recommendation-systems" class="level1">
<h1>Week 10: Recommendation Systems</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>If you’re making automated decisions with data, you’re probably using a recommendation system at some level. Recommendation systems typically focus on “what video does Bryan want given all the data we have on him and people like him?”. But the principles also extend to: how do I recommend one course of action to my stakeholder?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don’t have great resources here, but getting the concepts down will help you understand how virtually every social media app or streaming service works. (Netflix, Spotify, Instagram, etc all use recommenders to figure out the content you’re interested in. )</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://eliassi.org/charu_recsys_intro.pdf">http://eliassi.org/charu_recsys_intro.pdf</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="week-11-do-projects" class="level1">
<h1>Week 11+: Do Projects</h1>
<p>Now that you’ve studied analytics, data viz, regression, machine learning, and deep learning, create two blog posts or personal projects.</p>
<ul>
<li>Build a dashboard using a Jupyter notebook that updates daily. You can host on GitHub using quarto to render the notebook and use GitHub actions to update it every day.</li>
<li>Create a model to predict who will win the next NBA game</li>
<li>Analyze any data from data.gov</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="prepare-your-resume" class="level1">
<h1>Prepare your Resume</h1>
<p>Now you’ve got 10 blog posts, which is 10 more bullet points on your resume than you had before you started. You’ve learned a ton if you only do 10% of all that’s above.</p>
<p>I’ve loved the advice I found written up here: <a href="../posts/2022-11-18-writing-a-tech-resume/index.html">Writing a Tech Resume</a>.</p>
<p>Once you have a good resume, find real people to give it to. Dont apply blindly online. Talk to everyone you know. Find people on LinkedIn and message them directly with a personal message. Use one of your blog posts in your message to tell them why you’re a good fit for their role. Perhaps even write a blog post specific to data from their company!</p>
<p>Good luck!</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>data science</category>
  <category>featured</category>
  <category>career</category>
  <category>recommendation systems</category>
  <category>A/B testing</category>
  <category>analytics</category>
  <category>beginners</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/a-10-week-self-guided-data-science-intro-course.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 21:59:18 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Only Mind that’s Clear Is the One That Sees No Alternative</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-only-mind-thats-clear-is-the-one-that-sees-no-alternative.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The easiest thing one can do is see the world through their own viewpoints. It takes no effort. Takes no work. It’s already done: your viewpoints are there. Either you care about climate change today or you don’t. Either you care about opossums or you don’t. You are who you are, right now.</p>
<p>The only gap between who you are today and who you are tomorrow is what you learn and experience and how you see the world because of what you learn and experience.</p>
<p>You learn from others. You learn from your experiences. You learn from other’s experiences.</p>
<p>The goal isn’t to be right. The goal is to understand.</p>
<p>And so, I believe in the value of learning from those around me, especially those I disagree with. It’s hard work to grind through walls of disbelief or misunderstanding. But it’s always worth it, even if at the other side you merely understand. That in and of itself is a destination worth pursuing because of the many benefits it yields.</p>
<p>But beware, with an assumption of understanding comes peril. Therefore, the goal is to constantly seek understanding, because no person is every the same one day to the next.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-seeing-through-a-glass-darkly-and-then-clearly.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Seeing through a glass darkly and then clearly</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Sources: - <a href="../book-review/how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people.html">How to Win Friends and Influence People</a> - the constant focus of the book is to put yourself in the other’s shoes. - <a href="../book-review/greenlights.html">Greenlights</a> African tribe: don’t seek to be right. Seek to understand. - <a href="../book-review/the-coddling-of-the-american-mind.html">The Coddling of the American Mind</a> - tribalism is when you don’t see another’s viewpoint and only feel you are right.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>my principles</category>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-only-mind-thats-clear-is-the-one-that-sees-no-alternative.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 20:31:52 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Writing Only Makes Sense to the Author</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/writing-only-makes-sense-to-the-author.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>If you’re a bad author</em>, your writing will only make sense to you.</p>
<p>Problem is, we’re all bad authors.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>My writing makes sense as I put it fown</li>
<li>It doesn’t always make sense to me 5 minutes later (my future self is practically another person)</li>
<li>The probability of it being perfectly interpreted by someone who isn’t even me, is likely near zero.</li>
</ol>
<p>So when we write, we send out an idea. It then becomes a painting on the wall, up for anyone to interpret how they may.<sup>1</sup> therefore, it’s best to put yourself as much in your audience’s shoes as possible (something discussed often in <a href="../book-review/how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people.html">How to Win Friends and Influence People</a>).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-image-people-in-an-art-museum-staring-at-a-painting-of-scribbles-on-the-wall.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">“Now what on earth was Bryan trying to say?!?” “I think he was inspired” “nah man, he just wrote scribbles on the wall. That’s not writing!” “Yea, maybe he should slap a banana with duct tape on there. Would have gotten the point across better”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


<aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Going to an extreme - ever write a kind word that was taken as an insult, or sent something sarcastic and it was interpreted as literal?↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</aside>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>communication</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>art</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/writing-only-makes-sense-to-the-author.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 12:01:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Problem with Public Opinions</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-problem-with-public-opinions.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>If you become a public opinion person (author, speaker, podcaster), you’re inherently inviting publicity bias.</p>
<p>A message is like a product. If it’s not well received, either through attention, clicks, or books purchased, then most people may abandon the idea. Very few (those seeking truth), are staunch advocates of an opinion not popularly received.</p>
<p>Even unpopular opinion people try out their ideas. They may rise on social media as “they want to cancel me, so trust my opinion”. That sales pitch only lasts so long as you’re a minority.</p>
<p>Point is: if your opinion gets reception, you’re less likely to change your opinion. This is a problem in politics for people who espouse something for a long time.</p>
<p>Instead we should be like Galileo: show me the data.</p>
<p>So be cautious if people like your opinion because you may be at risk of not being able to change it, either through your own evolving greed or desire for social acceptance and popularity.</p>
<p>The reception of an idea doesn’t determine its truthfulness, but the ability of the idea to stand on its own.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-galileo-stars.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Look for the evidence, not the popularity</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I always try to think about this when listening to a popular author or podcaster: what about their idea has garnered popularity? Have they changed course in the face of evidence? I recall Amy Cuddy having one of the most popular Ted talks on Power Poses, only to have a Slate article come out that refused her research. She doubled down despite her research not being reproducible: the gold standard a scientist should seek.</p>
<p>Few people are like Amy Cuddy in that their ideas cannot be easily tested and so the world lazily believes them. This is the risk: when people stop thinking for themselves.</p>
<p>Things why Frank Herbert wrote <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>: to encourage people to think for themselves and not put too much trust in their leaders.</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="../goals/2024-01-17.html">2024-01-17</a> update:</p>
<p>Chapter 14 of <a href="../book-review/the-quest-for-cosmic-justice.html">The Quest for Cosmic Justice</a> discusses this way better than I do here.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <category>social media</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-problem-with-public-opinions.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 22:19:58 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>You can plan your life in 5 minutes</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/you-can-plan-your-life-in-5-minutes.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It doesn’t take 30 years to plan a good life. It’s actually quite simple and if you sit down for 5 minutes you can figure out the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>do you like where you’re at? Heading? No? Where do you want to go? Why? What do you need to change to get there?</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it.</p>
<p>No fancy grand vision. No elaborate planning. Just maybe 15 minutes to plan ahead.</p>
<p>The speed of planning is 0.01% of the effort required to execute. “We’re going to the moon by the end of the decade”. Plan. Done. Execution is hard.</p>
<p>Ideas are fleeting. Plans are changeable. Plans and ideas aren’t the IP of your company. It’s the people and the execution. Thats the hard part.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-sunrise-on-hike.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">We’ve been to the moon. Now let’s go to the sun.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>purpose of life</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/you-can-plan-your-life-in-5-minutes.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 22:44:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Junk attracts Junk</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/junk-attracts-junk.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Ever throw the shoes <em>by</em> the shoe rack? Or leave <em>one</em> dish in the sink? You know what happens: an avalanche.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-one-bowl.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">All it takes is one bowl</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Badly formatted code attracts more badly formatted code.</p>
<p>But the same is for good: a clean floor makes you want to keep it clean.</p>
<p>So what explains the fulcrum - where is the balance between accepting dire straights vs pushing for perfection? We oscillate between these worlds as our attention wanders.</p>
<p>I’m guessing the fulcrum is based on incentives. Guests coming over? Clean up the house. Boss reviewing? Clean the code.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>laws of human nature</category>
  <category>observations</category>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/junk-attracts-junk.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 00:07:09 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Biden’s debt relief won’t relieve what he thinks it will</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/bidens-debt-relief-wont-relieve-what-he-thinks-it-will.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Reading <a href="../book-review/the-quest-for-cosmic-justice.html">The Quest for Cosmic Justice</a>, Sowell points out repeatedly how policies focused on helping a target demographic may not only hinder them, but those around them too. Policies are for politicians to pursue power, to win the next vote.</p>
<p>What good does relieving <a href="https://www.ed.gov/news/press-releases/biden-harris-administration-announces-additional-9-billion-student-debt-relief">130bn</a> in university debt do?</p>
<p>the argument is that our system is broken. So we’ll fix it with money.</p>
<p>The more flawed thinking is that “education is a right.” Should this be true, then food is a right. Then social media is a right. Our phones are a right.</p>
<p>Life is a right. Liberty, and the pursuit of happiness, too.</p>
<p>But my decision to go 200k in debt for an investment that didn’t return dividends (hence my inability to pay), is not a right. It’s a poor investment choice.</p>
<p>Sending out money signals a poor precedence, apart from the blatant desire to buy votes. The economics aren’t aligned. The incentives are bad.</p>
<p>“Go learn about something, investing 4 years, and discover it’s not capable of helping you earn wages” is nothing more than a sabbatical.</p>
<p>We need to spend that money incentivizing innovation. Entrepreneurs. People who create value.</p>
<p>The “educated” masses (3.6m) who cannot afford to pay their debt, when they scoffed at tradespeople who were employable the moment they finished their 3 week training, and then asked those tradespeople to pay for their schooling, is disappointing.</p>
<p>We need to think about incentives, both long and short term.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-robinhood-stealing.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">At some level the government stole from the uneducated to pay for the unemployable ‘educated’</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The solution: student loan officers should be on the hook to ask “what is your potential income return?” The loan must be payable within 8 years at a 10% additional tax on their wages. They need to be able to survive with this 10% tax, and the 10% tax over 8 years should be sufficient to pay the bills.</p>
<p>So if you have a $100k job, that’s $80k education. 10% tax for 8 years is 10k per year to pay the debt.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>politics</category>
  <category>economics</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/bidens-debt-relief-wont-relieve-what-he-thinks-it-will.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2024 21:33:05 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cool Quarto Site</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/cool-quarto-site.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Quarto lists a <a href="https://quarto.org/docs/gallery/">gallery</a> of things you can do with it.</p>
<p>This post illustrates</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>How you can array your blog</li>
<li>How you can collect subscribers with just google form</li>
<li>How you can iframe other apps, such as from huggingface.</li>
</ol>
<p>I came across this site: <a href="https://forbo7.github.io/" class="uri">https://forbo7.github.io/</a>. I enjoyed seeing how they arrayed their blogs, which I had never seen before - they used grids.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/quarto-demo-forbo7-landing.png" class="preview-image img-fluid"></p>
<p>They use an embedded google form for subscriptions:</p>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/screenshot-quarto-demo-forbo7-subscribe.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>And they have an<a href="https://forbo7.github.io/web_apps/apps/flood_detector.html">iframe on a Huggingface</a> app to show something cool:</p>
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/quarto-demo-forbo7-huggingface.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>That’s all.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>quarto</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>coding</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/cool-quarto-site.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 14:44:29 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The six hour sandwich</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-six-hour-sandwich.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>“Avocado and turkey over ciabatta, it’s a delicious way to start your day and fills you up for about six hours.”</p>
<p>That last part - six hours…I had never heard such a sales pitch from a deli person in my life.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-avocado-sandwich.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Six hour sandwich</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>But it’s the perfect sales pitch. Because I care how full I’m going to get off a $13.00 breakfast sandwich. But he just amortized the cost for me - implicitly stating it’s only $2.16/hr for 6 hours.</p>
<p>Would I pay $2 to not be hungry for an hour? I’m not sure what other snack (maybe a .60c banana) can fill me up for an hour.</p>
<p>Genius.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>sales</category>
  <category>life musings</category>
  <category>people I meet</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-six-hour-sandwich.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 08:29:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What’s your decision framework?</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/whats-your-decision-framework.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Annie Duke asks the question “how do you make decisions? What’s your framework?” (<a href="../book-review/how-to-decide-simple-tools-for-making-better-choices.html">How to Decide: Simple Tools for Making Better Choices</a>)</p>
<p>She remarks that many people don’t have one. Many CEO’s just go off their gut.</p>
<p>I encountered this in my investing days (ahem, internship). I lead a discussion on a paper I had read about how emotions affect our judgment and investment decisions.</p>
<p>I proposed an idea: that the investors should make a spreadsheet with labels on their feelings for that decision. They can use this as further information later on when evaluating their buy/sell/holding decisions.</p>
<p>I was laughed out of the room.</p>
<p>“Hey! Why don’t we all get some mood rings?!” Well, that guy (the boss) was later fired, but that’s not the point.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-unhappy-investor-vector.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Don’t let your emotions cloud your judgment.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Point is: if you think you’re making decisions independent of your emotions, you’re incredibly mistaken. Judgment is based off reason and gut. Decisions usually rely on gut though. You have to “feel good”.</p>
<p>I had seen this boss make many decisions without explaining his thinking. “Hold.” Why? The company is tanking per reports. “Sell”, but this one’s looking good!</p>
<p>The point is nobody could replicate his decision making. Half the time it felt arbitrary.</p>
<p>Only later did I learn that one of the most famous investment company, Bridgewater Capital, does this very thing. It’s not for everybody, nor do I do it, but I think it’s a good idea 😄. # proposal</p>
<p>Make a spreadsheet for your decisions.</p>
<ul>
<li>What to decide</li>
<li>Description</li>
<li>Decision: what you chose</li>
<li>Rationale: why you chose it</li>
<li>Facts: supporting facts</li>
<li>Emotional Reasoning: how you “felt” about it.</li>
</ul>
<p>Do this for all decisions: even the “hold” decisions (maintain status quo). Because decision to not change course is a decision in and of itself.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>insights from books</category>
  <category>investing</category>
  <category>memories</category>
  <category>personal stories</category>
  <category>emotional intelligence</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/whats-your-decision-framework.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 13:42:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Organization and Minimalism</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/organization-and-minimalism.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It’s hard to be a minimalist as a parent. Or as…a human…in this economy. We all want more stuff.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-bear-with-messy-stuff.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">When in doubt, toss it out</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>With a small living space and a growing family I’ve grown accustomed to throwing stuff out. I grew up in a bigger house than I have now so there was space for everything. Now there’s space for very little. It’s actually a great feeling because I know what’s in every box (after doing some deep cleaning over winter break).</p>
<p>I remember helping a friend move in high school. Endless hoards of products, products, products. Three moving trucks. Why? I wondered.</p>
<p>My philosophy now is: RAM and Hard drive.</p>
<p>RAM: the random access memory. The things you see when you open doors affect your brain state. Your brain can only hold so much. If you live in clutter you have clutter. So the things you see in your house should reflect what you can hold in memory.</p>
<ul>
<li>Toys should have a theme (blocks, action figures, doll house). If it doesn’t match a theme, it’s gone (begone random slap bracelet! “Afuera!!!”, (quote from new Argentine President))</li>
<li>Things you see should be things you use. Don’t use flower every day? Don’t have it in the pantry. Put it in the corner thing. Cereal every day? Put that front and center.</li>
</ul>
<p>Then long-storage is the hard drive. It’s about keeping stuff you know you’ll want. This is easier to say than do.</p>
<ul>
<li>Holiday decoration? (Theme) keep those in the attic, out of sight out of mind. But when you need it you know where it is.</li>
<li>You get the point.</li>
</ul>
<p>The same goes for code. Maintenance and search cost increase as you add garbage. When it doubt, delete code. Afuera!!</p>
<p>When in doubt, “afuera!!”</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1fXr95TcSxY?si=dVxufSBO5XWz5gX0" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>minimalism</category>
  <category>organization</category>
  <category>software</category>
  <category>parenting</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/organization-and-minimalism.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 10:38:11 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Becoming an expert is kind of a fallacy</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/becoming-an-expert.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Just watched this clip:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/I2ZK3ngNvvI?si=p4BCDVMWKBoc4KJQ" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Important discussion points: as a novice you’re worried about where to go or picking the wrong thing.</p>
<p>I remember not taking an opportunity to learn C++ because “that’s not what I want to do”. In another occasion I wanted to learn PySpark over SQL because Python…</p>
<p>While I don’t regret that choice per se, because I chose something else I was interested in, I’ve largely come to realize that I don’t care what programming language I’m using. I care about getting the job done.</p>
<p>Also, I’m probably over the 10,000 hours of <em>something</em>, I just don’t know what. Am I an ML expert? Data expert? SQL? Python? R?</p>
<p>Is it the application of the skill that makes you an expert? I’m not sure. Because I think novices can do some incredible things if they hone in.</p>
<p>If you read one book on a topic, you’re by no means an “expert”, but you probably know more about that topic than 99% of the nation. I learned this when I spent 6 months diving into the home security industry for my first job. Pretty sure I knew more about that than anyone I spoke to. Was I an expert? I really only had maybe 300 hours. Maybe I was inexperienced. Sure.</p>
<p>And who spends literally 10,000 hours on any one thing? Like 10,000 hours on XGBoost? Image classification? Deep learning? Machine learning? A/B testing? Spreadsheets? Generalist vs specialist, etc. if you’re an ML scientist at Google, you worry about very different things than an ML scientist at a startup. At a startup, you worry about your bigquery allocation and pipeline failures. At Google you worry about what your 5th skip VP is going to deprecate that month.</p>
<p>That’s just the nature of education. There are so many things in the world to know…that being an “expert” is a relative thing. But I agree that working hard and learning useful things helps you innovate faster.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-rocky-balboa-expert.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">I’d change my opinion on being an expert if I needed to beat Rocky.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Last thing, the crux is: don’t compare yourself to others. Compare yourself to yourself. That’s how you assess your progress.</p>
<p>But I’d argue: why even compare yourself to yourself? Compare your solution to the problem. Does it matter if you have 10,000 hours? No.&nbsp;What matters is if the solution fits. This is why innovations and disruptions come from unexpected places: because novices can nail solutions.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>personal development</category>
  <category>growth</category>
  <category>grit</category>
  <category>life lessons</category>
  <category>data science</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/becoming-an-expert.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 22:55:24 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mark Cuban Mogul Support</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/mark-cuban-mogul-support.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Great video, I’ve always loved mark cuban:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ko5AJh2J4xU?si=kHeFPMXe5oCAxQXn" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<ul>
<li>read, be curious, adapt, sell.</li>
<li>Get a sales job. → if money is coming in, you can do anything. There is no company without sales</li>
<li>Use the simpler word. No cohort. Just “group”.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/photo-mark-cuban-youtube.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Mark!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>entrepreneurship</category>
  <category>YouTube clip</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/mark-cuban-mogul-support.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 21:47:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Write a thousand songs</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/write-a-thousand-songs.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I listened to an interview with Imagine Dragons. The lead singer talked about how he writes several songs per day.</p>
<p>No wonder he’s so successful. Repetitions breeds opportunity.</p>
<p>This has two affects on the brain. 1) lowers the pressure of individual songs. Don’t need to knock it of the park. 2) you get better at writing that much faster.</p>
<p>I heard once about a photography that let one half of the students only take 5 photos in a semester. The other half had to take 100. Which group had the better photos?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>You miss 100% of the shots you don’t take. <del>Wayne Gretzky</del> Michael Scott</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-hockey-shots-surreal-impressionist-water.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">More shots is more opportunities for a goal. Worry about good shots later.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>creativity</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/write-a-thousand-songs.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 15:10:01 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>When Leaders Lose their People</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/losing-to-yesmen.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In a scene in <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>, Paul notices that his warrior turns into his worshipper. He laments the loss, wondering if his non-religious warrior will be lost too.</p>
<p>Being a worshipped means you’re worshipped. Unchallenged. Can do no wrong. As such, you’re left with the intellect of one.</p>
<p>As a leader, you need to avoid worshippers. People who fail to challenge you out of fear or an abundance of praise. This all has to do in the decisions you make as a leader. The culture you decide to build. Is every voice heard, or does one voice rule them all?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-king-one-voice-to-rule.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">One voice to rule them all</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/losing-to-yesmen.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 14:31:39 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Multiverse of Careers</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-multiverse-of-careers.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Spoken about in <a href="../tech/dreaming-software.html">The Dream State of Software</a>, Paul of <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a> has a moment where he’s both past and present in his mind. He doesn’t know even whether he’s had his kid or not.</p>
<p>In a podcast I listened to lately on happiness, one suggestion was to write out all your goals and cross them off from day one. Pretend like it doesn’t even matter if you accomplish them. This helps free you.</p>
<p>Careers are like both of these things. We want everything. We can pretend like we have it. We can come to terms with it. And we can say “doesn’t matter if I don’t get that, because I’ve got a life outside my career.”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-multiverse-of-choice.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Which path you choose isn’t as important as who you choose as companions</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Consider your career from your deathbed (<a href="../posts/my-tombstone.html">My Tombstone</a>). What path did you take that mattered? What were all the alternate realities and multiverses you could have had.</p>
<p>Put them all together. In one multiverse you’ve been fired. In another you end up getting insanely wealthy. In another you start your own company. In another you become an online blogger.</p>
<p>All of them can’t be true when you do this exercise extensively enough. And choosing which one probably doesn’t matter as much (right vs wrong path thinking). If you’ve ever left a job you realize that nothing really comes over with you. Most relationships at work are short lived and contextual, like your relationships in high school. And that’s life.</p>
<p>Happiness is perhaps being okay with not having everything you desire, except for the few things that are truly attainable: peace with God, self, and cherished relationships.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <category>deathbed meditation</category>
  <category>career</category>
  <category>decisions</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/the-multiverse-of-careers.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 13:00:31 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>30 Seconds is All You Get</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/30-seconds-for-payment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Apple iTunes changed the music industry forever with one simple decision: the preview of a song should be 30 seconds long.</p>
<p>This little change dramatically altered how music sounds today. I’ve recently listened to some bangers that were only 90 seconds long. They left me hanging.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-listening-to-music-colorful.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Enjoy the music while it lasts</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Why was my song so short? Because nobody gets paid after 30 seconds.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Apple’s decision made artists want to have more interesting 30 seconds in the iTunes Store</li>
<li>That evolved into: an artist doesn’t get paid if you don’t listen at least 30 seconds. And they don’t get paid any more if you listen 31 or 900 seconds. In fact, they get paid more if you listen to two songs, 30s a piece.</li>
</ol>
<p>Spotify, Amazon, YouTube, Apple, etc all pay based on views. They each define views their own way, but they need to negotiate with the labels who already decided to agree to Apple’s 30s schemes in the early 2000’s. They may have different payment schemes, but some have a scheme of “take all revenue, distribute it according to the artist’s share of views.” So if I pay $10/mo for Spotify and don’t use it, my money goes to someone I didn’t listen to.</p>
<p>So how do small artists compete? They’ve got to build their following. Proportionally, the major artists (rather, their labels) soak up all the streaming royalties.</p>
<p>What would be more fair is if my $10 went to the artists I actually listened to, as if I bought their music.</p>
<p>Why does any of this matter? Algorithms. Optimization. Monetization.</p>
<p>Incentives drive outcomes. How we designed our music payment incentives altered music forever (try to be super catchy for 30s). Now, with AI, music can be created much faster which will dilute the pool.</p>
<p>In the end, one simple decision changed billions of lives. 30s? That’s all you need to get paid.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>music</category>
  <category>economics</category>
  <category>incentives</category>
  <category>posts</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/30-seconds-for-payment.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My Tombstone</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/my-tombstone.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>They call it a death meditation, to look back from the end of your life and reflect as if you had just died (out of body style). Here’s my tombstone:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Here lies Bryan, son of Aragon, data scientist extraordinaire who knew how to use regular expressions and properly test linear regression assumptions</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Seem like a good tombstone?</p>
<p>Why do we measure our lives by something nobody cares about? Consider Steve Jobs, Isaac Newton, or whomever you idolize. What are they known for? Only a few things.</p>
<p>I read <a href="../book-review/steve-jobs-biography.html">Steve Jobs (Biography)</a> a while back. And I also read <a href="../book-review/leonardo-da-vinci.html">Leonardo da Vinci</a>. First was 25 hours, second was 17 hours. And guess what - that’s less than two days combined. Two “impressive” lives summed up in a few days.</p>
<p>My grandma’s obituary was brief. Yet her life was filled with millions of unwritten sentences - many written on my life. The in between moments. The laying around moments. The relationship moments. (Maybe it’s called a relation-“ship” because it sails the waters of life continuously, despite the infrequent dock postings.)</p>
<p>Nobody’s going to remember me, except those who call me dad, husband, brother, son, and friend. And I’m okay with that. I was never that good at data science anyway 😉.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-data-scientist-tombstone-on-beach.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">If I’m going out as a data scientist, at least my resting spot will be cool</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>mortality</category>
  <category>work</category>
  <category>work life balance</category>
  <category>perspective</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <category>priorities</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/my-tombstone.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Your Mood is Contagious</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/your-mood-is-contagious.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-mood-sharing.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Moods flow. Keep the negative waves at bay</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There’s no question that moods are contagious. I once asked someone at the beach to leash their dog, and they slightly rebuked me, “this is a dog friendly beach.” <em>Well, so it is,</em> I thought, grumpily. I complained to a family member about this grumpy dog owner.</p>
<p>Moods escalate. And negative moods are even more pervasive and contagious than positive ones. They say a disgruntled customer tells more friends and family than happy ones. Why is this?</p>
<p>In the “Black Cat” (<a href="../book-review/the-best-of-edgar-allen-poe.html">The Best of Edgar Allen Poe</a>), Poe describes a gruesome tale man who wanted to do evil just for the sake of it. That it’s in his nature. Not because you want to do the thing, but because you want to do a forbidden thing. The same goes the other way, for sure. But I think we trend slightly pessimistic because being an optimist is more beneficial, more rewarding and therefore more difficult.</p>
<p>A leader once told me when I was managing a team, “They’ll pick up on <em>everything</em> you do or say.” Oddly, I was picking up on what he was saying.</p>
<p>So when you lead, lead carefully. Whether in home or work, lead with kindness, compassion, and restraint. Speak three kind words before a negative. Ask to understand before assuming. Lead as a servant. It takes all the effort to overcome negative vibes, and who better equipped than the leader to do it?</p>
<p>Don’t be Moriarty:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ncbEucjsNFU?si=rYhBqqavn4Nergap" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>“Why can’t you be more hopeful for a change?”</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <category>parenting</category>
  <category>emotional resilience</category>
  <category>grit</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/your-mood-is-contagious.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Emotional Recovery</title>
  <dc:creator>Bryan Whiting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/emotional-recovery.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Imagine you just ran a red light at 10:15pm. You were driving without music or phone distractions, you just zoned out and coasted through.</p>
<p>Your emotions run high as you consider what might have happened otherwise. But nothing happened. Something <em>could</em> have happened, but nothing did. In the end, all is well.</p>
<p>How do you calm yourself down? In <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>, someone almost dies because of Paul’s “mistake”. But nobody died.</p>
<p>Life is full of thousands of these things. Several of them we recognize and brush off “oh that was close.” But how many events go unnoticed because we were unaware we even could have done harm (no red light to be found)?</p>
<p>How we identify and recover is a skill. How do you process such experiences? How do you get over the person who cuts you off on the highway? How do you get over not realizing you cut someone off?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-red-light-night.png" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">The red lights of life</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>posts</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/posts/emotional-recovery.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
