<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Bryan Whiting</title>
<link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.515</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 23:49:54 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>This drug is habit forming</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/this-drug-is-habit-forming.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Sometimes they tell you that at the pharmacy: “this drug is habit forming”. Or, the saline nasal spray bottle thing I tried once, “this spray is refreshing, but not habit forming.” Oh, how nice.</p>
<p>Why doesn’t everything have this distinction? Driving in the car: non habit forming. Eating a bag of goldfish when I’m noodling on a work problem: def habit forming.</p>
<p>One time, someone put a candy jar with skittles right beside my desk. It was for the whole floor, but my consumption was certainly not a pro-rata share. Buggy code? Gimme some skittles. Habit formed.</p>
<p>Social media? Someone likes your post? Habit formed.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-habit-forming-drug.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Ironically Dalle put “habit farming”, which is kinda what social media is</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Why don’t they warn that social media is one of the most addictive digital things we do? That we’ve just accepted as a society?</p>
<p>It took until 1964 before the surgeon general announced smoking caused cancer. The first cigarette machine was invented in 1881 by Albert Bonsack. That’s +80 years, not to mention it was popular for much longer before that.</p>
<p>So yes, society can get it wrong for many years before they change course and do the more healthful thing.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>social media</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/this-drug-is-habit-forming.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 23:49:54 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Matrix: Social Media’s Influence on Human Interaction</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/the-matrix.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Have you ever been alone in a crowded room?” - Dark Blue, Jack’s Mannequin</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I know kung fu - Neo, “The Matrix”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What do these to quotes have in common? Social Media.</p>
<p>Everyone on social media is downloading something. They do it because they want to learn kung fu. And while they’re not on social media, other people are getting the download even more.</p>
<p>Something strange happens once you start spending 3+ hours on social a day. You start to see what’s actually going on. You start getting the cross-internet jokes. And once you do, you feel alone in a crowded room: you get the jokes that nobody else in your family gets. (Presumably because they have lives not on social media.)</p>
<p>Detach from social (<a href="../tech/a-knife-to-a-gun-fight.html">A Knife to a Gun Fight: Why I’m off Social Media</a>) and you start to see something else: when you’re not on your phone at a party, you start to see <em>just</em> how much everyone is on social. Checking their SMS, their posts, etc. That’s when you really feel alone in a crowded room.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-alone-in-a-crowded-room.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Alone in a crowded room</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>social media</category>
  <category>digital minimalism</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>modern living</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/the-matrix.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 23:33:03 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Knife to a Gun Fight: Why I’m off Social Media</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/a-knife-to-a-gun-fight.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Tim Ferris describes why he doesn’t have social media on his phone:</p>
<div class="quarto-video"><video id="video_shortcode_videojs_video1" class="video-js vjs-default-skin vjs-fluid" controls="" preload="auto" data-setup="{}" title=""><source src="<https://youtu.be/_Fn-giKevmo?si=f1Lz9H2U08BQhKwv>"></video></div>
<p>I recently deleted social media from my phone 14 days ago. I had been using Instagram until April when I quit and Twitter all year. I realized within days how much better I felt without social media. Happier. Legitimately happier.</p>
<p>And why? What do I get out of it? I’m not growing closer to friends. That’s what texting and calling and spending time in person does. But I’d argue even texting doesn’t really strengthen a relationship because it’s so hard to properly interpret emotions and cues via text: you interpret them how you read those texts. You interpret it according to your emotional state, not the sender’s.</p>
<p>Phone provides vocal emotional cues. Body language another set of emotional cues. I can get probably 70% of this out from FaceTime or <a href="../gratitude/zoom.html">Zoom</a>. But being in person is what we’re meant for.</p>
<p>This is why we strengthen relationships locally, and fail to continue ones from high school or our previous job.</p>
<p>So what was I doing on social media? Watching clips of either strangers I don’t care about or college associates I friended (once lived locally with) that I no longer talk to.</p>
<p>So what’s the knife you’re bringing to the gun fight? When at YouTube I heard the CEO praise a team for increasing “seconds watched” by 15% by reducing the lag of the swipes between YouTube shorts (TikTok clone). The lag reduction was in the milliseconds. Your attention is being bought and manipulated by the shareholders of these companies.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-knife-gun-fight.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Yes, they’re targeting specifically you. You don’t stand a chance. And you have a pocket knife, and you’re 50 feet away. Who’s gonna win?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>They A/B test everything. This isn’t morally wrong. It’s actually quite human: we all A/B test everything every day. A joke here. A smile there. We put out feelers and see if we get a reaction. Don’t believe me? Ask my kid why he keeps throwing things in the toilet!</p>
<p>Billions of dollars and the brightest minds on earth are working at FAANG. Why? They need to provide for their families and academics doesn’t pay. Non-profits don’t pay. This isn’t immoral, it just is. There are very good people working there: honest, moral people. Some of the best I’ve seen in the industry. But when you get paid to maximize swipes, you maximize swipes. It’s just human nature. And some of them buy into the odd notions of “snackable content”, as if swiping for 30 minutes while on the toilet is what anyone wakes up excited to do. Keep on snacking…</p>
<p>Social media and Netflix provide a ton of value to the world in my opinion. I can use them to call anyone I want, raise money for a cause, or get likes on a cute pic of my cat (I don’t have a cat). I <em>do</em> see the value.</p>
<p>But the costs for me have outweighed the value.</p>
<p>I <em>do</em> miss laughing about some random Reel. There’s nothing that can get you laughing faster than a 10 second clip paired with the right cuts and music and everything. The right meme just nails it in a way nothing else can. I miss seeing memes from my friends. But when all I do is send memes to these friends, is that a friendship?</p>
<p>Since being off social media I feel like my senses have grown. I now find my kids a lot funnier, my wife funnier, and I’m able to make heavy situations lighter much easier.</p>
<p>There’s a quote in <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a> that’s something like “If you rely only on your eyes, your other senses weaken”. I’d argue my other relationships weakened too. Time to leave the fight. I was losing.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>personal experiments</category>
  <category>A/B testing</category>
  <category>social media</category>
  <category>big tech</category>
  <category>incentives</category>
  <category>decisions</category>
  <category>relationships</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>emotional intelligence</category>
  <category>purpose of life</category>
  <category>digital minimalism</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/a-knife-to-a-gun-fight.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 11:24:09 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AI won’t replace us. We’ll always create.</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/ai-will-not-replace-human-creativity.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I recently got back into writing some poems. <a href="../creative/poem-the-dove-forevermore.html">The Dove (Forevermore)</a> was fun to write. After the fact, I tried getting ChatGPT to create something similar. I only tried once before declaring victory.</p>
<p>Why is this poem meaningful to me? Because it has my soul in it. It’s the summation of my experience as a parent. Should you find it interesting, perhaps that’s why.</p>
<p>Reading <a href="../book-review/the-best-of-edgar-allen-poe.html">The Best of Edgar Allen Poe</a> recently I’m amazed (besides how depressing he is) at how excellent a writer he is. He peers into the mind and soul and extricates anything interesting. It’s interesting because a human wrote it.</p>
<p>Do we still paint, even if a camera can take a picture? Do we still ride bikes and horses even with cars and things? Do we still read even though we have TV and movies?</p>
<p>Words. Creative expression. They will always be interesting to us. Humans are interesting to us. Stories. Social acceptance is a fundamental human need. We desire connection. We’ll like reading something because a human wrote it.</p>
<p>But what about that guy I heard about who makes a ton of money using ChatGPT to create fake digital books on Amazon. People don’t <em>know</em> it’s AI-written. Digital GenAI images now are insanely accurate - it’s only 2024. It’s very possible great AI art will inspire us more than non-AI art (whatever that means because everyone uses photoshop anyway).</p>
<p>I’m not saying we won’t find value in AI art (creative writing, digital, video, etc.). We will. It’s clear we’ll have a really hard time knowing what’s human vs not.</p>
<p>But I am saying that creativity will never disappear. We’re always going to be interested in creating - even if machines can do it better. Machines can beat us at Go and StarCraft (<a href="../posts/2023-12-25-ai-robots-are-mastering-tasks-faster-than-humans-/index.html">AI Robots are mastering tasks faster than humans</a>), but we’ll still play. Because what else will there be to do?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-leonardo-painting-the-mona-lisa.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">I guess I’ll pick up painting now…</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>futurism</category>
  <category>humanity</category>
  <category>creativity</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/ai-will-not-replace-human-creativity.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 23:21:29 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What startups and musicians have in common</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/what-startups-and-musicians-have-in-common.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I was reminded of a video I watched a while back on YouTube. It was a great documentary about these new artists and their debate about whether to sign a record label (there’s a recent trend to selling music as an independent artist).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-musician-signing-record-label-watercolors.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Putting pen to ink</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I forget all the details, but there are some roughly insane trends that are generally interesting as I recall:</p>
<ul>
<li>new record labels are for $500k give or take. This is so the artist can invest a year into their music and get an album out, pay for production, etc.</li>
<li>many artists at that early stage aren’t financially literate and end up wasting the (they’re musicians, not bankers)</li>
<li>Some have to pay back the money</li>
<li>Up to 85% of the streaming royalties are owed to the label (started when streaming became a thing)</li>
<li>Labels also take a large portion of touring revenues now (something that wasn’t common 10 years ago)</li>
</ul>
<p>Why is this similar to tech startups? Lots.</p>
<p>Musicians have to find product market fit. They need to find their customers. Their monthly listeners.</p>
<p>They need to keep them coming back.</p>
<p>They need to differentiate.</p>
<p>Those who are customer focused and build a following are those who succeed. (Money in the bank and relying too much on the label can cripple you)</p>
<section id="the-musicians-in-town" class="level1">
<h1>The Musicians in Town</h1>
<p>I remember hanging out with some new artists while I was running my startup (we both used the same videographer). I couldn’t help but notice how similar the dynamics were. The founders. The first hires (replacements). The convos about who gets what. It’s all very fascinating.</p>
<p>Not much else to say.</p>


</section>

<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>startups</category>
  <category>music</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/what-startups-and-musicians-have-in-common.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 20:53:53 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The future wave of AI hype</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/the-future-wave-of-ai-hype.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Reading about Airplane’s failure per OnlyCFO. A few notable quotes:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Airplane’s shutdown and future shutdowns like this will have negative consequences for many early stage companies. For many years buyers of these tools haven’t had to deal with a tool being abruptly killed. It only takes this happening once for you to really second guess purchasing a startup tool that is mission critical, deeply integrated, or would take a long time to replace.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/the-future-wave-of-ai-hype.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 20:32:46 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Dream State of Software</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/dreaming-software.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-dreaming-software.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Dreaming code working is ever coders dream</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I returned from vacation yesterday and tried running my code. It didn’t work. I looked at code I had written, it had my imports correctly and all - why wasn’t it running?</p>
<p>The file it was importing didn’t exist.</p>
<p>I thought I created that. I swear I made it. My coworker remarked, “oh so you set up all the scafffolding but didn’t write the actual code?” I was in disbelief. maybe it was deleted by accident or stashed on another branch. But the <code>git log</code> shows all: the imported file never existed.</p>
<p>In <a href="../book-review/dune.html">Dune</a>, Paul Atriedes has many visions and the author uses this feature to skip the book ahead three years. Paul wakes up one morning and doesn’t know what’s past or future. It’s all one in his mind.</p>
<p>So it is with software. It gets created in the mind near instantly. Coding is a burden, the journey of many failures and design choices to enable the simple vision of the mind.</p>
<p>Perhaps Gen AI can help us dream software faster. I look forward to when my dreams are realities, and not the rude awakening I still have coding to do.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>design</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>futurism</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/dreaming-software.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Psychology of New Software Releases and its Parallels with Fashion</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/why-we-want-new-software.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>What is it about a new release that gets people excited? Would you buy software that never changes? How about a hammer?</p>
<p>Why are we okay with buying a hammer, but not stagnant software? Our culture is addicted to new widgets. A/B testing.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-ship-fashion-software.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">Shipping software like fashion, every season</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Software releases are free, but development is not. Therefore, research and development is constant, whereas the Hammer company hasn’t needed to update its product in a couple…millennia. That’s why they call it software. It’s not hard to make.</p>
<p>Is there a way to sell software like you sell a hammer?</p>
<p>No.&nbsp;Because per <a href="../book-review/innovators-dilemma.html">Innovator’s Dilemma</a>, those who can out-do you will. And software is easy to alter and improve. I’m not convinced all “updates” done in the software industry are actually improvements, but people like change. Ever see a fashion line repeat itself?</p>
<p>Software is like fashion.</p>



<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>business strategy</category>
  <category>saas</category>
  <category>sales</category>
  <category>tech</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/why-we-want-new-software.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Replacing human work with AI</title>
  <link>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/swapping-out-human-labor-for-ai.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In a <a href="https://mitsloan.mit.edu/ideas-made-to-matter/4-questions-to-ask-swapping-out-human-labor-ai">recent MIT article</a>, the author discusses how to know if you’re ready for AI adoption. It boils things down to a rather obvious four-step questioning process:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>How much time would I save if I used AI?</li>
<li>How expensive is the task? (How expensive is the salary of the person doing the task.)</li>
<li>How capable is the AI of completing the task successfully?</li>
<li>How easy is it to determine if the output is good/correct?</li>
</ol>
<p>I say obvious because these are actually just questions you’d ask of any task worth doing by any person at your company. In every decision in running a business, there is an ROI question at play - what does this person cost me, what’s the return?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center page-columns page-full">
<figure class="figure page-columns page-full">
<p><img src="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/img/dalle-ai-task-vs-human.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="margin-caption">It’s not: “should I use AI?” It’s “how?”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="knowing-what-you-dont-know-and-how-to-know-you-know-it" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Knowing what you don’t know, and how to know you know it</h1>
<p>The author lays out the hypothetical “I asked this ChatGPT to write something in Perl and it did it well on the second try!”</p>
<p>Consider that. Do you know what Perl is? Would you know how to evaluate if the code is complete? How would you execute such code - do you know the programs to run?</p>
<p>AI cannot solve these environmental, contextual problems yet. It can’t think through all the nuance. And, if you have an expensive salary, there’s a reason: you have a lot of experience. Experience to know what Perl is. Experience to recognize the code’s flaws and poor design patterns. This makes you all the more valuable <em>with</em> AI.</p>
<p>On the other hand, a highly creative, curious person could just ask AI “what programming languages are good for this task?” Like Neo in <em>The Matrix</em> when he “downloads kung-foo” into his brain, we all can get up to speed a lot faster.<sup>1</sup></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;I’ve read stories of people without technical backgrounds building websites with GPT. On the surface this is cool. Now do they care to keep doing that? Is that their personality? Are they going to get bored? This is the differentiator. And the people who stick with GPT to build a website and remain curious are the ones who will get ahead. Those who give up won’t.</p></li></div></section>
<section id="how-do-i-adopt-ai-not-should" class="level1">
<h1><em>How</em> do I adopt AI? (Not “should”)</h1>
<p>To me, the question isn’t “do these four questions check the box”? Instead, I see AI as an always-on strategy with various ranges of usefulness:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Do you care what the final product looks like?
<ul>
<li>Are you okay with an 80% solution?</li>
<li>Is this throwaway work?</li>
<li>Do you plan to maintain this code as part of a 10,000 line code base?</li>
<li>Do you just need ideas to get started?</li>
</ul></li>
<li>What are the risks in firing my experts?
<ul>
<li>Who will catch the mistakes of the AI? What if it’s wrong?</li>
<li>In many aspects of your business the risk of being wrong might be a lot lower than you think.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>What <em>can’t</em> it do well?
<ul>
<li>Assume AI is doing everything at your company - what would that look like?</li>
<li>Give AI the benefit of the doubt first, then work backward from what it can’t do.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>I think that AI holds great power to aid our jobs in a lot of ways. It <em>will</em> replace a lot of jobs, just as there are far fewer farmers today than a hundred years ago. Those farmers are far more effective than ever before - we get more yield for less. It will replace <em>part</em> of your job - the stuff you know how to do but would rather have someone else do it.</p>
<p>Coders <em>will</em> be highly automatable, especially those who think otherwise. Lawyers. Graphic designers. Marketers. This is a cycle as old as time: people and businesses who think they have a strong hold on the market (think: BlackBerry, <em>Innovators Dilemma</em>) are the ones who always get eclipsed. # Learn the new skillset</p>
<p>Have everyone at your company use it today. It’s the new programming language. It’s the new way of authoring. And yes, prompt engineering (how you ask it questions) widely impacts its usefulness. Therefore, we all need to learn how to prompt engineer.</p>
<p><em>That</em> is the new skillset: <strong>knowing what question to ask and how to pressure test its validity</strong>. In essence, the learning acceleration curve has skyrocketed, and one person can now actually be good at many things a lot faster. It’s the curious person who will win. It’s the visionary. The evaluator. The one who knows where they want to go, can discern if the steps they’re taking are taking them to their destination, and who have the ability to adapt and course correct when necessary.</p>
<p>For now, AI can hardly do things outside data it was trained on. In the future 10 years that may change. If so, we’ll all be on the edge of scientific discovery, pushing the bounds of creative work, and focusing on the nuance that will win/lose that legal case. AI will have a seat at the table. But so will we.</p>


</section>


<p>_________________________ <br> <br> <i><a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/about">Bryan</a> lives somewhere at the intersection of faith, fatherhood, and futurism and writes about <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech">tech</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/books">books</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/christianity">Christianity</a>, <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/gratitude">gratitude</a>, and <a href="https://www.bryanwhiting.com/">whatever’s on his mind</a>. If you liked reading, perhaps you’ll also like subscribing: <br><br> </i><iframe src="https://embeds.beehiiv.com/106e21ff-1989-43d2-9bd7-d4a4c4404ab6?slim=true" data-test-id="beehiiv-embed" height="52" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="margin: 0; border-radius: 0px !important; background-color: transparent;"></iframe></p> ]]></description>
  <category>tech</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>automation</category>
  <category>decisions</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <guid>https://www.bryanwhiting.com/tech/swapping-out-human-labor-for-ai.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
